<repository xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/"      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instanc">
<record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1585</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:43:45Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Regulation of Herpetic Stromal Keratitis: Role of Regulatory T Cells</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Sehrawat, Sharvan</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Herpetic stromal keratitis (HSK) is an immunoinflammatory corneal lesion caused by herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection. One of the dire consequences of which is blindness resulting from tissue destructive immunopathological reaction in corneal stroma. The lesion is considered to be orchestrated mainly by CD4+ T cells of Th1 phenotype. Studies on two animal models viz. immunocompetent and immunodeficient, shed light on the issues on specificity of the cells which at least in immunocomprised TCR transgenic animals were shown to be activated in a bystander manner. However, initial infiltration by innate immune cells in response to replicating virus set the stage for the chronic inflammation in the corneal stroma. Paradoxically, these cells are also critical in the control of virus in the cornea.
The first part (Part I) of this dissertation focuses on the understanding of HSV-1 induced immunoinflammatory processes in the cornea and trigeminal ganglia including the secondary lymphoid tissues and the involvement of regulatory mechanisms. The next three parts (Part II-IV) focus on the control of the inflammatory lesion and anti-inflammatory mechanisms that are activated following virus infection in the lymphoid organs and cornea. Results in Part II evaluate the immunotherapeutic potential of regulatory T cells in controlling the progression of the inflammatory lesions after ocular HSV infection. Results of the third section show that sequestration of T effector cells in the lymphoid organs and limited access to site of inflammation using a drug FTY720 after HSV infection resulted in diminished severity of SK and expansion of antigen-specific regulatory T cells that could contribute to the diminution of lesion severity. The fourth section describes the role of a previously unexplored inhibitory interaction between a Th1 specific cell surface marker, TIM-3 and its ligand galectin-9 in the causation of the viral induced corneal immunopathology. The administration of galectin-9 seemed to be an effective approach to terminate Th1 responses and promote regulatory cells activity thereby controlling the severity of lesions.
In this study, experiments were designed to control the progression of the ongoing inflammatory reaction in the cornea in order to evaluate some of the therapeutic strategies for HSK.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2008-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/517</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008Dissertations/SehrawatSharvan.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>


		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1058</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:43:56Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Histone Deacetylase Inhibitors for Selective Anti-Cancer Therapeutics</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Choudhary, Shambhunath</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Activating mutations of ras genes are frequently found in human cancers. Since Ras proteins and their functions play an important role in tumorigenesis, it is important to develop targeted anticancer therapeutics against Ras-related human cancers. We observed that in addition to tumorigenic ability, oncogenic H-Ras possesses a novel proapoptotic ability to facilitate the induction of apoptosis by histone deacetylase inhibitors (HDACIs), such as FR901228 and trichostatin A (TSA). HDACIs make up a new class of structurally diverse anticancer agents and have been shown to exhibit antimetastatic and antiangiogenic activities toward malignantly transformed cells. We detected that expression of oncogenic H-Ras potentiated intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) in human and mouse cells to enhance HDACI-induced ROS, thereby contributing to the induction of selective apoptosis and caspase activation.
The first part (Part I) of this dissertation focuses on the understanding of Ras proteins, their role in normal and transformed cell physiology, and current treatment options against Ras-related human cancers, as well as the role of HDACIs and ROS in anticancer therapeutics. The next three parts (Part II-IV) focus on revealing the mechanisms for the novel pro-apoptotic ability of oncogenic H-Ras that allow HDACIs to induce selective apoptosis of the oncogenic H-Ras expressing cells. Results in Part II &amp; III verify the pro-apoptotic activity of oncogenic H-Ras in the increased susceptibility of human cancer cells to HDACIs. The caspase pathways, the B-Raf and extracellular signal regulated kinase pathway, p21Cip1 and p27Kip1, and core histone contents are regulated differently by FR901228 in oncogenic H-Ras–expressed cells than their counterparts in parental cells, contributing to the increased susceptibility to the induction of selective apoptosis. Results in Part IV describe the role of reactive oxygen species in the pro-apoptotic ability ofoncogenic H-Ras to enhance the cell susceptibility to HDACIs. Intracellular ROS was cooperatively up-regulated by oncogenc H-Ras and HDACI treatment to induce selective apoptosis of oncogenic H-Ras-expressing cells. The last section (Part V) summarizes the findings with their importance and discusses future directions.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/27</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1058&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1068</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:44:03Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Coronaviral 2’-O-Methyltransferase Function in Virus Replication.</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Dziduszko, Agnieszka</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Primary and higher order RNA structures in the 5’ and 3’ untranslated regions of the genomes of positive-strand RNA viruses are known to function as cis-acting elements for genome translation and replication. Four cis-acting replication elements have been identified in the bovine coronavirus (BCoV) 3’ untranslated region that are postulated to recruit viral and cellular proteins for assembly of the replication complex and initiation of negative-strand synthesis. This study had the goal of identifying and establishing the function of the viral proteins that bind BCoV 3’ terminal cis-acting RNA structures. A major surprising discovery was a specific interaction of the BCoV-encoded 2’-O-methyltransferase (2’-O-MT), an enzyme normally involved in 5’-terminal cap methylation, with a 3’-terminal cis-acting octamerassociated bulged stem-loop. This discovery led to detailed analyses of BCoV 2’-O-MT that is summarized as follows: (i) Enzyme probing revealed the higher-order structure of the cis-acting 3’-terminal bulged stem loop. (ii) Specific binding of the 2’-O-MT to both the 5’ cap-0 structure and to the 3’-terminal bulged stem-loop was documented. (iii) Enhanced translation of a viral genomic RNA was demonstrated as a function of 2’-O-MT methylating activity. (iv) A requirement for 2’-O-MT methylating activity for virus replication was demonstrated with the use of the mouse hepatitis coronavirus reverse genetics system. (v) Over-expression of the viral 2’-O-MT in virus-infected cells had no detrimental in-trans effect on viral genome replication, transcription, or translation, but affected DI RNA accumulation in-cis. These results indicate that the coronaviral 2’-O-MT is essential for virus genome translation and replication and, as a multifunctional protein, is an attractive target for development of an anticoronaviral therapeutic drug.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/36</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1068&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1716</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:44:07Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Malignant Catarrhal Fever Viruses in Tennessee Ruminants</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Cissell, Robin Lynn</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Malignant catarrhal fever (MCF) is a lymphoproliferative and inflammatory syndrome affecting primarily ruminant species.  The disease, which is often fatal, is most often described as affecting bovids and cervids.  No vaccines are available for prevention of MCFV infection.  The primary method to control spread of disease is to prevent contact between carriers and clinically susceptible species.  There is no known method to control infection of malignant catarrhal fever virus-white-tailed deer variant (MCFV-WTD), as the carrier animal of this virus is unknown.
To determine the prevalence of malignant catarrhal fever viruses in Tennessee ruminant populations, blood and/or lymph node samples were collected from farms, animal processing and disposal facilities, and hunter check-in stations from 2006-2008 from several species of animals including cervids, cattle, and goats.  Strain-specific real time PCR was developed to detect ovine herpesvirus-2 (OvHV-2), caprine herpesvirus-2 (CpHV-2), and MCFV-WTD DNA.  MCFV DNA was detected in all species of ruminants sampled.  Although disease related to infection with MCFV-WTD and CpHV-2 has not been reported in Tennessee cattle or cervid populations, MCFV-WTD DNA was detected in 3 percent of cervid samples, and MCFV-WTD and CpHV-2 DNA was detected in 27 and 3 percent respectively of cattle samples from animal disposal facilities that process dead or debilitated animals. One hunter harvested deer (n=781) and 25 cattle (n=165) tested from animal disposal facilities were positive for OvHV-2 DNA.
This study demonstrated that healthy cattle and cervids can be infected with OvHV-2 and MCFV-WTD without apparent disease, and dead or debilitated cattle were infected with OvHV-2, MCFV-WTD and CpHV-2 at a higher percentage than healthy herd animals.  Prevalence of CpHV-2 in Tennessee goat populations (7%) was significantly lower than reported in other goat populations (73%).  Low prevalence of CpHV-2 in Tennessee goat populations likely explains why no evidence of infection was found in cervids tested, and the low prevalence of CpHV-2 infection in dead or debilitated cattle compared to prevalence of infection with OvHV-2 and MCFV-WTD.  The discovery of infection in cattle with CpHV-2 and MCFV-WTD opens a new avenue of investigation into the pathology and virulence of MCFV’s in domestic cattle.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/786</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1716&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>malignant catarrhal fever</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>white-tailed deer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>real-time PCR</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>sheep</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>goats</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Infectious Diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Preventive Medicine, Epidemiology, and Public Health</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1613</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:44:37Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Comparison of Fecal &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; From Dogs and Their Owners</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Stenske, Katherine Anne</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Contact between human beings and dogs may allow sharing of antimicrobial resistant and virulent bacteria. Objectives of this study were to determine the prevalence of cross-species sharing of fecal E. coli based on pulse field gel electrophoresis (PFGE) profile similarity, to compare antimicrobial susceptibility patterns and virulence factor patterns between dog-owner pairs, and to analyze the epidemiology of cross-species sharing using a questionnaire.
A cross-sectional study comparing fecal E. coli isolates from dogs and their owners was conducted. A questionnaire and fecal sample was collected from 61 dogowner pairs and 30 controls. Three E. coli colonies were isolated from each participant and confirmed biochemically. Antimicrobial susceptibility of each isolate was determined via disc diffusion for 17 antimicrobial agents routinely monitored by the National Antimicrobial Resistance Monitoring System. PFGE profiles were used to establish relatedness among bacterial isolates. A multiplex PCR was developed to determine presence or absence of 4 urovirulence factor genes: cnf, hlyD, sfa, and papGIII. The questionnaire asked about medical history, antimicrobial therapy, hygiene, and relationship with dog.
A wide array of PFGE profiles was observed in E. coli isolates from all participants. Within-household sharing occurred with 9.8% prevalence, and acrosshousehold sharing occurred with 0.26% prevalence. No specific behaviors were associated with increased clonal sharing between dog and owner.
No differences were found in susceptibility results or virulence factor patterns between dog-owner pairs. Control isolates were more resistant than canine isolates, and human beings carried more multiple-drug resistant E. coli than dogs. Isolates from owners who did not wash their hands after petting their dogs had increased resistance to ampicillin. An association was found in women between history of UTI and presence of each virulence factor in their dog’s fecal E. coli. Antimicrobial resistance was associated with reduction of virulence factors.
Within-household sharing of E. coli occurred more commonly than acrosshousehold sharing, but both direct contact and environmental reservoirs may be important routes for cross-species sharing of bacteria and genes for resistance and virulence. Cross-species bacterial sharing is a potential public health concern, and good hygiene is recommended.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2008-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/546</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/StenskeKatherineAnne.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Comparative and Laboratory Animal Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1705</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:44:44Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Molecular Targets of Green Tea Catechin, EGCG, on Human Colorectal Carcinogenesis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Sukhthankar, Mugdha G.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This thesis explores the effect of major green tea catechin, EGCG, on colorectal carcinogenesis particularly on target genes, bFGF and NUDT6. Cancer is a second leading cause and colorectal cancer is a third leading cause of deaths in the Western World. Recently there is a lot of persuasive epidemiological and experimental evidence that phytochemical-enriched diet may be involved in the prevention of colorectal cancer. EGCG exhibits beneficial effects like anti-tumorigenic, anti-oxidant, anti-angiogenic, and pro-apoptotic activity.
In studies presented here, we investigated the molecular mechanisms by which EGCG affects bFGF degradation (Chapter 3): EGCG increased the ubiquitination as well as trypsin like activity of 26S proteasome causing faster bFGF degradation. We also demonstrated that EGCG could decrease the tumor number and volume in mouse models of colorectal cancer.
Our microarray data from catechin-treated colorectal cancer cells revealed down regulation of a gene called NUDT6, an anti-sense of bFGF, which we have shown to regulate the bFGF function. NUDT6 is a mitochondrial protein whose biological function is unknown. EGCG affected the mRNA stability of NUDT6 by decreasing the luciferase activity of its 3‘UTR (Chapter 4). NUDT6 stable cells showed increase in cell proliferation and soft agar colony formation. The electrical impedance bio-analytical assay showed increased attachment of NUDT6 cells to the surface media and to each other. NUDT6 cells showed increased invasion rate and decreased Caspase 3/7 activity.
Injection of CONTROL and NUDT6 cells into nude mice complemented the in vitro data showing increase in tumor volume, mitotic index and decrease in caspase activity and apoptotic index. This was possibly due to binding of p53 to NUDT6 which led to degradation of p53. NUDT6 was highly expressed in human colon tumor tissue sample compared to normal and NUDT6 could be used as a marker in colon tumorigenesis.
The findings presented in this thesis clearly show that EGCG is an effective chemopreventive dietary agent, decreasing the expression of pro-angiogenic and cell proliferation genes, bFGF and NUDT6 in colorectal cancer cells. Further characterization of NUDT6 as a potential biomarker in colorectal carcinogenesis may provide a better prediction of disease progression in the future.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/636</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1705&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>


		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1342</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:44:56Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>RNA Interference of the Glycoprotein D and DNA Polymerase Genes of Feline Herpesvirus 1 by Synthetic siRNAs</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Wilkes, Rebecca Penrose</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Feline herpesvirus 1 (FHV-1) is a linear double-stranded DNA virus that causes approximately 50% of the upper respiratory tract infections and produces the most severe respiratory disease in domestic cats. Primary ocular infection, as occurs in humans with the related virus, herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1), consistently produces conjunctivitis and minimal corneal involvement; however, clinical manifestations of disease due to repeated recrudescence involve the cornea and can potentially lead to blindness. Vaccines only produce partial protection from clinical disease, and antiviral medications approved for treatment of HSV-1 in humans are only minimally effective for treatment of the chronic cases in cats. Therefore, RNA interference (RNAi), a RNA-guided gene regulatory mechanism that is found in a variety of eukaryotic organisms and provides anti-viral immunity in plants, was used as a therapeutic method for prevention of FHV-1 infection in feline cells. Previous RNAi experiments in related herpesviruses demonstrated that the DNA polymerase gene and a gene coding for a viral attachment protein are effective targets for inhibiting herpesvirus replication. Therefore, a region coding for highly conserved amino acid motifs of herpesvirus DNA polymerase genes, which is unique to each viral species and lacks DNA sequence drift for alphaherpesviruses, including herpes simplex virus type 2 and also feline herpesvirus as shown in this study, was targeted by RNAi. The attachment proteins for FHV-1 are unknown, but the highly conserved glycoprotein D (gD) gene was also chosen as a target for this study. HSV-1 gD is an essential receptor-binding polypeptide and is necessary for penetration of the virus into cells. FHV-1 gD, an envelope protein, is an inducer of virus-neutralizing antibodies and may play an important role in the restriction of the host range of the virus to feline cells.
Two synthetic siRNAs targeting the DNA polymerase gene and the gD gene of FHV-1 were effective in knockdown of their intended targets by 69-83% for DNA polymerase mRNA and 77-87% for gD mRNA, determined by quantitative real-time RT-PCR. Based on flow cytometry results, glycoprotein D mRNA knockdown decreased gD cell surface expression by 27-43%, and DNA polymerase mRNA interference decreased cell surface FHV-1 glycoprotein expression by 29-71%. Knockdown of the mRNAs from these genes also resulted in decreased infective virus in vitro, with decreased viral replication by 83-96% by DNA polymerase RNAi and 77-84% by gD RNAi, determined by plaque assays. Interference of each mRNA also resulted in a decrease in the amount of the opposite mRNA, independent of interferon β production. These results indicate that FHV-1 glycoprotein D, like its homolog in HSV-1, is essential for in vitro replication and is likely involved with viral attachment and/or penetration, and both this gene and the FHV-1 DNA polymerase gene are suitable targets for RNAi anti-viral treatment. This study lays the groundwork for potential in vivo investigations in cats. Such studies may provide unique insights into the prevention/treatment of herpesvirus infections by RNAi.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/289</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/WilkesRebecca.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1402</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:05Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Induction and Regulation of Herpetic Stromal Keratitis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Sarangi, Pranita Pragnyadipta</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Herpetic stromal keratitis (HSK) is an immunopathological and tissue destructive  corneal lesion caused by herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection, which induces an  intense inflammatory response and finally leads to blindness. Accumulating  evidence using the murine model has shown that Th-1 phenotype CD4+ T cells  orchestrating the inflammation mainly contribute to the immunopathological  reaction in HSV-1 infected cornea. However, prior to CD4+ T cell infiltration into  corneal lesions, various innate immune cells recruit and produce numerous  inflammatory and angiogenic molecules into the corneal stroma those in turn drive  the corneal immunopathology.
The first part (Part I) of this dissertation focuses on the understanding of  HSV-1 induced immunoinflammatory processes in the cornea and trigeminal  ganglia including the secondary lymphoid tissues. The next three parts (Part II-IV)  focus on different inflammatory and anti-inflammatory mechanisms that are  activated following virus infection in the cornea. Results in Part II evaluate the role  of various Toll-like receptors (TLRs) in driving the early inflammatory events that  occur in the HSV infected corneas. Thus, this part demonstrates that mainly TLR2  and to a lesser extent TLR9 ligand activity of HSV is important for driving SK  pathology. Results of the third section show that HSV infection results in the up  regulation of IL-23 that is needed for the survival of pathogenic Th-17 cells. The  data show that mice lacking IL-23 were more susceptible to SK lesions and that the  heightened lesion severity was attributed to higher IL-12 production and Th1  immune response in such animals. The fourth section describes the relative role of IL-10 and natural regulatory T cells (nTregs) as two independent anti-inflammatory  mechanisms that are needed for controlling HSK lesions.
In this study, experiments were designed to understand the mechanisms  involved in the induction and regulation of immunopathology in HSK and  modulation of such processes could be useful in designing therapeutic for HSK.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2008-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/344</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/SarangiPranita.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1848</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:13Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Murine Herpetic Stromal Keratitis: Elucidating the Early Events Involved in its Pathogenesis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Biswas, Partha S</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Herpes simplex viruses (HSV) infection is a common cause of ocular disease and can result in a chronic inflammatory reaction that impairs vision. This latter manifestation is called herpetic stromal keratitis (HSK) and usually occurs as a consequence of virus reactivation from latency in the trigeminal ganglion. The pathogenesis process involves complex interactions of cellular and molecular events. HSK in humans, and certainly its murine experimental model, appears to be an immunopathologic disease process. The crucial cell type orchestrating the inflammation is a CD4+ Tcell that has a Thl cytokineproducing profile. However, prior to this immunoinflammatory phase, multiple events occur that set the stage for subsequent pathology. These include production of cytokines and chemokines, infiltration of innate immune cells and neovascularization of the avascular cornea.
Current understanding about human and murine HSK pathogenesis is reviewed in Part I. Part II progresses this knowledge using knockout and transgenic mice. Results in Part II clarify the essential role of IL-l, a proinflammtory cytokine, produced as a consequence of virus replication, in HSK pathogenesis. Part III, in addition to Part II, elucidate the mechanisms involved in IL-l and IL-6 mediated polymorphonuclear leukocyte (PMN) influx and neovascularization of cornea following virus infection. These cytokines were shown to be produced quite early after infection and capable of inducing angiogenic factors, resulting in angiogenesis of the cornea. In addition, the role of IL-l in inducing proinflammatory arachidonic acid metabolites has been discussed in PART IV. Cycloxygenase 2 enzyme produced from resident corneal cells in presence of IL-l was shown to be crucial for creating an inflammatory milieu and facilitate early PMN influx in murine cornea. These results provide novel insights into the link between viral infections, pro-inflammatory mediators, PMN migration, angiogenesis and HSK development. Our understanding about the role of IL-l in HSK pathogenesis was evaluated clinically in Part V using an IL-l receptor antagonist (IL-l ra) protein. Mice receiving IL-l ra h~d diminished disease severity. The administration of IL-l ra was shown to reduce the influx into the cornea of cells of both the innate and adaptive immune response. In addition, the treatment also diminished corneal VEGF levels resulting reduced angiogenic response. Our results show the iluportance of targeting early proinflammatory molecules such as IL-l to counteract HSK and advocate IL-l ra as an effective agent to achieve this. In Part VI, a novel flow cytometry based assay has been used to quantify corneal angiogenesis following ocular HSV infection. Our results indicate that, this assay was sensitive enough to able to pick up the difference in angiogenic response between mice. Thus, estimation of angiogenesis on the basis of number of endothelial cells proved to be a useful approach to quantify corneal neovascularization.
This dissertation presents research aimed at elucidating both molecular and cellular events in HSK pathogenesis. These results will serve as guidelines for future development of more efficient prophylactic and therapeutic strategies.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2005-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/666</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1848&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2019</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:21Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Diagnosis and Management of Horses with Equine Metabolic Syndrome (EMS)</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Chameroy, Kelly Ann</dc:creator>
<dc:description>In horses, a painful and often debilitating disease known as laminitis can result in impaired function and, in severe cases, euthanasia.  Equine Metabolic Syndrome (EMS) is a syndrome in horses that results in development of laminitis and is characterized by the presence of general and/or regional adiposity (“cresty neck”), aberrations in blood lipid concentrations, insulin resistance (IR) and/ or hyperinsulinemia.  	Therapies have focused on improving the state of obesity and insulin resistance with the goal of diminishing the likelihood of laminitis development.  A definitive cause for laminitis has not been established, but hyperinsulinemia and IR are likely candidates as experimental states of hyperinsulinemia have been shown to induce laminitis and improvements in insulin sensitivity and obesity have been associated with a decreased risk of laminitis development. 	 This dissertation discusses associations between obesity and IR, as well as potential therapies for alleviating insulin resistance with the ultimate goal of decreasing the risk of developing laminitis.  Therapies evaluated included chromium and magnesium, levothyroxine sodium, and metformin hydrochloride.  Horses were treated with each supplement for 10 to 36 weeks, depending on the supplement tested, and physical measurements such as body weight, neck circumference, and body condition score were obtained.  Throughout each study, blood concentrations of glucose, insulin, and plasma lipids were analyzed.  Chromium and magnesium currently do not appear to have any effect on insulin sensitivity, whereas results of levothyroxine administration indicate therapeutic responses, as does metformin, though results indicate further work are required. 	 Research contained in this dissertation focuses on the potential of identifying animals at risk of developing IR and laminitis through measurement of blood biomarkers such as adiponectin and glucagon-like peptide 1.  Assays to measure markers included enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays, western blots, and radioimmunoassays.  Glucagon-like peptide 1 currently does not appear to differ between healthy and IR animals, but protein band density of high-molecular weight adiponectin does appear to be lower in horses with IR when compared to healthy animals.   	 There is still much to learn about IR in horses, and therapy appears to be dependent on a case by case basis.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/871</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2019&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>horse</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>insulin resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>laminitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>equine metabolic syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Animal Sciences</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Large or Food Animal and Equine Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nutritional and Metabolic Diseases</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2031</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:34Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Alternative Splicing in Human Colorectal Cancer</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Bahn, Jae Hoon</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Most human genes undergo alternative splicing, and many abnormal splicing processes are associated with human diseases. However, the molecular relationship between alternative splicing and tumorigenesis is not well understood. Here, we identified novel Krüppel-like factor 4 (KLF4) splicing variants produced by exon skipping in human cancer cell lines as well as colon tumor tissues. To elucidate the mechanism involved in KLF4 alternative splicing, we developed KLF4 minigene system and found that RNA binding motif protein 5 (RBM5) plays an important role in KLF4 splicing, as assessed by gain and loss of functional studies. Several anti-tumorigenic compounds were also tested for KLF4 splicing. Interestingly, sulindac sulfide restored wild type KLF4 (KLF4L) expression and this is mediated by dephosphorylation of RBM5. Another splicing variant, small KLF4 (KLF4S), localizes in the cytoplasm and nucleus, and antagonizes transcriptional activity of wild type KLF4. Our data suggest that RBM5 plays a pivotal role in the alternative splicing of KLF4, and these splicing variant forms may impact tumorigenesis.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/867</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2031&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Alternative splicing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>KLF4</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>RBM5</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>colorectal cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>sulindac sulfide</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cancer Biology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1102</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:49Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Characterization of Feline Adiponectin and its Association with Metabolic Indices in Lean and Obese Cats</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Lusby, Angela Lea</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Adipose tissue secretes over 100 different proteins and cytokines called adipokines. Adiponectin is one of the most intriguing adipokines because it is closely associated with insulin sensitivity and is an early marker for Type-2 diabetes mellitus in human beings. Cats are at risk for developing Type-2 diabetes with obesity, so it is important for researchers to understand the role adipokines, like adiponectin, play in feline metabolism. This project sought to lay the foundation for future research regarding feline adiponectin by sequencing adiponectin cDNA, measuring adiponectin’s expression in various tissues, validating and developing new techniques for measuring adiponectin in circulation, determining the influence of gender on adiponectin concentrations, and by monitoring changes in adiponectin as cats gain and lose fat mass.
The results of this project revealed that adiponectin has a similar cDNA and amino acid sequence to other species and is secreted almost exclusively from adipose tissue. However, cats differed from other species in that visceral adipose tissue had more adiponectin expression than subcutaneous adipose tissue. Serum feline adiponectin was measured using a commercially available murine adiponectin ELISA, and the high molecular weight (HMW) form was detected using gel chromatography combined with ELISA. Neutered male cats may have lower concentrations of total adiponectin than female cats and lower percentages of HMW adiponectin than all other gender groups. Similar to humans, HMW adiponectin was more closely associated with improved glucose metabolism than total adiponectin. HMW adiponectin also correlated more closely with body fat mass than total adiponectin. Despite some unique characteristics, feline adiponectin appears similar in structure and function to adiponectin in other species.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/72</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1102&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2243</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:46:35Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>ROLE OF IL-17 AND TH17 CELLS IN HSV INDUCED OCULAR IMMUNOPATHOLOGY</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Suryawanshi, Amol Sahebrao</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection of the cornea leads to a blinding immuno-inflammatory condition of the eye also called stromal keratitis (SK). SK immunopathology is characterized by the infiltration of CD4+ T cells of Th1 phenotype as well as the development of new blood vessels into the normally avascular cornea. Studies in mouse models of SK have firmly established the role of CD4+ T cells, and particularly of Th1 phenotype, as the principal mediators of SK immunopathology. However, with the recent discovery of IL-17A and Th17 cells, the role of this cytokine as well as Th17 cells remains to be further defined. Recently it was shown that the normal cornea expresses VEGF-A, however its biological activity is impeded by its binding to a soluble form of VEGF-A receptor-1 (sVEGFR-1). Past studies have implicated the role of vascular endothelial growth factor-A (VEGF-A) in HSV induced corneal angiogenesis, however the source of VEGF-A as well as molecular mechanisms, particularly in the context of VEGF-A/sVEGFR-1 balance during HSV infection, are poorly understood.
The first part of this dissertation (I) reviews past literature on HSV induced corneal SK immunopathology. It focuses on the understanding of HSV-1 induced events that particularly results in corneal angiogenesis as well as tissue damage mediated by different type of cells as well as their secreted products. The next three parts (II-IV) focus on the mechanisms of HSV induced corneal angiogenesis as well as the relative role of Th1 and Th17 cells in SK immunopathology. Results in part II focuses on the relative role of IFN-γ/IL-17 as well as Th1/Th17 cells in HSV induced corneal immunopathology. The third section evaluate the significance of VEGF-A/sVEGFR-1 balance in HSV induced corneal neovascularization. Results in part IV focus on the role of IL-17A in altering the balance between VEGF-A and sVEGFR-1 post ocular HSV infection and subsequent corneal angiogenesis.
Collectively these studies identified novel mechanisms by which HSV infection of the cornea leads to the development of angiogenesis as well as corneal tissue damage and subsequent SK immunopathology, the most common cause of infectious blindness in the Western World.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1132</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2243&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>HSV</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>SK</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>VEGF-A</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Angiogenesis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Immunopathology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>IL-17A</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medical Immunology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medical Microbiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Microbiology and Immunobiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Pathology and Pathobiology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1156</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:46:36Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Feline Lentivirus: Molecular Analysis and Epidemiology in Southern African Lions</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Adams, Hayley Rebecca</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Feline immunodeficiency virus is a retrovirus of domestic cats causing significant lifelong infection. Infection has also been detected in nondomestic species, including African lions. It is endemic in certain populations in east and southern Africa. Infection leads to immunologic dysfunction and immunosuppressive disease in domestic cats; however, little research exists about the pathogenic effects of infection in lions and its epidemiological impact on free-ranging and captive populations. Little is known about the lentivirus in these populations at the molecular and host level. Analysis of the virus from these populations is necessary for development of detection assays that are both sensitive and specific.
Whole-blood and serum samples were collected opportunistically from free ranging lions in Kruger National Park, South Africa, and from Hlane Royal National Park, Swaziland. Whole-blood and serum samples were also collected from captive exotic felids in RSA andUS and domestic cats in RSA. A nested polymerase chain reaction assay was performed on all whole-blood samples, and all positive products were sequenced and analyzed phylogenetically. Serum samples were tested for cross-reactive antibodies to domestic feline lentivirus antigens and cross-reactive antibodies to puma lentivirus synthetic envelope peptide antigen. Serum samples were tested for feline haptoglobins and feline alpha-one acid glycoproteins by radial immunodiffusion.
This research represents the first epidemiological study of the lion lentivirus among free-ranging lions of Kruger National Park and the first epidemiological study comparing genetic material to antibody-based methods of lentivirus detection on lions in RSA. The polymerase chain reaction assay was successful in amplifying the lion lentivirus from African lions.
The conservation management of free-ranging lions must consider the infectious agents to which they are susceptible. No conclusions can be drawn from this investigation with respect to the potential virulence or pathogenic distinctions between viral subtypes, as little is known about the definitive consequences of lion lentivirus infection in African lions. Immunologic studies may uncover potential differences in immune expression among lentivirus-positive and -negative individuals with regard to increased resistance or increased susceptibility to infection or pathogenicity. To this end, lion lentivirus infection status could also be compared to the infection status of bovine tuberculosis.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/110</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/AdamsHayley.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Animal Sciences</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Other Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1209</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:46:44Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Characterization and Comparative Analysis of Gene Expression Profiles of Three Different Human Oral Squamous Carcinoma Cell Lines With Different Invasion and Metastatic Capacities</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Erdem, Necip Fazil</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Matrix metalloproteinases (MMP’s) and cathepsins are thought to play key roles in oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) invasion and metastasis. Three OSCC human cell lines, BHY, HN and HSC-3, have been studied based on their reported ability to invade adjacent bone or metastasize to lymph nodes and/or distant organs. The working hypothesis of this study is that OSCC that demonstrate different actions have different proteolytic enzyme and gene expression profiles.
Immunocytochemistry and flow cytometry were used to determine the expression levels of certain proteolytic enzymes. Complementary DNA (cDNA) microarray technique was used to determine the gene expression profiles of each of the three OSCC cell lines.
The immunocytochemistry and flow cytometry results showed that the BHY cell line expresses MMP- 9 and extracellular matrix metalloproteinase inducer (EMMPRIN). The BHY cell line expressed 139 upregulated genes and 117 downregulated genes. The HN cell line expressed 214 upregulated and 262 downregulated genes. Finally, the HSC-3 cell line expressed 128 upregulated and 117 downregulated genes. There were 13 genes that were upregulated and 83 genes that were downregulated in all three OSCC cell lines. Eight pathways were upregulated and 3 pathways were downregulated in the BHY cell line. In the HN cell line 10 pathways were upregulated and 9 were downregulated. Finally, in the HSC-3 cell line 3 pathways were upregulated and 6 pathways were downregulated.
MMP-1, MMP-9 and EMMPRIN appear to play a role in the invasion of OSCC to bone. KIAA, was upregulated in our study in the HN cell line. Upregulation of KIAA may be involved in the late stage of OSSC. PAM gene was the only downregulated gene in the HN cell line. The TM4SF10 gene was downregulated in all three OSCC cell lines. The COL1A2 and COL4A1 genes were upregulated in the HSC-3 cell line and they may cause the lymph node metastasis of OSCC. Based on this study OSCC involves multiple molecular genetic events that take place in many chromosomes and genes. Upregulation of the Jak-STAT signaling pathway may be involved in bone invasion of OSCC. The MAPK signaling pathway was upregulated in all three OSCC cell lines.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/162</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/ErdemNecipFazil.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1056</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:46:44Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Effects of 17- Beta Estradiol on G-Protein Inwardly Rectifying Potassium Channels (GIRKs) in Breast Cancer</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hance, Michael W.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Breast cancer is a leading cause of cancer death and in 2009, the American Cancer Society estimates that over 192,000 new cases of breast cancer will be diagnosed, and over 40,000 women will die from breast cancer. Estrogen (E2) is required for normal female development and reproduction, but long-term exposure is carcinogenic and considered a risk factor for breast cancer. Membrane ion channels are essential for cell proliferation and are suggested to have a role in cancer, especially potassium channels. In the present study, we investigate the effects of estrogen and the estrogen antagonist ICI182780 on G-protein inwardly rectifying potassium channels (GIRK) in estrogen responsive MCF-7 breast cancer cells. GIRK1 and GIRK2 specific channels are thought to play a major role in rapid channel activation. We found increases in GIRK1 and GIRK2 membrane protein levels in response to estrogen treatment, as well as increases in intracellular potassium concentrations and cellular proliferation. ICI182780 treatment increased GIRK1, GIRK2 and GIRK4 membrane protein levels but resulted in an initial decrease in intracellular potassium concentration and decreased cell proliferation. GIRK1 RNAi knockdown decreased estrogen receptor alpha protein levels and activation. In addition, estrogen treatment resulted in increased phosphorylation of specific members of GPCR and MAPK signaling pathways that have been shown to be responsive to GIRK1 knockdown. Using microarray analysis of nontreated and E2 treated MCF7 cells, we observed 489 differentially expressed genes (283 upregulated and 206 downregulated) that were comprised largely of transcription and cell cycle associated genes. This study identified several human cell cycle associated genes that are both responsive to E2 treatment and are functionally correlated with GIRKs. Five genes were selected for further analysis by real time PCR. Our data suggests that specific GIRK channel composition at the cell membrane may be stimulated by estrogen exposure or downstream targets of estrogen signaling and may contribute to increased cell proliferation in MCF-7 breast cancer cells. Taken together, these data add further support of GIRK involvement in cancer progression and identify some potential biological roles of GIRKs in cancer biology beyond the initilal findings of GIRK1 assciation in metastatic breast cancer.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/41</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1056&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medical Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2207</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:47:01Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Immunologic Risk Prediction Model for Kidney Graft Function</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Bishop, Christina Diane</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Clinicians lack appropriate non-invasive methods to be able to predict, diagnose, and reduce the risk of rejection in the years following kidney transplantation. Protocol biopsies and monitoring of serum creatinine levels are the most common methods of monitoring graft function after transplant; however, they have several negative aspects. Use of traditional factors regarding donors and recipients such as Human Leukocyte Antigen (HLA) DNA typing, pre-transplant anti-HLA antibody levels, and basic demographics (age, ethnicity/race, gender), has proved inadequate for post-transplant graft monitoring past the first few years. We propose that by utilizing immunologic factors available to clinicians across the United States, development of a non-invasive model for predicting renal graft outcome will provide a useful tool for post-transplant patient monitoring. We advocate an expanded model which incorporates both the traditional factors, as well as new factors, which have shown promise in predicting kidney outcome and are widely available for testing using commercial kits. These additional factors include major histocompatibility complex class I chain-related gene A (MICA) typing of donor and recipient, degree of matching for killer cell immunoglobulin-like receptors (KIRs) between donor and recipient, detection of MICA antibodies, and soluble CD30 level (sCD30). This proposed graft-function prediction model is the first to include all of these factors.
Using multi-center data from adult recipients of standard-criteria deceased-donor (SCD) kidneys, we were able to construct models, containing the traditional factors only, for prediction of outcome at 1 year and 3 years post-transplant. Using single-center data from adult recipients of standard-criteria deceased-donor kidneys, we developed comparison models containing traditional factors only, as well as, expanded models containing the new suggested variables for prediction of outcome post-transplant. These additional variables, when incorporated into the expanded models provided greater positive predictive values, greater negative predictive values, and lower false negative rates for graft outcome at 1 year and at 3 years post-transplant than the models utilizing traditional factors only. Our results indicate that evaluation of sCD30, MICA and KIR as part of routine protocol testing, is helpful to clinicians for predicting risk of kidney graft rejection.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1059</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2207&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>prediction model</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>kidney</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>renal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>allograft</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>transplant</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>outcome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medical Immunology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Other Analytical, Diagnostic and Therapeutic Techniques and Equipment</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1080</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:47:03Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Quantitative Analysis of Influenza Virus-Specific B Cell Responses Generated by Infection and Vaccination</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Joo, Hye Mee</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The two cellular components of B cell memory are antibody (Ab)-secreting cells (ASCs) and memory B cells (BMem). BMem are quiescent cells that respond to “recall” antigen and contribute substantially to vaccine effectiveness. The rational evaluation of vaccination strategies is dependent on quantitative information on the state of B cell memory. Despite the importance of BMem in resistance to infection, there is little information on the nature of BMem populations generated by influenza infection or vaccination. The major goal of this dissertation was a comprehensive quantitative analysis of the frequency and distribution of influenza-specific BMem generated by influenza infection of the respiratory tract, or by vaccination with inactivated virus.
To achieve this, a prerequisite was the development of a sensitive and reproducible limiting dilution assay (LDA) for determining influenza-specific BMem frequencies. The results in Chapter 2 demonstrated that a strategy utilizing BPL-inactivated virus particles was effective for the in vitro activation of virus-specific BMem. This strategy selectively activates virus-specific BMem and, importantly, achieves this without a requirement for CD4+ T cell associated factors.
Using this strategy, the frequency of Influenza specific BMem in different anatomical sites was measured and we also tested three different forms of influenza virus immunization strategy; (i) intranasal (i.n.) infection, (ii) i.n. vaccination, (iii) intramuscular (i.m.) vaccination. The results in Chapter III, IV showed that following different forms of immunization, BMem dispersed broadly to organized lymphoid tissues throughout the body, and a population of ASCs was established in the bone marrow. ASC and BMem frequencies in these locations reflected the magnitude of the primary B cell response to the form of immunization. Thus, the frequencies were higher following i.n. infection. Interestingly, the state of B cell memory in the lung was profoundly influenced by the form of immunization. The lung was a preferential site of BMem localization after i.n. infection. However, this was not the case after i.m. immunization when BMem frequencies in the lung were considerably lower than in other sites. Our findings point to an effect of influenza infection on the lung environment that profoundly influences ASC and BMem trafficking to this site.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/52</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1080&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2045</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:47:16Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Mechanism of phospholipid induction of cell migration</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Wu, Dongwei</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Lysophosphatidic acid (LPA) is a potent bioactive lipid component of oxidized low density lipoproteins (oxLDL). High concentrations of LPA have been detected in human atherosclerotic plaques. Our data has shown that LPA highly induces smooth muscle cell (SMC) migration. Cyr61, a matricellular protein, which also accumulates in human atherosclerotic plaques, has been implicated in the injury-induced neointimal formation. Smooth muscle cell migration is a key event in the development of atherosclerosis, and it contributes to the progressive growth of atherosclerotic lesions. Data generated by this study demonstrate that LPA markedly induces Cyr61 expression in mouse aortic smooth muscle cells (MASMC). We hypothesized that LPA-induced matricellular Cyr61 mediates LPA-induced MASMC migration. To date, little is known about the relationship between LPA and Cyr61 in smooth muscle cells; the signaling pathway leading to LPA-induced Cyr61 is unknown. Furthermore, whether Cyr61 contributes to LPA-induced cell migration is unrevealed. Our study demonstrates that LPA, by binding to LPA1 receptor, activates the intracellular signaling pathway leading to the activation of PKCdelta which in turn contributes to the increased expression of Cyr61 in MASMCs. Interestingly, we found that after LPA-induced Cyr61 mRNA has been translated into its protein intracellularly, the de novo synthesized proteins promptly accumulate in the Golgi apparatus and then translocalize to the extracellular matrix. Importantly, our data reveal a novel LPA/Cyr61 pathway in controlling MASMC migration. Understanding the mechanism underlying LPA induction of Cyr61 provides new insight into pathogenesis of atherosclerosis.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1040</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2045&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>cell migration</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>phospholipid</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>matricellular protein</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>oxidized low density lipoprotein.</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medical Cell Biology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1891</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:47:32Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Methicillin Resistance in Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Black, Chad Christopher</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Staphylococcus pseudintermedius affecting dogs is analogous to S. aureus on humans, acting as both normal flora and opportunistic pathogen. Methicillin resistance in S. pseudintermedius is recent, with the first documented occurrence of an isolate bearing the methicillin resistance gene, mecA, in 1999. This gene encodes penicillin binding protein 2a, which renders all beta-lactam drugs ineffective and functions as a “gateway” antibiotic resistance determinant. In the presence of ineffective antibiotics, opportunities for mutational events and acquisition of mobile genetic elements increase as microbial densities increase, often leading to multi-drug resistance. Methicillin-resistant S. pseudintermedius (MRSP) infections have become increasingly common. For example, approximately 30% of the S. pseudintermedius isolates tested by the University of Tennessee College of Veterinary Medicine Clinical Bacteriology Laboratory are resistant to methicillin. An increasing number of MRSP isolates are also resistant to most clinically useful antibiotics available to veterinarians except for chloramphenicol, and resistance to this antibiotic is common among European MRSP isolates. Chloramphenicol resistance has begun to appear in the US and if this trend continues there may soon be few viable antibiotic treatment options.
Compared with the arrival of methicillin-resistant S. aureus in the 1960s, the opportunity currently exists to apply advanced molecular methods early in this recognized emergence of MRSP. To that end I have pursued projects utilizing multilocus sequence typing, pulsed-field electrophoresis, and SCCmec characterization of both susceptible and resistant S. pseudintermedius. The initial result was the detection of a clonal population of MRSP in the southeastern United States. Further characterization of this and other clonal lineages using genomic sequencing and real-time RT-PCR expression analysis of antibiotic resistance and quorum sensing genes revealed a marked difference in the regulation of antibiotic resistance between regional clones. These discoveries have interesting epidemiological implications and provide a foundation for the development of novel therapeutics to circumvent the expanding antibiotic resistance repertoire of MRSP. Potential targets identified by this work include membrane-bound beta-lactamase receptors responsible for the regulation of mecA, non-cognate auto-inducing peptides, and synthetic antisense oligonucleotides.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/775</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1891&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>methicillin-resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>dogs</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>mecA</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>blaZ</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bacteria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Molecular genetics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pathogenic Microbiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Infectious Diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Microbiology and Immunobiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Preventive Medicine, Epidemiology, and Public Health</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1348</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:04:26Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Estimating the Early Postmortem Interval in Domestic Canines</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Proctor, Keith William</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The estimation of time of death (TOD) can be used to aid law enforcement officers in solving criminal cases involving a death. By determining the period from the TOD until the time the body is discovered, forensic investigators can potentially link or rule out a suspect. A great amount of research has been conducted for the purpose of establishing a reliable and accurate means of estimating TOD in humans. In contrast, most animal studies have centered on techniques that might be applied to human forensic cases or to aid wildlife officers in prosecuting criminals who violate conservation laws. However, little research has been conducted concerning the estimation of TOD in companion animals, especially canines. Estimating TOD in companion animals can aid investigators in solving animal abuse cases involving the death of a pet and/or the murder of an owner that coincides with the death of the pet.
The objectives of this study are to take selected TOD measures and apply them for the purpose of expanding the current scientific knowledge concerning TOD determination in canines. Such information should be useful in animal cruelty/abuse investigations by providing a practical and inexpensive quantitative methodology of estimating TOD, maximize the probability that investigators with limited experience will collect useful data, and aid in teaching animal cruelty/abuse investigators proper forensic techniques for handling and collecting data in the field. The measures chosen for this study include postmortem temperature declines in the brain, liver, rectum, and external ear canal and analysis of changes in the concentration of vitreous humor potassium after death. Recording data for these measures are relatively easy, inexpensive, and have been shown in many studies to be the least controversial and most accurate means for estimating TOD. This study documented that body temperature declines measured in the rectum, liver, brain, and external ear canal can be documented using relatively inexpensive and readily available instruments. Further, this study confirms the work of others that changes in K+ concentration in the vitreous humor of the eye is a reliable measure for use in estimation of TOD in dogs.
Keywords: Estimation of time of death; Forensics; Canines; Core body temperature; Vitreous humor; Potassium</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/315</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/Theses/ProctorKeith.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Comparative and Laboratory Animal Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1912</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:05:46Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Effects of pituitary pars intermedia dysfunction (PPID), season, and pasture diet on blood adrenocorticotropic hormone and metabolite concentrations in horses.</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Elliott, Sarah Beth</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Studies described in this thesis were performed to investigate associations among season, diet, pituitary pars intermedia dysfunction (PPID) and blood concentrations of adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH), insulin, glucose, and leptin in horses.  In the first study, higher ACTH concentrations were detected in horses affected with PPID.  A seasonal increase in plasma ACTH concentration was detected in the late summer and early fall, but PPID did not affect the timing or duration of this increase.  Pasture grazing raised glucose and insulin concentrations with a peak in September, at the same time that horses had higher ACTH concentrations, and this convergence of risk factors may raise the risk of laminitis.  All of the horses included in this study were from the same farm.  The second study was performed to determine whether horses from different locations within the same region exhibited the same seasonal increase in ACTH concentrations.  Results of this study indicate that the seasonal increase in plasma ACTH concentrations occurs in horses from different farms with varying management practices.  The third study investigated the effects of season on plasma leptin concentrations in the horses from the first study.  We hypothesized that higher leptin concentrations would be detected in advance of the seasonal increase in plasma ACTH concentrations.  Results did not support our hypothesis because leptin concentrations increased after ACTH concentrations peaked in September.  Our findings suggest that the seasonal increase in ACTH concentrations induced leptin resistance, which might facilitate weight gain in the autumn.   Alternatively, leptin concentrations increased as a result of weight gain or change in body fat composition.  In summary, season appears to signal upregulation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis in horses, in an effort to prepare for winter.  This upregulation is retained in horses with PPID, a disorder associated with loss of dopaminergic inhibition to the pars intermedia of the pituitary.  The seasonal rise in plasma ACTH concentrations is followed by an increase in leptin concentrations, which suggests the development of leptin resistance or an increase in adiposity.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/792</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1912&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>pituitary pars intermedia dysfunction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>leptin</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>season</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>adrenocorticotropic hormone</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Large or Food Animal and Equine Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1497</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:05:55Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>A Descriptive Epidemiologic Study of Campylobacteriosis in East Tennessee</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Laughter, Karissa</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Campylobacteriosis is caused by the gram-negative bacteria Campylobacter and is a leading cause of gastrointestinal illness worldwide. In the United States an estimated 2.4 million cases occur annually with approximately $8.0 billion in associated costs. Due to the high cost of morbidity, understanding the epidemiology and risk factors of campylobacteriosis is important. It is unclear if the prevalence of campylobacteriosis is higher or lower in East Tennessee than other parts of the state or country or if the clinical characteristics of patients in the area are similar to the rest of the country. Therefore, the purpose of the study was to describe clinical and epidemiological characteristics of campylobacteriosis patients in East Tennessee to assist in health planning to control campylobacteriosis. Data from the Foodborne Disease Active Surveillance Network was analyzed for 2003-2006 in 16 counties in East Tennessee. The data was first assessed for its quality, then descriptive statistics were calculated and spatial and temporal patterns of reported cases and risk factors were assessed. The overall error rate in the data quality analysis was 6.5% although in the last year of the study it was only 2.6%. The mean annual prevalence of campylobacteriosis in East Tennessee was 10.4 cases per 100,000 population, which was 1.6 times higher than all of Tennessee (7.4 cases/100,000). Grainger and Jefferson Counties had higher age- and sex-adjusted prevalence estimates than the region and nation. It is yet unclear why this region has a higher prevalence of campylobacteriosis than the rest of the nation. The highest age-specific prevalence (41.6 cases/100,000) was observed in children under 5. Disease prevalence was consistently higher in the summer months compared to the other seasons. The median age of patients was lower in the most rural counties. More patients in East Tennessee were hospitalized than the rest of the nation. The most commonly reported risk factors were animal and raw meat exposure. Improvement in data collection and entry is necessary to improve the quality and application of this surveillance data. Educational efforts on proper hygiene following animal handling, and proper well protection and disinfection should be targeted at high risk groups.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2008-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/461</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008MastersTheses/LaughterKarissa.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1459</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:08:37Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Regulation of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt;, a Novel Type 4 P-type ATPase, in 3T3-L1 Mouse Adipocytes</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Peretich, Amanda Lynn</dc:creator>
<dc:description>A recently identified phospholipid translocase, Atp10c, may be involved in the modulation of glucose and lipid metabolism in mouse adipocytes. Aminophospholipid translocases have previously been associated with cell signaling and intracellular protein trafficking. In this study, the role of Atp10c in the insulin signaling pathway and adipogenesis was investigated using the murine 3T3-L1 cell line.
Atp10c mRNA is highly expressed in undifferentiated cells and 2-fold down-regulated during adipogenesis. Interestingly, Western blotting showed a band for ATP10C protein at 70 kDa, a lower molecular weight than expected; ATP10C expression increased during differentiation. Possible reasons for these discrepancies will be discussed.
Since PPARgamma is considered to be the master regulator of adipogenesis and controls the expression of adipocyte genes, the effect of PPARgamma agonists on Atp10c expression was examined. The PPARgamma agonists and anti-diabetic drugs MCC555 and troglitazone both promoted adipogenesis and consequently reduced Atp10c expression by 5-fold and 3-fold, respectively. When used in combination with the PPARgamma antagonist GW9662, treatment rescued some of the decrease in Atp10c due to MCC555 or troglitazone alone. The pattern of Atp10c expression is shown to be opposite to that of PPARgamma.
Additionally, the correlation between effectors of glucose and lipid metabolism and Atp10c was investigated. Treatment of 3T3-L1 adipocytes with insulin and dexamethasone showed significantly increased expression of Atp10c; treatment with the β-adrenergic factor isoproterenol slightly decreased expression. This suggests transcriptional control of Atp10c by hormonal factors, but not β-adrenergic factors, during differentiation.
To further explore the function of Atp10c in lipid metabolism, ATP10C silencing through transient transfection of 3T3-L1 cells was first optimized to ultimately allow the assessment of changes in proteins related to obesity and diabetes. An 84% and 77% knockdown of Atp10c gene expression in preadipocytes and adipocytes, respectively, was achieved. To elucidate a potential role for Atp10c/ATP10C in the insulin signaling pathway, glucose uptake was investigated. Following Atp10c silencing in 3T3-L1 adipocytes, glucose uptake was significantly increased at both 24 and 48 hours.
Based on the results presented herein, the Atp10c gene and ATP10C protein have an important role in the insulin signaling pathway and may be involved in adipogenesis.,/p&gt;</dc:description>
<dc:date>2008-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/426</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/PeretichAmanda.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2374</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-02-03T19:31:16Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Geographic Disparities Associated with Stroke and Myocardial Infarction in East Tennessee</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Golden, Ashley Pedigo</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Stroke and myocardial infarction (MI) are serious conditions whose burdens vary by socio-demographic and geographic factors. Although several studies have investigated and identified disparities in burdens of these conditions at the county and state levels, little is known regarding their geographic epidemiology at the neighborhood level.  Both conditions require emergency treatments and therefore timely geographic accessibility to appropriate care is critical. Investigation of disparities in geographic accessibility to stroke and MI care and the role of Emergency Medical Services (EMS) in reducing treatment delays are vital in improving health outcomes. Therefore, the objectives of this work were to: (i) classify neighborhoods based on socio-demographic and geographic characteristics; (ii) investigate spatial patterns of neighborhood level mortality; (iii) identify disparities in geographic accessibility to stroke and MI care; and (iv) identify disparities in EMS transport times for stroke and MI patients in East Tennessee.
Fuzzy cluster analysis was used to classify neighborhoods into peer neighborhoods (PNs) based on their socio-demographic and geographic factors.  Neighborhood level spatial patterns of stroke and MI mortality risks were investigated using Spatial Empirical Bayesian smoothing techniques and neighborhoods with high mortality risks identified using spatial scan statistics. Travel times to stroke and cardiac care facilities were computed using network analysis to investigate geographic accessibility. Records of over 3,900 suspected stroke and MI patients, from two EMS providers, were used to investigate disparities in EMS transport delays.
Four distinct PNs were identified. The highest stroke/MI mortality risks were observed in less affluent, urban PNs, and lowest risks in more affluent, suburban PNs. Several significant (p&lt;0.0001) stroke and MI high mortality risk spatial clusters were identified. Approximately 8% and 15% of the population did not have timely accessibility to appropriate stroke and MI care, respectively.  The disparity was greatest for populations in rural areas. Important disparities in EMS transport delays were identified, with the travel time to a hospital contributing the longest delay.
The identified disparities in neighborhood characteristics, mortality risks, geographic accessibility, and EMS transport delays are invaluable in guiding resource allocation, service provision, and policy decisions to support evidence-based population health planning and policy.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1182</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2374&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Statistics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Geography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health Disparities</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Population Health Planning</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiovascular Disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Biostatistics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiovascular Diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health Services Research</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Multivariate Analysis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vital and Health Statistics</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2281</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-02-03T19:52:20Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Toward Personalized Medicine: The potential role of RNA interference in Plasma Cell Dyscrasia</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Phipps, Jonathan E</dc:creator>
<dc:description>A major contributor to mortality in patients with plasma cell dyscrasias (PCDs); i.e., multiple myeloma, light chain deposition disease and AL amyloidosis is the deposition as insoluble aggregates of monoclonal immunoglobulin light chain proteins (LC) in the kidneys and other organs.  Currently anti-plasma cell chemotherapies are used to reduce LC synthesis, and slow deposition.  While effective, these treatments are toxic, non-specific, expensive, and might not be appropriate in all cases, making the identification of an alternate means of reducing toxic LC species desirable.  To this end, we have investigated whether RNA interference (RNAi) could achieve these goals.
Human (RPMI 8226, Bur) and transfected mouse myeloma (SP2/O-lambda 6) cells which produce measureable quantities of human LC protein were used as model systems for testing the efficacy of both synthetic small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) and short hairpin RNA (shRNA) expression vectors in reducing LC synthesis.  Sequencing of LC genes provided the basis for design of siRNA duplexes targeting either the variable (V) or joining (J) regions of individual LCs, or the constant (C) region of either kappa or lambda LC isotypes.  Myeloma lines were transfected with siRNAs using lipid-based transfection media.  Cells receiving non-silencing siRNAs served as controls.  Exposure of myeloma lines to siRNAs was well tolerated and no cytotoxicity was observed.  LC mRNA expression was shown to be reduced ≥40% in 8226 and SP2/O- lambda 6 cell lines receiving siRNA treatment as compared with untreated controls.  Exposure to siRNAs was also effective in significantly reducing both intracellular and secreted LC protein levels in cell lines tested as evidenced by flow cytometry or enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays (ELISAs).
Effective siRNA nucleotide sequences were used to generate shRNA cassettes which were ligated into lentiviral expression vectors under the control of the RNA polymerase III promoter, U6.  These expression systems were used to generate replication incompetent lentiviral particles.  Exposure of 8226 to lentiviral particles resulted in significant knockdown of LC mRNA and protein both in vitro and in xenograft tumor bearing immune compromised mice.  These results provide positive evidence for the ability of RNAi based approaches to reduce LC secretion in models of PCD.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1217</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2281&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Gene silencing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Plasma cell dyscrasia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>RNA interference</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Multiple Myeloma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Light Chain Amyloidosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medical Molecular Biology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2337</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-02-03T19:57:47Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Immunity and Immunopathology in acute viral infections</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Sharma, Shalini</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Herpetic stromal keratitis (HSK) is an immunopathological and tissue destructive corneal lesion caused by herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection, which induces an intense inflammatory response and finally leads to blindness. Accumulating evidence using the murine model has shown that Th-1 phenotype CD4+ T cells orchestrating the inflammation mainly contribute to the immunopathological reaction in HSV-1 infected cornea. Initially various innate immune cells recruit and produce numerous inflammatory and angiogenic molecules into the corneal stroma those in turn drive the corneal immunopathology.
While the basic principles of immunity to the influenza A viruses (IAV) are probably similar for all vertebrates, detailed understanding is based largely on experiments in laboratory mice. Virus clearance is normally mediated via CD8+ effector T cells but, in their absence, the class-switched antibody response can ultimately achieve the same goal. Influenza virus-specific plasma cells and CD8+ T cells persist in the long term and the recall of the CD8+ T cell response can lead to earlier virus clearance.
The first part (Part I) of this dissertation focuses on the understanding of HSV-1 induced immunoinflammatory processes in the cornea and the secondary lymphoid tissues and the involvement of immuno-modulatory mechanisms following acute viral infections such as HSV and IAV. The next three parts (Part II-IV) focus on different inflammatory and counter-inflammatory mechanisms that are activated following acute viral infections. Results in Part II evaluate the role of small molecule inhibitors of VEGFR2/src kinase inhibitors in controlling the progression of the inflammatory lesions after ocular HSV infection. Results of the third section show that the host counter inflammatory mechanisms inhibit tissue damage but these may also act to constrain the effectiveness of immunity to acute infections. The fourth section describes the functional significance of HVEM expression on regulatory T cell in their expansion following HSV-1 infection.
In this study, experiments were designed to understand the mechanisms involved in the regulation of immunity and resultant immunopathology using HSV-1 and IAV as the model systems and that modulation of these processes can enhance immune response and diminish immunopathology following acute infections.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1225</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2337&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Immunity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Immunopathology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Herpes Virus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Influenza A virus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Immunology of Infectious Disease</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2386</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-02-03T20:02:27Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Role of Systemic Inflammation in the Development of Equine Laminitis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Tadros, Elizabeth MaryRose</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Laminitis is a crippling disease of horses that can result in chronic lameness and debilitation, and sometimes warrants euthanasia.  It is a complication of inflammatory conditions such as gastrointestinal disease, and also occurs in obese, insulin-resistant horses with Equine Metabolic Syndrome (EMS).  Inflammation and insulin resistance are risk factors for laminitis, and these mechanisms might converge to induce laminitis in susceptible animals.
Systemic inflammation is often attributed to endotoxemia, although circulating endotoxin concentrations are not commonly measured in the clinical setting.  Although a theoretic basis exists for endotoxemia in the pathogenesis of laminitis, administration of endotoxin alone does not induce the condition.  This could be related to differences between experimental models and naturally occurring disease.
Studies presented in this dissertation address the overall hypothesis that systemic inflammation causes laminitis and new experimental models can be developed to better represent clinical disease.  Associations between systemic inflammation and laminitis were first established by measuring blood inflammatory cytokine expression during a laminitis induction model.  A clinically relevant endotoxin model that induced laminitis was then sought, but endotoxin administration alone was insufficient to cause laminitis and endotoxin tolerance developed.  Endotoxemia was therefore evaluated in conjunction with predisposing factors such as obesity.  In horses with EMS, endotoxin infusion caused exaggerated inflammatory responses, and derangements in glucose homeostasis were more pronounced.  Laminitis, however, did not develop.  Repeated inflammatory events are implicated in the pathogenesis of sepsis-associated organ failure, so a final study was performed to test whether preexisting endotoxemia increased the risk of laminitis during subsequent carbohydrate overload-induced systemic inflammation.  This did not occur, however systemic inflammation was more pronounced in horses that developed laminitis compared to non-responders, and tissues rather than circulating leukocytes appeared to be the major source of inflammatory mediators.
Our results do not support a role for endotoxin as the causal agent of laminitis, even when combined with predisposing factors.  Tissues appear to be an important source of inflammatory mediators, therefore their role in laminitis should be further characterized.  Additionally, future investigations should determine whether exaggerated inflammatory responses and loss of glycemic control increase the risk of laminitis in horses with EMS.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1231</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2386&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>horse</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>laminitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>systemic inflammation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>endotoxemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Equine Metabolic Syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>insulin resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Large or Food Animal and Equine Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2389</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-02-03T20:07:08Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Identification of Novel Molecular Targets of Resveratrol in Colorectal Carcinogenesis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Whitlock, Nichelle Chantil</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Current research suggests resveratrol, a phytoalexin found predominately in grapes, may function as a chemopreventive and/or chemotherapeutic agent for various cancers, including colorectal cancer.  However, the underlying mechanism(s) involved in these activities remain elusive.  Thus, the objective of the studies discussed here sought to investigate the effect of resveratrol treatment on gene modulation in human colorectal cancer cells in order to identify and characterize novel molecular targets that contribute to the observed anticancer activities of resveratrol.  Here, we identify activating transcription factor 3 (ATF3) and early growth response-1 (Egr-1) as novel targets of resveratrol and provide data to elucidate the mechanism(s) of regulation and how each target contributes to the anticancer effect of resveratrol in colorectal cancer cells.  We demonstrate the involvement of resveratrol in ATF3 transcriptional regulation, which is facilitated by Egr-1 and Krüppel-like factor 4 interactions, and show that ATF3 contributes, at least partially, to resveratrol-induced apoptosis (Chapter 3).  Moreover, we suggest that increased Egr-1 transcriptional activity by resveratrol requires posttranslational acetylation of Egr-1 in a SIRT1-independent manner.  This acetylation by resveratrol may contribute to Egr-1-mediated expression of the pro-apoptotic protein nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID)-activated gene-1 (NAG-1) induced by the phytoalexin (Chapter 4).  Taken together, the work presented here provide (1) novel mechanisms by which resveratrol induces ATF3 and Egr-1 expression and (2) represent additional explanations for the anti-tumorigenic/anti-carcinogenic effects of resveratrol in human colorectal cancer cells.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1237</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2389&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>ATF3</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Egr-1</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>KLF4</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>resveratrol</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2166</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-04-25T01:14:56Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Spatial Epidemiology and Temporal Trends of Heart Attack and Stroke in Middle Tennessee</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Busingye, Doreen</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Despite declines in mortality risks of myocardial infarction (MI) and stroke in the US since the 1960’s, the burdens of these conditions remain high. These conditions require emergency and specialized care and therefore quick transportation of patients to appropriate hospitals is critical. Geographic disparities in MI and stroke burdens have been consistently reported in the US with the south-east having the highest risks. Most studies of geographic disparities have been performed at county or higher geographic units. Therefore, spatial patterns at neighborhood levels are unclear. Moreover, it’s important to investigate disparities at neighborhood levels to better understand neighborhood health needs. Therefore, the goal of this study was to investigate neighborhood disparities associated with MI and stroke in Middle Tennessee. Specific objectives were to investigate: (a) geographic disparities in timely access to emergency care; and (b) geographic disparities in MI and stroke mortality risks.
Street network, hospital, population, and mortality data (1999-2007) were obtained from Streetmap USA, the Joint Commission on Accreditation of Health Organizations, US Census Bureau, and the Tennessee Department of Health, respectively. Network analysis was used to investigate and identify neighborhoods lacking timely access to emergency MI and stroke care. Moran’s I and Kulldorff’s spatial scan statistic were used to investigate geographic hot-spots of MI and stroke mortality risks at both the county and neighborhood levels. Poisson and negative binomial models were used to investigate predictors of identified geographic patterns.
A temporal increase in the percentage of the population with timely geographic access to stroke and cardiac centers was observed. In 2010, about 5% of the population, located mainly in rural neighborhoods, lacked timely access to a stroke center. Significant (p&lt;0.05) hot-spots of MI and stroke mortality risks were identified at both neighborhood and county levels. However, clusters identified at the neighborhood level were more refined. Neighborhoods with higher proportions of older populations and those with lower education had significantly (p&lt;0.05) higher mortality risks.
These findings are vital for guiding health planning, resource allocation and service provision in an effort to provide needs-based services to the population. This is important in reducing/eliminating neighborhood disparities and improving population health.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1061</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2166&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Spatial Disparities</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Temporal Trends</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Heart Attack</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Stroke</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Middle Tennessee</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2479</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-08-22T19:06:43Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>&lt;i&gt;In Vitro&lt;/i&gt; Alterations of a Putative Phospholipid Translocase, &lt;i&gt;Atp10c&lt;/i&gt;, and Its Role in Glucose Metabolism</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hurst, Sarah Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Atp10c/ATP10C is a putative aminophospholipid translocase or “flippase” that encodes for a type 4 P-type ATPase. Based on previous research, we hypothesize that Atp10c/ATP10C due to its flippase nature plays a role in diet-induced obesity and type 2 diabetes as Atp10c heterozygous mice display this phenotype. For purposes of this dissertation, Atp10c/ATP10C was characterized both generally and biologically to gleam information about its molecular weight, cellular location and possible biological roles and/or functions. Multiple experiments, both in vitro and in vivo, were performed in order to accomplish these characterizations and are discussed at length. Essential results from this dissertation work include the validation of ATP10C’s expected molecular weight (~165 kD), the localization of ATP10C to the plasma membrane, its possible co-localization with GLUT4, and the high expression of Atp10c in key tissues (skeletal muscle and adipose tissue) of two mice models, one a model of diet-induced obesity mice and another a genetic model (ob/ob). To identify molecular and cellular targets of ATP10C, Atp10c expression was altered in vitro in C2C12 and L6-G4myc skeletal muscle myotubes. Functional outcomes of GLUT4 translocation and glucose uptake assays were performed resulting in the significant alteration of normal GLUT4 regulation and a significant decrease in glucose uptake. Additionally, when the expression of Atp10c was altered both experimentally and genetically, significant up-regulation of native and activated mitogen-activated protein kinases, p38, and ERK1/2 were observed. These results demonstrate that Atp10c-silencing does affect these main mitogen-activated protein kinase proteins and in turn, glucose metabolism via both insulin-independent and insulin-dependent manners. Taken together, all these results presented in this dissertation indicate that Atp10c/ATP10C has an important role in the regulation of glucose metabolism, at least in part via the mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway, and as such, plays a significant role in the development of insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1308</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2479&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>type 2 diabetes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>glucose</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>metabolism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>siRNA</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2358</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-08-23T17:01:48Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Pulmonary Pharmacokinetics of Tulatuthromycin in Mice and Pigs</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Villarino, Nicolas Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Tulathromycin is an antimicrobial approved for use in the treatment and control of bovine respiratory disease and treatment of swine respiratory disease in United States and European Union. This macrolide is a unique drug which has an extraordinary capacity to accumulate in lung tissue and shows distinctive pharmacokinetic features in animals. The pulmonary pharmacokinetics of tulathromycin in mice and pigs were evaluated in this dissertation. In mice, the pulmonary pharmacokinetics of tulathromycin was evaluated in healthy animals and animals challenged with lipopolysaccharide of Escherichia coli (LPS-Ec). A group of challenged animals were also rendered neutropenic. In pigs, the pulmonary pharmacokinetics of tulathromycin was assessed in healthy animals and animals challenged intra-tracheally with LPS-Ec. The pulmonary pharmacokinetics of tulathromycin was assessed using lung tissue (middle and caudal lobes), pulmonary and bronchial epithelial lining fluid (BELF) samples. We introduce a novel technique for the assessment of the concentration vs. time profile of tulathromycin in BELF. This technique is based in the use of fiberscopically guided bronchial micro-sampling probes (BMSp). The BMSp were first evaluated in a pilot trial. Then, the BMSp were used as sampling tool for harvesting BELF in a larger study. The use of BMSp represents a cost effective technique. This technique can be introduced in discovery and preclinical pharmacokinetics studies for screening of candidate drugs that will be indicated for the treatment of respiratory conditions. This technique might enhance the experimental design and maximize the experimental resources (number of animals, time, and cost). This dissertation expands the understanding about the distribution of tulathromycin into the lungs. It evaluates the kinetics of tulathromycin in middle and caudal lobes and intra-airways compartment from healthy and animals with an acute pulmonary inflammatory response. This work provides the first evidence of the pharmacokinetics of tulathromycin in lung tissue administered to neutropenic, normopenic, and neutrophilic mice. Finally, this dissertation introduces and evaluates an innovative technique for the study of pulmonary pharmacokinetics of drugs in veterinary species.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1364</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2358&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Tulathromycin</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pigs</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pharmacokinetics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lung</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pneumonia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2460</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-11-28T20:41:47Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Nutritional Adequacy and Performance of Raw Food Diets in Kittens</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hamper, Beth Alair</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Feeding raw food diets to domestic cats is controversial. The objective of this study was to determine if raw feline diets were nutritionally adequate for kittens and whether they enhance immune function, reduce oxidative stress and improve digestibility. Twenty-four 9-week-old kittens underwent a 10-week growth feeding trial with two raw diet groups and one control group (commercial heat-processed canned diet) of eight kittens each. Anthropomorphic measurements, feed efficiency, oxidative stress, and blood biomarkers for innate and humoral immune function were evaluated. Additionally, 6 kittens and 4 adults participated in a 14 day digestibility trial using a 3 x 3 latin square design. Composite fecal cultures were periodically monitored for common bacterial pathogens.
Both raw diets passed an American Association of Feed Control Officials (AAFCO) growth trial and had similar growth performance compared to the control diet.
Minimal differences were measured in markers of innate or humoral immune function. Over time, higher lymphocyte and immunoglobulin responses were measured in kittens consuming the raw diets. A trend toward higher IgM levels was noted in one raw diet group. Higher exposure to bacterial degradation products, pathogen exposure, or nutritional differences may have stimulated a more robust immune response in the raw-fed groups.
No differences in levels of oxidative stress were noted among the three groups. All kittens had decreasing levels of urinary isoprostanes over the 10-week testing period.
Significantly higher digestibility of dry matter, organic matter, protein and energy were noted in the raw vs. control groups for both kittens and adult cats, despite similar levels of intake. These changes may be attributed to structural changes in proteins following processing, alterations in gastrointestinal flora, or differences in ingredient quality among diets.
In conclusion, there was neither an advantage nor disadvantage of the two raw feline diets when compared with the commercial heat-processed, control diet and both diets would be deemed nutritionally adequate for feline growth based on AAFCO feeding trials. The raw food diets were associated with higher digestibility and decreased fecal matter. Future research on methods to reduce pathogen load while minimizing processing of animal tissue proteins is recommended.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1389</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2460&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>kitten</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>raw diets</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>growth</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>immune function</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>oxidative stress</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>digestibility</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dietetics and Clinical Nutrition</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2492</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-12-06T17:34:36Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Effects of Folate Availability on Expression of Adipocyte Metabolic Genes Via Modulation of DNA Methylation</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Gouffon, Julia Stair</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Epigenetic modifications serve as a means of intermediate gene expression control and nutritional inputs may modify methylation patterns in regulatory regions of genes. Therefore, we proposed that specific nutrient availability of folate affects adipocyte development and metabolism through impacting the one-carbon cycle and subsequent DNA methylation patterns. Accordingly, we sought to determine if the methylation level of CpG islands could be influenced in adipocytes and if so, how this might affect gene signaling in mature adipocytes. We treated adipocytes with 0 to 0.9 millimolar [mM] folate, the methyl donor S-adenosylmethionine (SAMe) and the methylation inhibitor, 5-aza-2-deoxycitidine (2-DC) both during adipocyte differentiation and the maturation process. Lipogenesis was measured by accumulation of oil red O and lipolysis was quantified by a glycerol release assay. Methylated regions of adipocyte genomic DNA was evaluated using a methylation-specific antibody and hybridized against a Nimblegen whole genome CpG island array to identify targets for expression analysis RNA was obtained and genes involved in adipocyte differentiation, one-carbon metabolism, lipogenesis and lipolysis were quantified using RT-PCR. We found that low folate levels or inhibition by 2-DC decreased CpG methylation, thus increasing gene expression. Surprisingly SAMe performed similarly and decreased global CpG methylation. Low folate increased lipid accretion and subsequent lipolysis. Exposure to folate during the critical differentiation process had a greater impact on lipogenesis and lipolysis than exposure during the maturation.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1429</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2492&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Epigenetics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>DNA Methylation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adipocytes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Folate</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metabolism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Genomics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Molecular, Genetic, and Biochemical Nutrition</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nutrition</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2445</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-12-06T17:36:07Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>A Description of the Movement of the Canine Pelvic Limb in Three Dimensions Using an Inverse Dynamics Method, and a Comparison of Two Techniques to Surgically Repair a Cranial Cruciate Ligament Deficient Stifle</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Headrick, Jason</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The purposes of the dissertation were: 1) to describe three-dimensional (3D) motion of the canine pelvic limb using an inverse dynamics method, and 2) to compare these motion patterns between normal, healthy dogs and those that have had their stifles stabilized by one of two surgical methods approximately five years earlier.
Twenty-five dogs were allocated to three groups; healthy control dogs, dogs that had received the tibial plateau leveling osteotomy (TPLO), and dogs that had received the lateral fabellar suture (LFS) stabilization technique. Both surgical techniques were performed approximately five years prior on stifles with surgically induced cranial cruciate ligament (CCL) rupture. A kinematic model was created so that virtual markers could be used to describe the pelvic limb motion in 3D. Kinetic, kinematic, and morphometric data were integrated so that an inverse dynamics method could be used to describe angular displacement, joint moment and power across the hock, stifle, and hip joints in the sagittal, frontal, and transverse planes. Discrete points and shapes of waveforms were analyzed for any differences among groups.
Motion and energy patterns were successfully determined in 3D for all three joints of the canine pelvic limb. There was similarity between all three groups for all variables studied in the three planes with the exception of two variables. In the sagittal plane, the TPLO group had a more extended hip at the beginning of stance phase compared to the control group. Also, in the frontal plane, the LFS group had a significantly larger maximum power across the stifle when compared to the normal group. Despite the differences between these two variables, there were no differences in gait patterns between these groups that would suggest that one surgical procedure is superior to the other. Both surgical groups moved similarly to the healthy control group. The method of collecting kinematic data in this study allowed for the description of motion of the canine pelvic limb in 3D using inverse dynamics. Comparison between normal controls and dogs that had two different methods of repair for stifle instability showed similar gait patterns for all three groups.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1471</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2445&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>inverse dynamics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>TPLO</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>lateral fabellar suture</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>cruciate ligament</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>stifle</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>3D</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Biomechanics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Comparative and Laboratory Animal Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Orthopedics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Small or Companion Animal Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sports Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2644</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-12-06T17:36:12Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Growth Regulation of Pancreatic Cancer Cells and Their Normal Cells of Origin by Nicotinic Acetylcholine Receptors</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Al-Wadei, Mohammed Hussein</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Pancreatic cancer is the fourth leading cause of cancer mortality with a five-year survival rate of less than 5 %. It shows no symptoms until it has reached an advanced stage upon which it has metastasized to distant organs limiting therapeutic options. Several studies have identified smoking, alcohol, diabetes and pancreatitis as risk factors for pancreatic cancer. While smoking is a well-documented risk factor for this malignancy, there still remains a controversy on whether alcohol can act as a risk factor itself or cooperatively enhances the effects of other risk factors.
Previous reports provide evidence that nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) and beta-adrenergic receptors cooperatively stimulate the growth and migration of normal and pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) cells upon binding NNK. Binding of the nicotine-derived nitrosamine ketone (NNK) to nAChRs result in neurotransmitters production regulation. These neurotransmitters in turn act as agonists to β-ARs [beta-adrenergic receptors] thereby activating adenylyl cyclase and the subsequent cAMP dependent signaling pathways. This ultimately results in the stimulation of proliferation, migration and angiogenesis and inhibition of apoptosis.
Using assays for the assessment of adrenaline, noradrenaline, GABA and cAMP production; PKA activity; CREB, Src, Akt and ERK phosphorylation; and cell proliferation and migration, we have identified an autocrine catecholamine loop that is jointly regulated by α3, 5 and 7-nAChRs [alpha 3, 5 and 7-nicotinic acetylcholine receptors] in normal pancreatic ductal epithelial cells (HPDE6-C7) and PDAC cell lines (BxPC-3 and Panc-1) upon stimulation by nicotine or ethanol. This catecholamine loop in turn acts to stimulate growth of normal and PDAC cell lines via cAMP dependent signaling pathways downstream β-ARs [beta-adrenergic receptors]. This loop however, is interrupted upon γ-amino butyric acid [gamma-amino butyric acid] (GABA) treatment of cells at the level of adenylyl cyclase activation thereby inhibiting nicotine and ethanol-induced stimulatory effects on cell proliferating and migration.
Our study findings therefore suggest smoking and chronic alcohol intake to be risk factors for the development of PDAC. These agents regulate catecholamine and GABA synthesis via modulation of nAChRs thereby stimulating proliferation and migration and inhibiting apoptosis. The observed effects of nicotine and ethanol were all reversed by treatment of cells with GABA, suggesting it as a potential therapeutic agent for the treatment and prevention of this malignancy.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1474</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2644&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Pancreatic cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>alcohol</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>nicotine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>adrenaline</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>noradrenaline</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>GABA</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medical Sciences</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2818</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-01-11T18:14:00Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Canine Hypoadrenocorticism (Canine Addison's Disease): History, Contemporary Diagnosis by Practicing Veterinarians, and Epidemiology</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Kelch, William James</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This study of canine hypoadrenocorticism (canine Addison's disease; adrenal insufficiency) used several techniques to determine the incidence and prevalence of the disease and to identify factors associated with its occurrence. These techniques were historical; statistical, including meta-analysis and logistic regression; and epidemiologic, including both case series and case control data. Data were gathered by: extracting the details of cases reported in the veterinary literature, a rudimentary meta-anaylsis; using data obtained by Ciba Animal Health in the clinical trial of the drug microcrystalline desoxycorticosterone pivalate (DOCP); using data obtained from the Veterinary Medical Data Base (VMDB), a data repository of clinical information from colleges of veterinary medicine in the United States - augmented by directly querying VMDB non-participant colleges of veterinary medicine in the United States and Canada; surveying by mail veterinarians enrolled in the Ciba Animal Health clinical trial of DOCP; and surveying by mail l,000 practicing small animal veterinarians selected randomly from the mailing list of the American Veterinary Medical Association.
The historical study focused on how humans first recognized the existence of the adrenal glands, next understood they were involved with disease in humans and other animals, and then developed methods for identifying and treating hypoadrenocorticism. The historical study began with Galen in the second century A.D., continued as human understanding expanded over the centuries, ended with the contemporary understanding of hypoadrenocorticism, and provided a context in which the specific results of the study became meaningful.
Incidence estimates for canine adrenal insufficiency were, depending on the data set used to obtain the estimate, 0.13/1000 dogs/yr, 0.34/1000 dogs/yr, and 0.6/1000 dogs/yr. A point estimate was 0.36/1000 dogs/yr. Prevalence estimates were 3.2/1000 dogs, 1.7/1000 dogs, and 0.6/1000 dogs. A point estimate was 1.8/1000 dogs.
Estimates of the average age (yr) at diagnosis for dogs with hypoadrenocorticism were 4.3, 4.9, and 5.4, again depending on the data set. A point estimate was 4.9. The ages of cases and controls suggested, based on the computation of age-specific odds ratios (OR) and logistic regression, that age was associated with the occurrence of disease and that the probability of disease increased with age.
Female dogs were more likely to be hypoadrenal than males, and neutered dogs of either sex were more likely than intact ones. These conclusions were based on sex-specific incidence estimates, sex-specific OR, and logistic regression. The latter confirmed that sex was a significant factor associated with hypoadrenocorticism in dogs.
Breed was, based on breed-specific OR and logistic regression, a significant factor in whether or not a dog developed adrenal insufficiency. Airedale Terriers, Basset Hounds, Bearded Collies, German Shepherds, German Shorthaired Pointers, Great Danes, Poodles, Saint Bernards, Springer Spaniels, and West Highland White Terriers were at increased risk of disease. Boston Terriers, Boxers, Cocker Spaniels, Dalmatians, Lhasa Apsos, Pit Bull Terriers, Pomeranians, Shetland Sheepdogs, Shih Tzus, and Yorkshire Terriers were at decreased risk. There was less compelling evidence that Labrador Retrievers and Mixed breed dogs were at decreased risk.
Average body weight (kg) estimates for hypoadrenal dogs were 23.4, 24.5, and 19.7, depending on the data set. A point estimate was 22.5. The body weights of cases and controls suggested, based on age-specific OR and logistic regression, that body weight was associated with disease and that the probability of disease increased with body weight.
Hypoadrenal dogs were characterized by hyponatremia, hyperkalemia, and a decreased ratio of serum sodium to potassium concentrations. Point estimates for serum sodium concentration, serum potassium concentration, and serum sodium to potassium concentration ratio were 132.1 meq/L, 6.6 meq/L, and 21.1, respectively. There was evidence that hypoadrenal dogs were seldom normal for all three diagnostic indicators.
Common clinical findings among hypoadrenal dogs were anorexia, vomiting, depression, weakness, weight loss, azotemia, and diarhrea. Though probably affected by measurement bias, there was evidence that dogs with adrenal insufficiency were more likely than dogs from the general population to have anemia, arthritis, cruciate ligament rupture, diabetes mellitus, hepatitis, hypothyroidism, keratoconjunctivitis sicca, megaesophagus, myasthenia gravis, nephritis, and thrombocytopenia.
The study concluded that epidemiologic studies of canine hypoadrenocorticism may use the practicing veterinarian's diagnosis as a case definition rather than require a strict case definition based on the adrenocorticotropic hormone stimulation test. This would produce larger numbers of cases, be less complex, more convenient, and less costly.
Logistic regression of data from the mail survey of veterinarians enrolled in the clinical trial of DOCP indicated that age, breed, sex, and body weight were associated with canine hypoadrenocorticism. The probability of disease increased with age and body weight, was greater in females than males, was greater in neutered than intact dogs, and varied with breed. There was model-dependent evidence of higher order interactions, but the exact nature of these interactions could not be determined. Models were prepared which could predict the relative probability of hypoadrenocorticism in different dogs. It was emphasized that these models undoubtedly overlooked other unknown variables.
Data from the veterinary literature, VMDB, clinical trial of DOCP, and survey of veterinarians enrolled in the DOCP clinical trial were all useful. The mail survey methodology was valuable, and should be a useful tool in veterinary epidemiologic studies. The mail survey of randomly selected veterinarians was a poor method for studying an uncommon disease; this deficiency might be overcome if larger samples were obtained.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1996-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1486</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2818&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Comparative and Laboratory Animal Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2444</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-02-05T20:31:26Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Population Genetics and Immune Response to Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Solyman, Samar Mohammed Mansour</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Staphylococcus pseudintermedius is an opportunistic bacterium affecting canines that has recently developed a high prevalence of methicillin resistance and corresponding multi-drug resistance. Developments of alternatives to antibiotics such as vaccines are important strategies for control of this organism.Multilocus sequence typing is based on the sequence variations of slowly evolving genes and usually uses a minimum of seven genes. Population genetic studies of S. pseudintermedius have been based on sequencing four genes (MLST-4). Forty-five genes were selected from available genomic data and tested as MLST candidates. Four genes were amplified from all isolates and showed the highest number of alleles. By adding four new genes to the existing ones, an MLST scheme based on 8 genes (MLST-8) was developed for S. pseudintermedius. MLST-8 was applied to 176 isolates of previously characterized S. pseudintermedius from dogs (165 isolates), cats (5 isolates) and humans (6 isolates). They were contained in 83 sequence types (STs). MLST-8 identified 106 STs which indicated a high level of diversity of the species but also verified the clonal nature of methicillin resistant isolates.Five different STs of S. pseudintermedius were selected and reacted with serum samples from dogs with pyoderma and healthy control dogs to measure their immune reactivity. Significant differences in the IgG reactivity between the different genetic backgrounds of S. pseudintermedius were found, this variation should be considered in designing a vaccine for S. pseudintermedius. The reactivity of other staphylococcal species with canine pyoderma and healthy control sera showed that minor genetic differences may be associated with significant variations in IgG reactivity.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1391</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2444&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>MLST</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Immune response</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3203</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-08-08T19:24:21Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Genetic Analysis of Feline Calicivirus (FCV) Isolates Associated with a Hemorrhagic-like Disease</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Abd-Eldaim, Mohamed Mostafa</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Feline Calicivirus (FCV) is one of the most common causes of upperrespiratory tract disease in cats. Other disease syndromes associated withFCV infection have been reported. Recently, calicivirus infectionsassociated with a hemorrhagic-like disease leading to significant mortality incats has been reported. The clinical signs are similar to those observed withthe Calicivirus of Rabbit Hemorrhagic Disease. This investigationcharacterized two FCV isolates associated with hemorrhagic-like disease.Nucleotide sequencing of the complete genome was done on these twoisolates and four isolates representing other disease syndromes. Previouslyreported sequence data for the entire genome of classical FCV (six isolates)and a portion of the capsid gene for hemorrhagic-like FCV (three isolates)were used in the genetic analysis. Sequence data were used to determinerelationships among the isolates and any correlates with phenotype.Nucleotide sequence comparisons of the entire genome and individualORF’s revealed high homology among all isolates. However, data from thisstudy suggest that the virulence may have genetic determinants as revealedby phylogenetic clustering based on a specific 75 nucleotides stretch from the capsid protein gene of the isolates associated with hemorrhagic-likedisease.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2005-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1677</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3203&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Stephen Kania</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Melissa Kennedy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Michael Karlstad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2573</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-08-09T21:53:04Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Staphylococcus pseudintermedius: Population Genetics and Antimicrobial Resistance</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Videla, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Staphylococcus pseudintermedius is a Gram-positive coagulase-negative coccus. It is a normal inhabitant of the skin of dogs. However, clinical disease can be observed in animals that are immunossuppressed or if the skin barrier is altered. This bacterium is recognized as the main cause of canine pyoderma and has also been associated with other conditions such as infection of the urinary tract, the ears, and surgical wounds.
Methicillin resistance and resistance to other antimicrobials regularly used by veterinarians is common among S. pseudintermedius which can complicate treatment. The first report of mecA, gene responsible for methicillin resistance, in S. pseudintermedius is from 1999. Since then, resistance to methicillin and to other antimicrobials has become increasingly more common, making this bacterium a possible reservoir for antimicrobial resistance genes. The reason for the increase in the presence of antimicrobial resistance among S. pseudintermedius is still not well understood.
This research focuses on characterization of S. pseudintermedius isolates from the United States in order to determine their genetic diversity, antimicrobial susceptibility profiles, and possible relationships among the two. A description of the genetically related populations that are present in the country may help in the understanding of the mechanisms of expansion of this microorganism. Also, the availability of more current information on the susceptibility to antimicrobials should help in the reestablishment of the consequences of misusage of antimicrobials and highlights the need for the development of novel treatment alternatives.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1694</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2573&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Staphylococcus population genetics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Staphylococcus antimicrobial resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Small or Companion Animal Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Infectious Diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Microbiology and Immunobiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Preventive Medicine, Epidemiology, and Public Health</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2811</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-08-12T19:33:12Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Kinetic and kinematic evaluation of compensatory movements of the head, pelvis and thoraco-lumbar spine associated with asymmetrical weight bearing of the pelvic limbs in dogs</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hicks, David Alan</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The purposes of this dissertation were to 1) determine ground reaction forces of dogs with mild asymmetrical weight-bearing of the pelvic limbs while trotting and 2) use three-dimensional motion analysis to identify compensatory vertical motion of the head and pelvis, and lateral motion of the thoraco-lumbar spine in dogs with mild asymmetrical weight-bearing of the pelvic limbs while trotting, and 3) use this information to introduce a subjective grading system for the pelvic limbs in dogs. Our hypotheses were that dogs with asymmetric weight bearing demonstrate compensatory motions of the head, pelvis and thoraco-lumbar spine while trotting, and that these motions would have a positive correlation with the degree of weight bearing asymmetry.
Twenty-seven dogs were included in the study. Nine were normal dogs, which had no surgical intervention, 9 dogs had a cranial cruciate ligament transection and tibial plateau leveling osteotomy 3 ± 0.5 years prior to study start, and 9 dogs had a cranial cruciate ligament transection and extracapsular lateral fabellar-tibial suture (modified retinacular imbrications technique) 7 ± 0.5 years prior to study start. A kinematic model was created so that reflective markers placed on the sagittal crest of the skull, the ischiatic tuberosity and 3 points along the thoraco-lumbar spine of each test subject could be tracked over time while trotting. Kinetic and kinematic data were used to characterize weight-bearing asymmetry between the left and right pelvic limbs, and to describe linear vertical displacement of the head and pelvis, and lateral angular displacement of the thoraco-lumbar spine. Maximum, minimum and range of motion values were analyzed for any differences between the pelvic limbs.
Dogs with subtle asymmetric weight bearing of the pelvic limbs demonstrated a greater range of pelvis linear vertical displacement (PLVD) on the side with a greater peak vertical force, and greater thoraco-lumbar lateral angular displacement (TL-LAD) toward the side with a lower peak vertical force while trotting. No differences in mean head linear vertical displacement (HLVD) were detected, and there were no significant correlations between the magnitude of HLVD, PLVD and TL-LAD and the degree of asymmetrical weight bearing of the pelvic limbs.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1734</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2811&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Kinetics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Kinematics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dogs</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lameness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Osteoarthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cruciate</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Small or Companion Animal Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2795</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-08-12T19:34:05Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Contribution of microRNAs and Robo4 signaling after herpes simplex virus infection: Role for regulatory mechanisms</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Mulik, Sachin Vishvas</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection of the eye results in chronic immunopathological response in corneal stroma orchestrated by CD4 T cells. Due to its neurotrophic nature, HSV can also invade brain and leads to deadly encephalitis. HSV infection of the eyes leads to corneal neovascularization (CV), which is an important step in the pathogenesis of herpetic stromal keratitis (HSK), an important cause of human blindness. This study was undertaken to investigate the contribution of miRNAs and Robo4 signaling in HSK. The role of miR-132 and miR-155 was evaluated. In the first chapter, we review literature regarding the contribution of miRNAs in several human diseases and speculate about the role of those miRNAs in herpes viral latency and HSK. We also discuss involvement of Robo4 signaling in the context of pathological angiogenesis.
In the second chapter, we show that HSV infection of the eyes of mice leads to appearance of Robo4+ blood vessel endothelial cells in corneas but levels of Slit2 (a ligand for Robo4 receptor) were minimal. The provision of exogenous Slit2 protein reduced CV following HSV infection.
In the third chapter, we report the role of miR-132 in angiogenesis following ocular HSV infection. We observed VEGF and IL-17 driven upregulation of miR-132 during HSK. miR-132 was shown to augment VEGF induced angiogenic responses and blockade of miR-132 using antagomir nanoparticles reduced pathological angiogenesis in eyes after HSV infection.
In the fourth chapter, we analyzed the involvement of miR-155 after ocular infection with HSV. The mice unable to produce miR-155 were found to be highly susceptible to encephalitis after HSV infection with the majority of mice dyeing by day 9. We further show that virus replication in brain was responsible for death in miR-155 null mice. When T cell responses were measured, miR-155 knockout animals demonstrated attenuated CD4 and virus specific CD8 T cell immunity. Additionally, we also evaluated the role of miR-155 in HSK. miR-155KO survivors from herpes simplex encephalitis were relatively resistant to HSK. In conclusion, we demonstrated that the miR-155 is a regulator of herpes simplex encephalitis but it promotes inflammation during HSK.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1764</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2795&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>HSK</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>VEGF</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>microRNA</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>angiogenesis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Th1 cells</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Immunology and Infectious Disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Life Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2923</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-08-13T21:24:23Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Modulating T cell Responses to Control Stromal Keratitis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Veiga Parga, Tamara Antia</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Herpetic stromal keratitis (SK) is an immunoinflammatory corneal lesion caused by herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection. This infection, in some cases, can result in a chronic immunoinflammatory lesion that is the most common cause of infectious blindness in the developed world. Studies in animal models have revealed that SK lesions are orchestrated mainly by IFN-gamma producing CD4+ T cells (Th1) and neutrophils that infiltrate the corneal stroma.
The first part of this dissertation (I) reviews literature on HSV induced corneal SK immunopathology and the role of Tregs in viral infections. It also focuses on the understanding of HSV-1 induced immunoinflammatory events in the corneas, particularly T cells. The next three parts (II-IV) concentrate on the inflammatory and regulatory mechanisms that happen following HSV-1 infection in both, the cornea and secondary lymphoid tissues, and the use of therapies to control the inflammatory immune responses and the immunopathological lesions. Results in Part II evaluate the role of regulatory T cells in controlling the progression of the inflammatory lesions during the clinical phase of SK and the mechanisms used by Tregs to control immunopathology. Results of the third section show that modulating the aryl hydrocarbon receptor signaling by the use of TCDD shifts the balance toward regulatory T cells, mainly by inducing apoptosis on T effectors and generating Tregs, which results in diminished severity of SK. The fourth section describes the role of lymphotoxin-alpha (LT-a) after HSV infection, a proinflammatory molecule that can be secreted by or expressed in some subsets of T cells. Depletion of LT-a positive T cells, by the use of a monoclonal antibody seemed to be an effective approach to terminate Th1 responses thereby reducing the severity of lesions.
Collectively, in these studies, experiments were designed to understand the role of regulatory T cells during the disease and to control the progression of ongoing inflammatory reactions by developing different therapeutic strategies for SK, the most common cause of infectious blindness in the Western World.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1789</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2923&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>HSV-1</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>SK</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Th1</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Treg</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>immunopathology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Disease Modeling</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Eye Diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Immune System Diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Virus Diseases</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2775</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-08-13T21:24:25Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Geographic and Temporal Epidemiology of Campylobacteriosis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Weisent, Jennifer</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Campylobacteriosis is a leading cause of gastroenteritis in the United States. The focus of this research was to (i) analyze and predict spatial and temporal patterns and associations for campylobacteriosis risk and (ii) compare the utility of advanced modeling methods. Laboratory-confirmed Campylobacter case data, obtained from the Foodborne Diseases Active Surveillance Network were used in all investigations.
We compared the accuracy of forecasting techniques for campylobacteriosis risk in Minnesota, Oregon and Georgia and found that time series regression, decomposition, and Box-Jenkins Autoregressive Integrated Moving Averages reliably predict monthly risk of infection for campylobacteriosis. Decomposition provided the fastest, most accurate, user-friendly method.
Secondly, forecasting models were used to predict monthly climatic effects on the risk of campylobacteriosis in Georgia. The objectives were to (i) assess temporal patterns of campylobacteriosis risk (ii) compare univariate forecasting models with those that incorporate precipitation and temperature and (iii) investigate alternatives to random walk series and non random occurrences that could be outliers. We found significant regional associations between campylobacteriosis risk and climatic factors and control charting identified high risk time periods.
Our spatial study in Tennessee compared standardized risk estimates and investigated high risk spatial clustering of campylobacteriosis at three geographic scales. Spatial scan methods identified overlapping clusters (p
Objectives of the second study were to (i) identify socioeconomic determinants of the geographic disparities of campylobacteriosis risk (ii) investigate if regression coefficients demonstrate spatial variability and (iii) compare the performance of four modeling approaches: negative binomial, spatial lag, global and local Poisson geographically weighted regression. Local models had the best fit and identified associations between socioeconomic factors and geographic disparities in campylobacteriosis risk. Significant variables included race, unemployment rate, education attainment, urbanicity, and divorce rate.
Recent technological advancements have opened a virtually limitless ‘toolbox’ of analytical methods and offer novel means of identifying temporal spikes, spatial clusters and geographic disparities in campylobacteriosis risk that expand and hone our ability to create cost efficient, needs-based prevention and control measures.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1792</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2775&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Campylobacter</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>spatial and temporal modeling</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>GIS</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>time series</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Applied Statistics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Longitudinal Data Analysis and Time Series</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Public Health</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3346</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-09-16T20:25:06Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Control of p27 Localization and Degradation by the PI3 Kinase Akt/PKB pathway in MCF-7 Breast Cancer Cells</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Bradbury, Marissa J.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Breast cancer is caused by a variety of environmental and genetic factors that influence cell growth and survival. Changes in the level or function of cell cycle regulatory proteins are often associated with breast cancer.  Low expression of the cell cycle inhibitor, p27Kip1, is associated with aggressive breast tumors.  Clinical observations have inspired studies to analyze p27 as a potential target for signal transduction pathways in cancer cells. The stability of p27 determines it’s ability to regulate the cell cycle, and changes in transcription and translation of p27 are less influential. The regulation of the cellular localization of p27 by signal transduction pathways has become a focus of recent research. This study attempts to clarify how Akt regulates p27 localization and stability, and what implications this data may have on tumor growth and metastasis. Cells were transfected with MryAkt plasmid to artificially activate Akt. Immunoflorescence and cell fractionation results verified that MryAkt causes cytoplasmic retention of p27 in MCF-7 breast cancer cells. Labeling experiments with 35S methionine demonstrated that MryAkt causes  nascent p27 to accumulate in the cytoplasm .Metabolic pulse chase labeling and cyclohexamide experiments also determined that p27 was stabilized by MryAkt.  Degradation in the nuclear and cytoplasmic compartments was unaffected by Akt, which supports the hypothesis that MryAkt effects only p27 localization, and the stabilization of p27 by Akt is a result of its cytoplasmic retention. Lastly, the mitogen estradiol has similar effects on p27 as MryAkt, proving that estrogen can influence p27 through the Akt pathway.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2004-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1917</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3346&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3449</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-09-24T16:54:38Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>“Effects of n-3 and n-6 Polyunsaturated Fatty Acids on Human Promyelocytic HL- 60 Cells</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Gillis, Robert Clements</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Enteral nutrition with eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA; 20:5 n-3) and γ-linolenic acid (GLA; 18:3 n-6) decreased pulmonary inflammation by reducing neutrophil counts and chemotactic factors in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid during acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). We hypothesize that the antiinflammatory effects of EPA and GLA may be due, in part, to induction of neutrophil apoptosis. Neutrophil apoptosis is an important physiological process in the resolution of pulmonary inflammation. Furthermore, pro-inflammatory eicosanoids formed from arachidonic acid (AA) by lipoxygenase (LO) and cyclooxygenase (COX) pathways have been shown to inhibit apoptosis in certain cell types. The purpose of this dissertation is to determine whether EPA and GLA, alone or in combination, trigger apoptotic cell death in the human promyelocytic leukemia HL-60 cell line. This dissertation will also determine whether inhibition of LO and COX increases apoptosis with AA, the combination of EPA and GLA, and EPA in HL-60 cells, in vitro. Finally, this dissertation will determine the apoptotic gene profile of EPA/GLA-treated HL-60 cells.
Study 1, HL-60 cells were incubated with 10, 20, 50, and 100 μM EPA, GLA or various combinations of EPA and GLA for 2, 4, 8, 12 and 24 hours. Oleic acid (18:1 n-9) was used as a fatty acid control. Flow cytometry using dualstaining with propidium iodide and annexin V-FITC assessed apoptosis, necrosis and viability. Apoptosis was verified by DNA fragmentation as assessed by agarose gel electrophoresis. EPA, GLA, and various combinations of EPA and GLA significantly induced apoptosis and reduced cell viability in HL-60 cells. vi Viability was significantly reduced to the same extent with the combination of 50 μM EPA\20 μM GLA as compared with 100 μM EPA. These data indicate that EPA and GLA, alone or in combination, reduce cell survival by induction of apoptosis. Thus, induction of apoptosis by select dietary n-3 (EPA) and n-6 (GLA) polyunsaturated fatty acids may be the mechanism of reduces pulmonary inflammation in ARDS.
Study 2 was conducted as follows: HL-60 cells were incubated with 50 μM AA and an enzyme inhibitor (1-10 μM) for either COX, LO, 12-LO, and 5-LO for 12 hours. Flow cytometry was used to assess viability, apoptosis, and necrosis. Apoptosis was further assessed using TUNEL and DNA fragmentation. The highest concentration of LO inhibitors, but not COX inhibitors, decreased viability and increased apoptosis and necrosis in the presence of exogenous AA. These results suggest that disruption of the metabolism of AA by LO, in particular 5-LO, decreases cell survival and increases apoptosis. Thus, downstream metabolic processing of AA by LO but not COX plays a critical role in the regulation of HL- 60 cell apoptosis.
Study 3 was conducted as follows: HL-60 cells were incubated with 50 μM EPA /20 μM GLA in the presence of an enzyme inhibitor (1-10 μM) for 12 hours. Compounds were used to inhibit COX (ibuprofen), 12-LO (baicalein), or 5-LO (AA-861). Flow cytometry assessed viability, apoptosis, and necrosis. 5- LO inhibition reduced cell viability and increased cell death (apoptosis+necrosis) in EPA/GLA-treated HL-60 cells. Inhibition of COX 1 and 2 and 12-LO had no significant effect on cellular viability and death in EPA/GLA-treated HL-60 cells. vii Adding leukotriene B4 counteracted the effect of 5-LO inhibition on apoptosis in EPA/GLA-treated HL-60 cells. These data suggest that the processing of EPA and GLA by 5-LO is critical to HL-60 cell survival.
Study 4 was conducted as follows: HL-60 cells were incubated with 50 μM EPA in the presence of an enzyme inhibitor (1-10 μM) for 12 hours. Compounds were used to inhibit either COX 1 and 2 (ibuprofen), 5-, 12-, 15-LO (NDGA), 12-LO (baicalein), 5-LO (AA-861), and 5-LO activating protein (MK- 886). Eicosanoid (0.001-1.0 μM) add back experiments were also conducted; LTB4 and 5-HETE with 5-LO inhibition and 12-HETE with 12-LO inhibition. Flow cytometry, TUNEL assay, and caspase-3 western blotting were used to assess apoptosis. Inhibition of COX 1 and 2 had no effect on apoptosis. Inhibition of 5- LO and 12-LO significantly increased apoptosis in EPA-treated HL-60 cells. Furthermore, addition of LTB4 reduced apoptosis to levels significantly lower than EPA-treated HL-60 cells alone. 5-HETE and 12-HETE also lowered apoptosis to control levels. These data indicate that inhibition of LO, particularly 5-LO, increased apoptosis in EPA-treated HL-60 cells. Furthermore, this study clearly demonstrated that the products of the LO enzymes, particularly LTB4, are critical in the regulation of apoptosis in EPA-treated HL-60 cells.
Study 5 was conducted as follows: HL-60 cells were incubated with 50 μM EPA and 20 μM GLA for 12 hours. Apoptotic gene profiles were assessed using GEArray original series human apoptosis-2 gene arrays. Total RNA was extracted and probes were synthesized with a primer mix unique for each array. Arrays were hybridized and developed in a non-isotopic manner. Arrays were viii visualized using a 16-bit CCD camera. The apoptotic gene profile for no treatment and EPA/GLA-treated HL-60 cells after 12-hours differed from each other. When comparing density values as a percent of control, all genes assayed were down-regulated. When comparing arrays’ relative intensities, several genes were different between control and treatment groups. For example, Bad, Bax, and Fas were down regulated and Bax, Bcl-2, and p53 were up regulated as compared with control.
This dissertation has provided a possible mechanism for the observed effect of EPA and GLA in human and animal studies of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS): i.e., that enteral nutrition with specialized diets containing EPA and GLA reduced the number of neutrophils and reduced the levels of LTB4 in the bronchoalveolar lavage fluid, reduced pulmonary inflammation, and improved clinical outcomes in patients and animals with ARDS. This dissertation demonstrates that the observed clinical results may be due to increased neutrophil apoptosis induced by EPA and GLA. Induction of apoptosis likely occurs through a change in the eicosanoid profile as well a genetic change through the up-regulation and down-regulation of various pro- and anti-apoptotic genes. Thus, the ability to alter the inflammatory cell phospholipids profile to reduce the amount of AA available for metabolism to pro-inflammatory eicosanoids, in conjunction with 5-lipoxygenase inhibitory compounds, may lead to new therapies that will increase neutrophil apoptosis and provide a injurylimiting pathway in the resolution of pulmonary inflammation in ARDS.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2003-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2016</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3449&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Chemicals and Drugs</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3488</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-09-26T15:24:41Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Expression and Characterization of the MHC Class II Transactivator in K-562 Cells</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Day, Noel Elyssa</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The K-562 cell line was developed from the pleural effusion of a patient with chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML) in blast crisis and has served as an excellent model to study the properties of CML cells. The highly undifferentiated cells can be induced by a variety of chemicals to follow multiple pathways of differentiation. When K-562 cells were treated with phorbol myristate acetate (PMA), they exhibited accessory cell functions by replacing monocytes in the activation of resting Th2 lymphocytes. However, K-562 cells are negative for the expression of class II major histocompatibility complex (MHC) antigens HLA-DR, -DP, and -DQ. The focus of this study was to determine the functional capacity of the class II transactivator (CIITA), a crucial regulatory factor of MHC class II genes, in K-562 cells. CIITA is a co-activator, which is regulated in a tissue-specific manner by four alternative promoters. The transcription factor is recruited to the MHC class II promoter by factors that associate with the promoter, such as regulatory factor X (RFX). The CIITA mRNA is present in K-562 cells and, due to alternative splicing, there is an insertion of an additional genomic sequence not present in the wild-type. The insertion occurs at the carboxy terminus of the CIITA gene, introducing a stop codon at nucleotide 2796, which results in a truncated protein of 932 rather than 1130 amino acids. Although a truncation of this type does not interfere with the ability of CIITA to associate with the MHC class II promoter or with the RFX complex in vivo, it does lead to an inactive protein, which might explain the absence of MHC class II molecules on K-562 cells. The most active CIITA promoter in these cells is promoter III, which is generally specific to B cells. Although IFN-g treatment of K-562 cells does not result in MHC class II expression, the IFN- g inducible CIITA promoter IV does exhibit low levels of basal activity, and the activity of promoter IV is greatly enhanced upon treatment with IFN- g. These results provide insight into the role of CIITA in malignant cells, as well as supporting the hypothesis that the negative expression of MHC class II molecules is caused by the alternatively spliced CIITA transcript identified in K-562 cells.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2001-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2052</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3488&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-3326</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-09-26T18:58:33Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Agouti Mice Models to Study the Diabetogenicity of FK506 (Tacrolimus)</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Joshi, Rashika</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Dominant mutations in the promoter region of the mouse agouti gene lead to a syndrome characterized by agouti yellow coat color, obesity, hyperinsulinemia, hyperglycemia, type II diabetes and increased linear growth. The mechanism of agouti modulation of the coat color development as well as obesity involves competitive antagonism of the ? -melanocortin stimulating hormone at its receptor.
Hyperplasia of the pancreatic ? cells in agouti mice precedes the development of obesity. Enhanced insulin secretion is induced in vitro by agouti effects on calcium influx into islet cells. Preliminary testing of insulin producing pancreatic cells has shown that exposure to high doses of an immunosuppressive drug tacrolimus (FK506) altered the secretion of insulin. The hypothesis of the present study is that FK506 treatment of transgenic mice, which either overexpress the agouti gene ubiquitously or in the adipose tissue, may alter expression of agouti mRNA and protein. Agouti mice also have an impairment of the immune system thus, another hypothesis to be tested was if immunosuppression by FK506 would amplify the agouti phenotype.
There was decrease in food intake and glucose levels in the aP2 mice with Tacrolimus (FK506). There was no detection of agouti mRNA or protein in adipose or pancreatic tissue of wild type mice and no significant effect of FK506 on agouti mRNA or protein expression in the aP2 mice. Toxic effects of FK506 at this dose in both mice were not significant.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2001-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1968</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3326&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3562</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-01T19:34:16Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Analysis and Diagnostic Implications of the Fusion and Attachment Protein Genes of Respiratory Syncytial Viruses of Ruminants</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Eleraky, Nasser Zakaria</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Respiratory syncytial viruses (RSVs) in ruminants are classified into two subgroups, ovine RSV and bovine RSV. Although ovine RSV infects cattle, its contribution to bovine respiratory tract disease has not been established which is an important issue for vaccine development in cattle.
Diagnosis by virus isolation or serology has low or variable sensitivity and/or specificity and PCR has been recommended as a rapid and sensitive technique for RSV detection. Prior to this study, a laboratory test to differentiate between bovine and ovine RSVs did not exist.
First, the nucleotide sequence of the ovine RSV fusion (F) gene was determined and compared with representative strains of bovine RSV and human RSV subgroups A and B. The ovine RSV F gene has 85% and 72-73% nucleotide identity with those of bovine RSV and human RSV respectively. The predicted amino acid sequence of the ovine RSV F gene has 94% and 83-84% amino acid identity with those of bovine RSV and human RSV respectively.
Two RT-PCR assays have been developed for simultaneous detection of bovine and ovine respiratory syncytial viruses. One, a set of primers amplified a 426 bp fragment of either bovine or ovine RSV F gene (RT-PCR F). PCR-F products could be distinguished by EcoRI or BstYI restriction endonuclease cleavage. In the other assay, a set of primers amplified a 542 bp fragment of either ovine or bovine RSV G gene (RTPCR G). EcoO109I and RsaI restriction enzymes were used to differentiate between the ovine and bovine PCR-G products. Sequencing of the PCR products confirmed the fidelity of both assays.
The two assays were evaluated using eight bovine RSV isolates, one ovine RSV, one bighorn sheep RSV, one caprine RSV, two human RSV isolates and several viruses associated with bovine respiratory tract disease.
The two PCR assays described in this study potentially constitute sensitive and specific means for simultaneous detection of bovine and ovine RSV and differentiation between them. However, RT-PCR F followed by the appropriate restriction enzyme cleavage may be superior to RT-PCR G to discriminate between the two ruminant RSV subgroups and for determining the relative contribution of ovine and bovine RSV to the pathogenesis of bovine respiratory tract disease. This is relevant to the complete understanding of RSV epidemiology and immunoprophylaxis.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2002-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2117</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3562&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3621</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-07T20:03:56Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>BAD is a Central Player in Cell Death and Cell Cycle Regulation in Breast Cancer Cells</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Fernando, Romaine Ingrid</dc:creator>
<dc:description>BAD is a Central Player in Cell Death and Cell Cycle Regulation in Breast Cancer Cells
The estrogen, 17-b estradiol (E2) can stimulate proliferation or induce differentiation or death depending on the cell context.  In MCF 7 cells, an estrogen receptor (ER) positive human breast cancer cell line, E2 has been shown to stimulate cell proliferation and may have an anti-apoptotic effect.  E2 rapidly activates mitogen activated protein kinases (MAPKs) in mammalian cells in an ER dependent fashion. The mechanisms underlying and the physiological significance of the signaling through MAPK remain to be determined. This signal pathway may represent a potential mechanism by which E2 regulates cell proliferation, growth as well as apoptosis.  Recent observation of Raf-1 kinase (which relays signals from cell surface receptor tyrosine kinase to MAPKs) activation by E2 in MCF 7 cells explained a possible link between cell surface and intracellular components of the signaling pathway.  PI-3 kinase and its down stream member protein kinase B (PKB/Akt) have been shown to be strongly involved in mitogenic and anti-apoptotic signaling in MCF 7 cells.
Chemical and biological inhibition of PI-3 kinase diminished E2 supported cell survival and concomitant Akt, MAPK (ERK) and its down stream target p90RSK activities.  On the other hand, interference of endogenous Ras with a dominant negative construct abolished signal mechanisms involving ERK as well as Akt.  These observations suggested that Ras/ERK and PI-3 Kinase pathways could operate as separate entities or cross talk and cooperate to enhance survival or impede apoptosis in MCF 7 cells in the presence of E2.
BCL2 family proteins play critical decision-making roles during apoptosis.  BH3 domain only, pro-apoptotic member, BAD has been intensively investigated for its contribution in regulation of apoptosis at the mitochondrial level.  Post-translational phosphorylation modulates BAD’s function and, most survival factors impose inhibitory phosphorylations on BAD via active Akt and MAPK pathways.
E2 rapidly induces Akt and ERK signaling pathways resulting in phosphorylation of BAD on two serine residues, and abolishes apoptosis in response to a variety of stimuli in MCF-7 cells.  Therefore, we hypothesized that E2 targets BAD for its anti-apoptotic effect.  Data presented clearly show that E2 effects are at least partly mediated via Ras originated ERK/p90RSK and PI-3 kinase/Akt pathways that add inhibitory phosphate groups onto corresponding serine 75 and 99 residues of BAD there by inactivating its pro-apoptotic tendencies.  We demonstrate the significance of BAD and its functional serine residues in E2 mediated anti-apoptosis with studies conducted with anti-sense mRNA and phosphorylation site mutants of BAD.  Over-expression of wild type or phosphorylation site mutant of BAD did not enhance the basal cell death, which was remarkably lessened by the inhibition of endogenous BAD.  E2 could rescue cells from TNFa induced death in control cultures and in wild type BAD transfected cells but not in phosphorylation site mutant BAD expressing cells.  This observation agrees with previous studies that demonstrate the importance of BAD’s phosphorylation sites in growth factor mediated cell protection.  This study shows for the first time that E2 is an anti-apoptotic agent in breast cancer cells whose response is mediated by non-genomic cytoplasmic signal networks that converge on BAD in turn regulating the mitochondrial membrane potential change.
When transiently over-expressed, wild type or dual phosphorylation site mutant of BAD did not induce apoptosis, as observed in the first part of this study, but the rate of growth of these cells was remarkably low compared to the untransfected or control vector transfected cells.  This suggested that the presence of extra amount of BAD could reduce the growth of MCF-7 cells.  Similar phenomenon have been reported with the overexpression of BCL2 in malignant as well as normal epithelial cells.  When over expressed, BCL2 arrests cell cycle in G0/G1 phase and this effect appears to depend on the amino terminal BH4 domain.  Interestingly in a variety of epithelial cell types, endogenous BCL2 was shown to localize to the chromosomes of mitotic nuclei.  This pattern of BCL2 expression is considered to be indicative of its special role in cell proliferation.
We hypothesized that BAD also exhibits a cell cycle related function in breast cancer epithelial cells, which was tested in the second part of this study.  We evaluated the distribution pattern of nuclear BAD in several breast cancer cell lines.  BAD overexpression lessened cyclin D1protein levels that agreeably correlate with the G1-S transition block observed.  Cyclin D1 regulation by BAD was assayed at the transcriptional level using a luciferase reporter under the control of the cyclin D1 promoter.  In asynchronous cells and in synchronous and E2 treated cells, BAD over-expression significantly reduced the cyclin D1 reporter activity.  Overexpression of a dual phosphorylation site mutant of BAD did not alter the cyclin D1 expression pattern or the cell cycle progression suggesting an involvement of these serine residues in BAD’s nuclear functions.  Furthermore, the BH3 domain deletion mutant and the S91A mutant, both of which carry intact S75 and S99 residues, exerted inhibitory effects similar to that of wild type BAD.
Wild type BAD overexpression as well as BAD depletion from nuclear extracts diminished the labeled AP-1/TRE DNA binding with the nuclear factors.  This demonstrates that BAD is capable of binding and sequestering some components from the nuclear extracts which bind with AP-1/TRE element.  Collectively our data suggest that in addition to pro-apoptotic functions, BAD regulates the cell cycle at least partly via AP-1/TRE element.  These functions appear to depend on its S75 and S99 phosphorylation status that are also the targets of pro-survival mechanisms.  Further, these results also suggest that the AP-1 transcription regulation by BAD is kept at its minimal level in normal cells as a result of the fine balance of its phosphorylation state.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2004-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2170</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3621&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3650</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-08T17:37:29Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Bordetella bronchiseptica: A Candidate Mucosal Vaccine Vector</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Rajeev, Sreekumari</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Bordetella bronchiseptica colonizes the upper respiratory tract of a wide variety of mammals and is involved in diseases such as kennel cough in dogs, atrophic rhinitis in pigs and upper respiratory tract infections of laboratory animals. Studies were focused on developing a heterologous antigen expression system in B. bronchiseptica and to evaluate the potential of this organism as a candidate mucosal vaccine vector. Since the role of Bordetella bronchiseptica and Pasteurella multocida toxin (PMT) in the disease atrophic rhinitis of pigs was well documented, this research was focused in the possibility of developing a refined vaccine to control this disease. A promoter region related to heat shock protein genes was identified using a green fluorescent protein reporter system. This promoter drove high- level expression of GFP compared to a tac promoter or B. bronchiseptica fim N gene promoter. A nontoxic protective P. multocida toxin fragment and GFP were expressed in B.bronchiseptica in a broad-host-range plasmid vector PBBR1MCS2 under the control of the promoter region identified. Colonization kinetics, plasmid stability, and immune responses generated following intranasal inoculation of recombinant B. bronchiseptica were evaluated. While wild type and recombinant B. bronchiseptica colonized the mouse respiratory tract effectively, the plasmid was completely lost from the organism after 72 hours post- inoculation. After a single intranasal inoculation, B. bronchiseptica specific IgM, IgA and IgG responses were detected in serum and respiratory lavage. However, PMT-specific antibodies were not detected. Four intranasal inoculations with B. bronchiseptica expressing green fluorescent protein (GFP) induced a GFP-specific systemic and mucosal immune response, while similar inoculations with B. bronchiseptica expressing PMT fragment did not induce a PMT-specific immune response.
This study also evaluated the immune response to a chimeric protein generated by combining a gene fragment encoding neutralizing epitopes of Mannheimia haemolytica leukotoxin and a fimbrial protein gene (fim N) from B. bronchiseptica. Immunization of mice with the recombinant chimeric protein elicited a significantly stronger anti-leukotoxin antibody response than comparable immunizations with fusion proteins lacking FIM N. The chimeric protein exhibited more stability. Leukotoxin is an important virulence factor in shipping fever pneumonia in feedlot cattle and is a critical protective antigen. This chimeric protein may be a candidate for inclusion in new generation vaccines against shipping fever pneumonia. The results of these studies strongly support the potential for developing B. bronchiseptica as a candidate mucosal vaccine vector and FIM N as a carrier protein for heterologous antigens.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2002-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2182</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3650&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Medical Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3664</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-08T20:51:19Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Investigation of Cognitive Impairments using functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) and Positron Emission Tomography (PET) in patients with mild Alzheimer's disease</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Stanonik, Mateja de Leonni</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Awareness and interest in diseases, which pertain to cognitive and affective functions in the elderly, has been increasing, as the proportion of elderly people in the population grows larger. Afflicting an estimated 19 million people worldwide the syndrome of dementia comprises some of the most prevalent and devastating diseases. The development of Alzheimer's disease (AD), the most frequent cause of dementia in the elderly, is associated with a number of pathogenic mechanisms that include genetic, immunologic, and vascular factors. AD is often unrecognized in its earliest stages even though it is the most common cause of dementia in the aged population, yet impossible to diagnose precisely without invasive techniques, particularly at the onset of the disease.
AD accounts for 70% of all cases of late-onset dementia (after 65 years of age). Since the incidence of AD doubles every 5 years after 60 years of age (Tanzi et al 2000), the incidence of AD is expected to increase further as more people live to advanced ages. Characteristic neuropathological features of AD include neurofibrillary tangles (NFTs), and extracellular deposits of b-amyloid protein (Ab) in senile plaques (SPs). However, AD seems to be etiologically as well as genetically heterogeneous, with probable interactions between genetic and nongenetic factors. The initial deficit in AD is normally in short-term and working memory, which progresses gradually for several years before impairments in other cognitive domains such as language, semantic memory, orientation, and visuospatial functions become evident. Short-term as well as working memory is built from several different types of attentional mechanisms, which allow for normal functioning and memory performance. This study postulates that a deficit in a subtype of attention, called selective attention, becomes impaired before evident deficits in short-term memory are observable. The anterior cingulate cortex (ACC) is believed to play an essential role in the mechanisms of selective attention in normal subjects. Moreover, the ACC is thought to be responsible for the initiation and motivation of goal-oriented behaviors. Impairments in ACC function produce marked deficits in selective attention, and may contribute to apathy and anosognosia seen in as many as one-half of mild AD patients. Mild AD patients that exhibit anosognosia are unaware of their symptoms, which are usually manifested as unawareness of short-term memory loss, and orientation function. These ACC impairments have implications in the clinical management of AD patients (i.e. driving).
Specifically, this study examines the contributions of the cingulate cortex to impairments in selective attention and anosognosia in mild AD patients. The cingulate cortex is a part of the mesial temporal lobe memory system known to be affected early in the course of AD. The main purpose of the study was two-fold: a) to investigate differences in brain activation between mild AD patients and normal controls when performing the Counting Stroop Test; and b) to investigate the biological substrates of attentional impairments and anosognosia in mild AD patients using different approaches of measuring cortical activity. Two functional imaging methods: functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) and 18-Fluorodeoxyglucose Positron Emission Tomography (18-FDG-PET) were implemented. Recent development of functional neuroimaging techniques, particularly functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), has made the evaluation of small brain structures, such as the different regions of the cingulate cortex, conceivable. In addition to the functional evaluation of the cingulate cortex by fMRI and PET, the anatomical integrity of brain structures was evaluated using high-resolution MRI in all of the study participants.
The Counting Stroop, a Stroop Test-variant specialized for fMRI and PET was used as the activation paradigm to test selective attention. Selective attention reflects upon the ability to choose successfully what an organism wishes to analyze in the environment and to ignore what it should disregard, which contributes to the overall integrity of cognitive function, and subsequently, behavior. A total of 23 unmedicated subjects from two groups were examined: 10 patients with probable AD according to NINCDS-ADRDA criteria (McKhann et al., 1984), and 13 cognitively normal age-matched control subjects. All of the participants performed the Counting Stroop Test while undergoing the fMRI scan; the mild AD patients also performed the Counting Stroop Test before having the FDG-PET scan. In addition, all of the subjects were also administered several cognitive assessments: 1. the Self Test (ST) and the Mini Mental Status Exam (MMSE) to stage the AD patients according to impairments in general cognitive function, 2. the Stroop Test to evaluate impairments in selective attention, 3. the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II), and 4.)the Anosognosia Questionnaire to assess AD patients’ awareness of symptoms.
Both groups of participants showed highly significant correlation between the written Stroop Test scores and the Counting Stroop Test scores exemplifying high degree of validity and reliability of the newly developed Counting Stroop Task. Furthermore, the AD and normal group differed significantly in the written Stroop Test scores: the normal control group had a mean score of 75 12 words/45 seconds compared to the mild AD group which mean score obtained on the written Stroop Test was 23 8 words/45 seconds.
While there were individual differences, the mild AD group consistently showed significant blood level oxygen dependent (BOLD) decreases in the ACC while undergoing the Counting Stroop Test as shown by the fMRI scans. When compared to the normal subjects the patients’ fMRI images showed that the anterior areas of the cingulate cortex had significantly increased BOLD activity. On the other hand, the mild AD group did activate the medial frontal lobe (bilaterally), the inferior frontal lobe (bilaterally), the insular cortex (bilaterally), the left caudate nucleus, the right thalamus, the medial and inferior occipital lobes, and the right posterior parietal lobe. Therefore, these results indicate that the mild AD group activated the frontostriatal-insular network; the absence of the ACC activation could not have been caused by poor neuronal responses.
The normal group showed significantly increased BOLD activity in the ACC bilaterally, the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, the superior parietal lobule, the inferior parietal lobule, the middle and inferior occipital lobe, and the inferior orbital cortex. Direct comparisons between the mild AD and the normal control group indicated significant differences in the following areas: the left dorsolateral prefrontal area, the ACC bilaterally, and posterior parietal areas bilaterally. The MRI anatomical scans of mild AD patients did not show significant focal lobar atrophy changes, which are typical of AD pathology; instead mostly age-appropriate atrophy was observed. The anatomical MRI findings were similar for the normal control group as well. In order to determine whether an association between anosognosia and BOLD activations in the ACC exists, the mild AD subjects were divided into 2 groups: those mild AD patients with no significant activations in the ACC compared to those mild AD subjects with one or more significant activations in the ACC. The results confirmed that a significant difference in anosognosia scores in those mild AD patients with no significant activations in the ACC compared to those mild AD subjects with at least one significant activation in the ACC existed (mean difference in AQ score 0.81, p&lt;.02).
The qualitative analyses of FDG-PET images indicated decreased utilization of glucose in the tempoparietal and temporal lobes in the mild AD group. This is a typical pattern of probable AD in the moderate to late stages as seen on FDG-PET without using an activation task. The same pattern was quantitatively determined using the Counting Stroop Test as the activation paradigm in the mild AD group. The coregistration of functional images (FDG-PET) combined with subjects’ own anatomical MRI images was performed to design improved, more efficient method of accurate specification of significant glucose hyper- or hypo-activated areas. After subtracting the activation FDG-PET images from the baseline FDG-PET images, the following focal areas of decreased glucose metabolism were determined quantitatively: the thalamus, the superior ACC, the superior colliculi, and the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex. In addition, a significant loss of the superior portion ACC glucose uptake was found in five of the six anosognosic patients with mild AD (p&lt;.01). The magnitude of the glucose uptake loss correlated positively with the mild AD patients’ Anosognosia Questionnaire scores. Thus, functional hypoactivity of the ACC was strongly indicative of anosognosia deficits in mild AD patients.
In conclusion, compared to the normal age-matched control subjects, all of the mild AD patients showed prominent impairments in selective attention as detected by the test for selective attention, the Color Word Stroop Test (CSWT). In addition, both groups of subjects showed highly significant correlation between the written CSWT scores and the Counting Stroop Test scores (obtained during the activation task) exemplifying a high degree of validity of the newly developed Counting Stroop Test. The absence of significant fMRI activations in the left dorsolateral prefrontal area, the ACC bilaterally, and posterior parietal areas bilaterally as well as decreased glucose metabolism in the thalamus, the superior ACC, the superior colliculi, and the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex determined by FDG-PET was determined to be associated with impairments in selective attention in the mild AD patients but not normal control subjects. Furthermore, the functional hypoactivity of the ACC of those mild AD patients with anosognosia indicated that these patients were generally not aware of their cognitive shortcomings. Anosognosia in mild AD patients appears to represent a defect in the ACC, and may thus denote specific cognitive abnormality of selective attention.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2002-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2199</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3664&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3726</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-10T19:19:16Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Respiratory, Cardiovascular and Abdominal Anatomy of the Ringed Seal (Phoca hispida)</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Smodlaka, Hrvoje</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This study investigated the anatomy the ringed seal (Phoca hispida) cardiovascular system (heart and large vessels) and lower respiratory tract (lung), as well as the topographic anatomy of the seal abdomen.
The ringed seal heart is dorsoventrally flattened, with each ventricle residing on its respective side within the thoracic cage. The heart lies horizontal, parallel to the sternum. The right ventricle is long, spacious and thin walled. The right coronary artery continues as the subsinuosal interventricular branch, making it different from domestic carnivores.
The aortic bulb is a large structure in comparison to the equivalent structure in terrestrial mammals, which is hardly noticeable. It lies in contact with the cranioventral aspect of the thoracic cavity. The aortic arch gives rise to three major blood vessels; brachiocephalic trunk, left common carotid and left subclavian artery. The paired caudal vena cavae continue the pelvic venous plexus as paired vessels through the caudal abdominal cavity. At the level of the third lumbar vertebral body the two separate limbs converge into a single vena cava. Soon after this junction as the hepatic veins join the vena cava, they expand into a large hepatic sinus. As the caudal vena cava passes through the diaphragm, muscle fibers of the diaphragm form a caval sphincter. The azygos veins are paired and join into a common trunk before emptying into the cranial vena cava as it enters the right atrium. Intercostal arteries perforate the right azygos vein. There are also communications between left and right azygos veins via short anastomosing branches. The pericardial venous plexus is present in the mediastinal pleura as a loop encompassing the apex of the heart. It is comprised of convoluted veins that eventually drain into the caudal vena cava as a single trunk. Pulmonary arteries are paired vessels that divide into caudal and cranial branches at the level of the principal bronchi. Three common pulmonary veins drain the lung lobes into the left atrium.
The lungs are subdivided into seven lung lobes. The right lung is divided into cranial, middle, caudal and accessory lung lobes. The left lung is divided into cranial, middle and caudal lobes. The pulmonary trunk upon reaching the atrial face of the heart divides into the left and right pulmonary arteries that lie adjacent to and follow the dichotomy of the bronchial tree. Three common pulmonary veins are formed by merging of the lobar veins. The common left and right veins drain their respective cranial and middle lobes while the caudal common vein drains both left and right caudal lobes and the accessory lobe. The ringed seal has three major tracheobronchial lymph nodes.
Microscopically, the lungs are characterized by a thick subpleural collagenous interstitial tissue, which sends septa deep into the lung parenchyma, thus subdividing the lung lobes into lobules. Segmental bronchi, exhibit a strong elastic fibrous support that is clustered into dense bundles. The bronchial gland duct system of the segmental bronchi is lined with pseudostratified ciliated columnar epithelium with goblet cells. Cartilage support for the bronchial tree extends as far distal as the respiratory bronchiole. Occasionally, respiratory bronchioles have a smooth muscle enhancements at their junction with alveolar ducts. Bronchioles are lined with cuboidal to columnar epithelium. Frequently, bronchioles and respiratory bronchioles have venules covered with squamous epithelium protruding into their lumen.
The ringed seal has the cupula of the diaphragm extending cranially to the level of the ninth thoracic vertebra, and is predominantly occupied by the liver. The liver extends caudally to the level of the 15th thoracic vertebra. The gall bladder is located at the level of the 12th thoracic vertebra. The cardia of the U-shaped stomach is located at the  The body extends caudally and bends back on itself at the level of the first lumbar vertebra, as the major curvature. The pylorus is located at the level of the 12th thoracic vertebra. The spleen is located on the left side, lying between the liver and cardia of the stomach, extending from the level of the 14th thoracic to the second lumbar vertebrae. When viewing CT scans just medial to the spleen’s dorsal border, the silhouette of the pancreas can be identified. The kidneys extend from the level of the second to the fifth lumbar vertebra. The cranial extremity of the right kidney is located more cranial than that of the left kidney.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2004-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2238</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3726&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3808</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-18T20:53:20Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The role of polyglutamine aggregate cytotoxicity in Huntington’s Disease</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Yang, Wen</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Polyglutamine diseases refer to a group of neuro-degenerative diseases including Huntington's disease , that share the same mutational basis: expansion of a CAG repeat coding sequence that encodes for a polyglutamine repeat in the respective proteins. Neuronal intranuclear inclusions (NII) formed by the aggregation of the expanded polyglutamine proteins is a hallmark of polyglutamine diseases. However, it is still under debate whether the polyglutamine aggregates are toxic to the cells, and if so, which aggregated forms are the toxic species. While important data has been provided by the existing transfected cell and transgenic animal models, technical aspects have limited our ability to rigorously interpret this data in terms of molecular and cellular mechanism. A number of comprehensive studies on in vitro polyglutamine aggregation kinetics, and features of the aggregates produced in vitro, provided the foundation to directly address the question of the cytotoxicity of polyglutamine aggregates. In the present study, we designed a new cell model by directly introducing in vitro synthesized polyglutamine aggregates into mammalian cells, both PC-12 and Cos-7, to study the cytotoxicity of different forms of aggregates. We found that cell viability was largely unaffected when polyglutamine aggregates are localized to the cytoplasm; aggregates of polyglutamine peptides containing a nuclear localization signal, however, are localized to nuclei and lead to dramatic cell death. This cytotoxicity is polyglutamine-sequence-specific. We also found that a short polyglutamine peptide (Q20), once aggregated and delivered to the cell nucleus, seems to be equally cytotoxic. Further studies suggest that the mechanism of cell death in this novel model system seems to be apoptotic. Our results support a direct role for polyglutamine aggregates in cytotoxicity and are consistent with a recruitmentsequestration disease mechanism. This is further supported by studies, also described here, in which a polyglutamine aggregation elongation inhibitor protects against cell death induced by nuclear polyglutamine aggregates.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2003-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2353</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3808&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3041</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-28T13:45:53Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Ability of Triclocarban (3,4,4’- trichlorocarbanilide) to induce premalignant breast cell carcinogenesis and enhance 2-Amino-1-methyl-6-phenylimidazo(4,5-b)pyridine (PhIP)-induced breast cell carcinogenesis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Sood, Shilpa</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Chronic exposure to environmental carcinogens may trigger development of sporadic breast cancer, a multistep tumorigenesis process involving aggregation of genetic and epigenetic alterations, resulting in a serial progression from a non-cancerous to precancerous stage and eventually malignant breast cancer. In this study, I used a cellular model that simulates induction and progression of chronic breast cell carcinogenesis using concentrations of environmental carcinogens which are achievable in blood or plasma. Process of carcinogenesis was measured by certain detectable constitutive and transient end points including acquisition of cancer-associated properties, increased ROS prodiction, cell proliferation, DNA damage and activation of Erk-Nox pathway which could be targeted by non-cytotoxic dosages of dietary compounds. Triclocarban (TCC) is an antimicrobial agent present in personal care products. This study was designed to investigate the ability of TCC to act as a co-carcinogen and therefore induce premalignant breast cell carcinogenesis and enhance 2-Amino-1-methyl- 6-phenylimidazo(4,5-b)pyridine (PhIP)-induced breast cell carcinogenesis in MCF10A cells. My results showed that repeated treatments with TCC induced cancer-associated properties of reduced dependence on growth factors and anchorage-independent growth in MCF10A cells. Concurrently, there was increased ROS production, cell proliferation and upregulation of Erk-Nox pathway in response to single as well as long term exposure to TCC. Curcumin, a polyphenolic component extracted from the rhizome, Curcuma longa, was able to suppress these transient and constitutive endpoints induced in breast cells exposed to TCC. MCF10A cells were also subjected to either individual or combined TCC and PhIP exposure. Cells co-treated with TCC and PhIP had significantly higher levels of cancer-associated properties, ROS production, cell proliferation and Erk- Nox pathway activation as compared to cells treated with PhIP alone. The transient and constitutive endpoints induced by co-treatement with TCC and PhIP were significantly suppressed by mimosine, a non protein amino acid isolated from Mimosa pudica and Ergosterol, a sterol found in cell membranes of fungi. These results proved that TCC has the ability to induce breast cell premalignancy and enhance breast cell carcinogenesis induced by PhIP in MCF10A cells. Furthermore, curcumin, ergosterol and mimosine could play promising roles in prevention of sporadic breast cancer.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2486</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3041&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>


		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2919</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-11-05T18:01:12Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Mechanism of LPA-induced lipid uptake in macrophages</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Xu, Kan</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Cardiovascular disease, currently the leading cause of mortality throughout the developed countries, is mainly caused by atherosclerosis, which is recognized as a chronic inflammatory disease. Atherosclerotic plaques are characterized by accumulations of lipid in arterial walls together with infiltration of macrophages. These macrophages differentiate from monocytes which transform into foam cells through phagocytizing various forms of lipid, are believed to be the main component of early atherosclerotic lesions.
Lysophosphatidic acid (LPA), a potent bioactive lipid, regulates a broad range of cellular functions in various cell types. In our findings, LPA-induced macrophages may enhance the lipid uptake effect in both J774A.1-mouse macrophage cell lines and bone-marrow derived macrophages (BMDMs) in a time and dose dependent manner.
To date, LPA activated signaling pathways in macrophage and possible intracellular molecules mediating LPA-triggered foam cell formation wait to be explored. According to our results, we found: 1) LPA receptor 2 and 5 were predominantly expressed than other receptors in macrophages. 2) Protein Kinase D (PKD) underwent activation both on the Ser744/748 activation loop and auto phosphorylation site Ser916 from 2 minutes to 5 minutes upon the addition of LPA. 3) During the early period of LPA treatment, phospho-ERK, phospho-JNK and phospho-P38 all showed signs of short term inhibition - which indicates that MAPK activity had been transiently inhibited in macrophages by LPA. 4) NF-kappaB, a key transcriptional regulator in macrophages, showed no obvious patterns of activation in our investigation through observing that neither IKK nor IKB units were activated upon LPA induction. And this finding excludes the possibility that NF-kappaB pathway is involved in LPA-induced macrophage activation. 5) Our northern blot analysis demonstrated that, SR-B1 and CD36 – two scavenger receptors that are critical in lipid accumulation of macrophages – were up-regulated by LPA.
Collectively, all emerging data leads us to hypothesize that LPA, through its receptors to activate intracellular pathways, mediates downstream gene expression level, then expedites foam cell formation, which may contribute to atherosclerotic lesion formation.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2480</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2919&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>LPA</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>macrophage</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>oxLDL</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>lipid uptake</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiovascular Diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cell Biology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-3312</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-01-22T19:19:02Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Leydig Stem Cell Differentiation in the Prepubertal Hamster (&lt;em&gt;Mesocricetus auratus&lt;/em&gt;)</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hance, Michael W</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Leydig cells in the testis are the primary source of androgens in the adult male mammal. Therefore, the process of Leydig cell differentiation during the prepubertal period is essential to establish the Leydig cell population in the adult. Little has been published regarding the factors that regulate the postnatal Leydig cell differentiation in hamsters. However, it has been observed in adult male hamsters that Leydig cells regress under reduced photoperiods, but recrudesce with re-exposure to normal photoperiods. In the present investigation, the effects of light, hypothyroidism, hyperthyroidism, and melatonin treatment on Leydig cell differentiation in the neonatal-prepubertal hamster are investigated. Six treatment groups of male Syrian Golden hamsters were used. Group I male hamsters were raised under regular light conditions (12hr: 12hr Light:Dark) and group II hamsters were raised under reduced light (23hr: 1hr Dark: Light). Hamsters in Groups III received triidothyronine (T3; 50 μg/ kg. bwt); lactating mothers were injected every four days from birth of pups to day 28, and were maintained under regular light conditions. Hamsters in Group IV were maintained under regular light regimes (12hr: 12hr) and were made hypothyroid by adding 0.1% propylthiouracil to drinking water of lactating mothers from birth to day 28. Hamsters in Group V were raised in dark (similar to Group II), but their mothers received T3 injections similar to those in Group III. Lactating mothers in Group VI received melatonin injections (15 milligrams/ kg. bwt) every other afternoon from birth to day 28. Following euthanasia at postnatal day 28, blood was collected from the heart, serum prepared and stored until assay for hormones: thyroxin (T4), and melatonin.
One testis from each hamster in each group was fixed by whole body perfusion, processed and embedded in epon-aradite. Using 1-micron sections that were stained with Methylene Blue-Azure II, Leydig cell numbers per testis in the experimental groups were quantified by the disector method. Leydig cells were identified by their characteristic morphology and their location in the testis interstitium. The ipsilateral testis from each hamster in each group was incubated in media containing luteinizing hormone (100ng/ml) and used to determine testosterone and androstenedione secretory capacity per testis in vitro. There was a reduction in Leydig cell numbers per testis in D28 hamsters (Group II), D28T3 hamsters (Group V), L28PTU hamsters (Group IV), and L28M hamsters (Group VI) when compared to L28 hamsters (Group I) and L28T3 hamsters (Group III). Significantly increased testosterone secretory capacities were found in the hamster groups D28 (Group II) and L28T3 (Group III) when compared to L28 (Group I). There were significantly reduced testosterone secretory capacities in hamsters in L28PTU (Group IV), L28M (Group VI), and D28T3 (GroupV), compared to L28 (Group I).The majority of the groups were not significantly different in androstenedione secretory capacity per testis except there were significantly lower values in L28PTU (Group IV) and D28T3 (GroupV). L28 (Group I) hamsters had significantly higher serum thyroxin levels than hamsters in D28 (Group II), L28PTU (Group IV), L28M (Group VI). Serum melatonin levels were the lowest in L28 (Group I) hamsters and the highest in L28PTU (Group IV) hamsters. These findings demonstrate that increased levels of melatonin and decreased levels of thyroxin negatively regulate and decreased levels of melatonin and increased levels of thyroxin positively regulate Leydig cell differentiation in the prepubertal hamster testis. It is concluded that thyroid pineal interactions are important in regulating the process of postnatal Leydig cell differentiation in the perpubertal hamster testis.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2005-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1954</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3312&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3604</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-01-22T20:16:20Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>HSV-1 Induced Ocular Angiogenesis: Antiangiogenic Strategies to Prevent Herpetic Stromal Keratitis Pathogenesis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Kim, Bum Seok</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Herpetic stromal keratitis (SK) is an immunopathological and tissue destructive corneal lesion caused by herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection, which induces an intense autoimmune inflammatory response and finally leads blindness. Accumulating evidence using the murine model has shown that Th-1 phenotype CD4+ T cells orchestrating the inflammation mainly contribute the immunopathological reaction in HSV-1 infected cornea. However, prior to CD4+ T cell infiltration into corneal lesions, various innate immune cells recruit and produce numerous inflammatory molecules into the corneal stroma. Interestingly, one prominent event early in the pathogenesis of SK is neovascularization of the usually avascular cornea. It is assumed that various angiogenic factors produced by inflammatory cells trigger the onset of pathological angiogenesis and the newly formed leaky blood vessels may assist corneal access of inflammatory cells orchestrating herpetic SK. Accordingly, inhibition of unwanted angiogenesis in an HSV infected cornea may moderate the pathologic process of SK lesions.
The first part (Part I) of this dissertation focuses on the understanding of HSV-1 induced SK pathogenesis including how abnormal neovascularization is generated after virus infection and how angiogenesis contributes the process of disease. The other parts (Part II, III, IV) explore the use of different antiangiogenic approaches as an effective therapeutic strategy for herpetic SK. Results in Part II demonstrate that the use of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) pathway-specific siRNAs can efficiently knock down their target genes and consequently inhibit HSV induced angiogenesis. Results of the third section (Part III) clarify the antiangiogenic role of IL-18 in the cornea. The data show that IL-18 down-regulates the expression of VEGF and also controls the proliferation of activated endothelial cells in inflammatory conditions. Furthermore, application of DNA encoding IL-18 into cornea diminished herpetic SK lesion severity. The final section (Part IV) explores the utilization of a VEGF receptor-2 (VEGFR-2 or FLK-1) based DNA vaccine to enhance immune response against endothelial cells expressing VEGFR-2. HSV-1 infected mice receiving attenuated Salmonella typhimurium harboring VEGFR-2 exhibited antiangiogenic response and reduced herpetic SK severity. These effects appeared to be due to the ability of cytotoxic CD8+ T cells targeting VEGFR-2 to control virus induced neovascularization.
In this study, experiments were designed to focus on controlling the pathological angiogenesis in herpetic SK model. We hope that these approaches may represent useful therapeutic strategies against neovascularization-related eye diseases.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2005-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2159</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3604&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-3649</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-01-23T15:10:08Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons from the Chattanooga Creek Flood Plain and Their Effects on Endothelial Cells via Group IVC Phospholipase A&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;</dc:title>
<dc:creator>McNeilly, Meghan Scott</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Exposure to environmental pollution can be a contributing factor to the development of cardiovascular disease (CVD). Due to contamination produced by long-term discharge of coal tar wastes into the creek, a 2.5-mile section of the Chattanooga Creek in south Chattanooga was designated as a Superfund site by the USEPA in 1994. In order to further investigate the potential health risks posed by creek contamination, 12 PAHs found in high levels in the sediment of the creek as compared to an uncontaminated control site were evaluated for their effects on the human coronary artery endothelial cell (HCAEC) phospholipase A2 (PLA2)/arachidonic acid (AA) cascade, a pathway known to play a significant role in endothelial cell inflammation, apoptosis, and atherosclerosis. Aortic tissue from feral mice trapped at the Superfund site exhibited an increase in markers of inflammation and apoptosis when compared to mouse tissue from the control site, suggesting that natural exposure to contaminants in the creek results in similar findings as in the in vitro studies. Six of the compounds studied (acenaphthylene, benz [e] acephenanthrylene, benzo [k] fluoranthene, fluoranthene, naphthalene, and phenanthrene) activated the AA cascade by targeting the isoform of PLA2, Group IVC PLA2. Upregulation of the enzyme was associated with an increase in apoptosis of HCAECs, as measured by 3H-AA release and histone fragmentation, as well as Western blot analysis for PARP cleavage. Transfection with siRNA specific for Group IVC decreased the amount of histone fragmentation induced by the six compounds. Two compounds (anthracene and benz [a] anthracene) were inactive. Four compounds (benzo [g,h,i] perylene, chrysene, indeno [1,2,3-c,d] pyrene, and pyrene) fluoresced independently of reagents used to measure histone fragmentation and were not able to be evaluated accurately in respect to this. However, these four compounds induced PARP cleavage and three of the four (chrysene, indeno [1,2,3-c,d] pyrene, and pyrene) produced significant 3H-AA release from HCAECs. These data suggest that PAHs present in Chattanooga Creek have potential toxic effects on the cardiovascular system both in vivo and in vitro, and confirm the need for further studies.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2005-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2239</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3649&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-3762</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-01-23T16:36:08Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Effect of Dietary Treatment with Stearidonic Acid and Eicosapentaenoic Acid on Membrane Phospholipid Fatty Acid Composition and Glycogen-Elicited Peritoneal Neutrophil Survival in Absence or Presence of Bacterial Endotoxin</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Phipps, Jonathan Earl</dc:creator>
<dc:description>We previously found that enteral nutrition with diets containing elevated levels of eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA; 20:5 n-3) reduced the number of neutrophils in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid and improved clinical outcome of patients with or at risk for adult respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). We have also shown that the treatment of the neutrophil-like cell line, HL-60, with EPA can induce apoptosis. It is not known, however, if the addition of EPA to the diet would result in similar occurrences in neutrophils.
It has been suggested that the use of diets enriched with stearidonic acid (SDA; 18:4 n-3) may provide a novel source of n-3 fatty acids while offering similar beneficial effects on health as diets containing EPA. Therefore, we examined whether dietary SDA can be used as a precursor to increase EPA content in liver tissue.
It is well known that endotoxin increases neutrophil lifespan and that this may be important in maintaining innate immune response. The second part of this study incorporated the use of glycogen-elicited peritoneal neutrophils from the rat to examine the effect of dietary intervention with n-3 fatty acids (either EPA or SDA) on constitutive and endotoxin induced neutrophil survival. Male Long-Evans rats (n=18) were randomly divided into 3 dietary groups and fed a modified US-17 diet providing 200kcal/kg/day and containing 2% oleic acid (OA; 18:1 n-9) (n=6), 1% EPA/1% OA (n=6), or 1% SDA/1% OA (n=6) for 2 weeks. Liver phospholipids were analyzed using gas chromatography and neutrophil lifespan was evaluated using flow cytometry.
Dietary supplementation with EPA significantly increased the concentration of EPA and docosapentaenoic acid (DPA, 22:5n3), but not docosahexaenoic acid (DHA, 22:6n3) in liver tissue as compared with animals fed OA. Dietary supplementation with SDA also increased tissue contents of EPA and DPA, but not DHA as compared with OA fed controls. The increase in
tissue EPA was about one-half as effective in animals fed a diet containing SDA as those fed EPA. SDA was about two-thirds as effective as EPA at increasing tissue DPA content. These results indicate that, when fed at current dietary levels, SDA can increase the incorporation of EPA and DPA into the membrane phospholipids of liver tissue in a similar manner to dietary EPA. This provides evidence that SDA may provide an alternative to EPA for increasing tissue levels of EPA and DPA, but not DHA.
Flow cytometry analysis of neutrophils following 20h incubation in either presence or absence of endotoxin indicated that diet did not significantly affect constitutive or endotoxin-mediated neutrophil survival when fed at current levels. There was a non-significant trend towards an increase in both constitutive viability and endotoxin mediated cell survival (p=0.069) in both SDA and EPA fed animals as compared with control animals that were fed OA. While these results do not fully explain the role that EPA or SDA play in reducing neutrophil influx during ARDS, they do provide evidence that it is not through an increase of neutrophil apoptosis or an attenuation of the neutrophil response to endotoxin. These findings may indicate the importance of dietary EPA for maintaining host immune response, while providing beneficial effects in regards to inflammation. Because of similar action between dietary EPA and SDA these results might also provide further proof as to the potential for dietary SDA to be used as an alternative for dietary EPA.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2005-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2296</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3762&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3339</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-01-27T21:50:27Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Safety and Immunoreactivity of a Xenogeneic DNA Plasmid Vaccine Expressing Human Tyrosinase in Tumor-Bearing Horses</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Lembcke Perez Prieto, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Melanomas are among the most common skin tumors in horses (second only to sarcoids), with prevalence rates reaching as high as 80% in adult gray horses. Despite the wide availability of measures of local control, there are currently no systemic therapies that can effectively prevent spread, or treat metastatic or locally advanced/non-resectable melanoma in horses. A form of gene immunotherapy based on a plasmid DNA construct containing a xenogeneic form of the antigen tyrosinase have been developed and optimized for targeting cancer in both humans and dogs; and have demonstrated significant immunoreactivity and clinical benefit in the treatment of melanocytic tumors in these species. This study describes how our group has performed all the necessary steps to extend this therapy to a new species: The horse. This project has taken this idea all the way from conceptualization to: (1) proof of target, by demonstrating tyrosinase overexpression in equine melanomas and thus supporting its role as a valid tumor antigen in this species; (2) to the identification of the best administration strategies for this vaccine; (3) to the evaluation of the vaccine’s ability to induce a tyrosinase-specific immune response in vaccinated horses, both healthy and melanoma-bearing. This last step included the first (modified) phase I dose escalation study with this immunotherapy in this species. To this objective antigen-specific humoral and cellular immunoassays optimized to tyrosinase immunoreactivity. Tyrosinase xenogeneic vaccination was able to induce a significant antigen-specific immune response, both humoral and cellular, in most of the vaccinated patients. Dose appeared, however, not to have a significant effect in this response. Toxicity data was also documented, and this DNA vaccine appears to be safe and well tolerated in horses.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2591</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3339&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Horse</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>melanoma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>immunotherapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>vaccine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>tyrosinase</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>immune response</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Large or Food Animal and Equine Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medical Immunology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nucleic Acids, Nucleotides, and Nucleosides</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Pathology and Pathobiology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3790</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-01-27T21:50:31Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Effects of Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs on Cellular Structure and Adhesion Proteins in Human Colorectal Cancer</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Liggett, Jason Lee</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This dissertation explores the effects of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) on human colorectal cancer (CRC) cell proteins related to cellular structure and adhesion. NSAIDs are extensively used not only to treat inflammatory diseases but also to prevent cancer among high-risk groups. Their mechanisms are not fully understood, but both cyclooxygenase (COX) dependent and independent pathways play a role in NSAID-induced anti-tumorigenesis. Our lab previously reported that NSAIDs induce other anti-tumorigenic genes in a COX-independent manner (Chapter 1). Human CRC cells treated with the NSAID sulindac sulfide (SS) showed dramatic morphological changes under differential interference contrast and fluorescent microscopy, as well as weakened cellular adhesion and loss of membrane permeability as measured by micro-impedance. To elucidate a molecular mechanisms involved, two independent microarray analysis were performed using HCT-116 cells, and the gene Nesprin-2 was selected for further study based on its novelty in relation to cancer and its role in cell organization and structure (Chapter 2). SS-treated cells diminished Nesprin-2 mRNA expression compared to vehicle-treated cells. Other NSAIDs were also tested and demonstrated that inhibition of Nesprin-2 was not unique to SS. Additionally, immunohistochemistry showed higher levels of Nesprin-2 in the tumors of many tissue types in comparison with normal tissue. Further micro-impedance experiments on cells with reduced Nesprin-2 expression showed a proportional decrease in cellular adhesion. Next, we examined the effects of SS on another potentially oncogenic protein, epithelial cell adhesion molecule (EpCAM), which is over-expressed in many cancers including CRC, breast, pancreas, and prostate. We found EpCAM to be regulated by SS in a manner that is independent of: COX activity, transcription, de novo protein synthesis, and proteasomal degradation. Our findings demonstrate that SS drives an uncharacterized cleavage of EpCAM between arginine residues at positions 80 and 81 which is blocked by mutation to alanine residues as well as deletions (Chapter 3). Findings presented in this dissertation (1) our data suggests that Nesprin-2 maybe a potential novel cancer-associated protein and NSAIDs decrease its expression (2) SS facilitates proteolysis of EpCAM at amino acids 80/81 and provides a novel COX-independent mechanism of NSAID anti-tumorigenesis at the post-translational level.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2593</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3790&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>sulindac sulfide</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>NSAID</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>colorectal cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Oncology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3480</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-01-30T16:25:49Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Beta-Adrenergic, Arachidonic Acid and Potassium Channel Associated-Regulation of Human Breast Cancer Cell Lines</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Cakir, Yavuz</dc:creator>
<dc:description>During the late stages of breast cancer progression, breast cancer cell growth switches from steroid hormone to growth factor dependence, and it is assumed that invasive breast cancers are growth factor receptor positive and estrogen hormone resistant. The cellular arachidonic acid (AA) pathway is upregulated in a variety of cancer types, and it may play an important role in the growth regulation of breast cancer cells.
Recent evidence suggests that beta-adrenergic receptors (β-ARs) are expressed in some estrogen receptor (ER) negative breast cancers and that beta agonists not only can trigger AA release via the activation of cytosolic PLA2 or MAPK but also stimulate DNA synthesis in ER (-) breast cancers. AA is metabolized to prostaglandins and leukotrienes by cyclooxygenases (COX-1, 2) and 5-lipoxygenase (5-LOX), respectively. COX-1 is constitutively expressed and required for the homeostatic function, whereas COX-2 is overexpressed during pathological conditions and cancer. It is well documented that COX-2 and 5-LOX are overexpressed in ER (-) breast cancers. Additionally, in many cell types there is a link between G-protein inwardly rectifying potassium channel 1 (GIRK1) and beta-adrenergic receptor pathways. A recent report has demonstrated overexpression of GIRK1 in metastatic breast carcinomas.
Using thymidine incorporation assays, this study shows that antagonists of β-AR, COX, 5-LOX or potassium channels in vitro decreased cell proliferation in both ER (-)
and (+) breast cancer cell lines. The general β-blocker propranolol was more effective than the selective β2-antagonist ICI 118,551 or the selective β1-antagonist atenolol. ER (+) cell lines generally were more responsive to the β1-antagonist atenolol whereas ER (- ) cell lines were more responsive to the β2-antagonists ICI 118,551. The β-1/ 2- agonist isoproterenol significantly increased DNA synthesis in only ER (-) cell lines. The reduction in DNA synthesis caused by the 5-LOX inhibitor MK-886 and non-specific LOX inhibitor NDGA was significantly higher in ER (-) cell lines than in ER (+) cell lines. The COX 1/2 inhibitor aspirin and the specific COX-2 inhibitor meloxicam reduced DNA synthesis in both cell lines. The potassium (K+) channel blocker quinidine inhibited DNA synthesis in both cell lines, and the ER (-) cell line MDA-MB-453 was more sensitive to this effect. RT-PCR experiments showed that the ER (-) cell line MDAMB- 453 expressed mRNA for the GIRK1 channel. In summary, our study suggests a link among beta-adrenergic receptor, potassium channel and AA cascade.
The observed ability of COX inhibitors, 5-LOX inhibitors, β-adrenergic blockers and K+ channel blockers to suppress the growth and proliferation of the a subset of human breast cancer cells lines is an important finding that provides the basis for the exploration of such agents in the clinical management and prevention of breast cancer. Because these inhibitors are already widely used for the treatment of various diseases they can immediately be used in clinical trials with breast cancer patients. In particular the β-ARs represent a promising new target for the development of new drug candidates with potential application in the clinical fields because a wealth of information is already available on the biochemical and molecular events underlying signaling by these receptors.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2001-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2043</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3480&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Medical Specialties</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3709</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-08-07T13:03:40Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Effect of a Leucine/Pyridoxine Nutraceutical on Energy Metabolism and Satiety in Lean and Obese Dogs</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Murphy, Maryanne</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Obesity is the most common nutritional disorder of pet dogs (prevalence of 23–59%). This 29-week study investigated a nutraceutical containing 1 g leucine and 13 mg pyridoxine designed to maintain lean muscle mass while decreasing adiposity when compared with positive and negative controls. After determining individual maintenance calorie requirements over 3 – 4 weeks, thirty-six healthy adult Beagles were divided into obesification, weight gain prevention, or maintain ideal body weight arms.
Obesity was induced and during a weight loss phase, excess calories were removed, and obesification dogs were given nutraceutical with CAD (ObN), placebo with CAD (ObP), or a therapeutic weight loss diet (WLD). Weight gain prevention dogs were fed CAD at levels in excess of what they would naturally consume in a single meal with nutraceutical (ExN) or placebo (EXP), and dogs maintaining ideal body weight (IBW) were fed CAD to individual maintenance calories requirements over 12 weeks.
Based on MANOVA, ObN and WLD lost similar levels of total weight (3.4 +/- 0.6 vs. 4.4 +/- 1.1 kg) and fat mass (3.1 +/- 0.6 vs. 3.9 +/- 0.8 kg) after 12 weeks of treatment, and more than ObP (1.2 +/- 1.0 kg weight; 0.9 +/- 1.0 kg fat; p &lt; 0.0001). ExP and ExN gained similar levels of weight and fat mass (up to 32.5 +/- 3.3 vs. 35.7 +/- 6.3% body fat). Behavioral indicators of medium term satiety did not differ clinically between groups. In general, plasma levels of gut hormones and endocrine factors followed expected trends and there was little effect of treatment on muscle or adipose tissue expression of genes involved in fat oxidation, oxidative phosphorylation, and mitochondrial biogenesis. Circulating plasma concentrations of IL6 and IL15 did not differ between groups.
These data show the nutraceutical holds promise as an option for successful weight loss in dogs. Maintenance levels of CAD were able to induce weight loss without risk of hypo- or anorexia, or the need to switch diets or restrict energy intake.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2784</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3709&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Canine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Leucine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pyridoxine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metabolism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Satiety</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Small or Companion Animal Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-3924</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-08-08T16:09:58Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Biological Variation of Thromboelastography Variables in Ten Healthy Female Horses</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Scruggs, Jennifer Lee</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Biological variability (BV) has important applications in laboratory medicine. It can be a source of variation in measured analyte values and provide guidance on reference interval use. BV has three components: between-individual variation (CVg), caused by differences in mean values of a particular analyte among members of a group, withinindividual variation (CVi), caused by fluctuations around an individual’s inherent homeostatic set point, and analytical variation (CVa). Thromboelastography (TEG), a type of viscoelastic coagulation analysis, is becoming increasingly common in veterinary referral centers. Despite increased popularity, the optimal method of results interpretation is not clear. While population-based reference intervals (PRI) are used for many analytes, reference change values (RCV) are more sensitive for disease detection for other analytes. The relative sensitivity of PRI or RCV in detecting significant deviations of reported analyte values can be derived from BV data, via incorporation of CVi and CVg into a simple formula to calculate index of individuality (IOI). This study measured BV of four TEG variables R, K, angle and MA in clinically healthy horses and, using calculated IOI, found that population-based reference intervals are appropriate when interpreting results from individual animals. Additionally, the ability to freeze a key reagent used in the TEG assay, tissue factor, was also investigated.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2776</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3924&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>horses</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>coagulation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>biological variation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>reference intervals</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Large or Food Animal and Equine Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4464</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-11-11T17:14:03Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Murine Herpetic Stromal Keratitis: Cellular and Molecular Mechanisms Involved in its Pathogenesis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Banerjee, Kaustuv</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Herpetic Stromal Keratitis (HSK) is a leading cause of infectious blindness resulting from corneal infection with herpes simplex virus (HSV-1). Extensive corticosteroid therapy is required to achieve remission and sometimes corneal transplantation is the only means of restoring vision. Murine model research has revealed that the immunological process that clears infection conversely leads to corneal tissue damage. This immune-pathological reaction involves complex interactions of cellular and molecular events.
Current knowledge about human and murine HSK pathogenesis is summarized in Part I. Parts II, III and IV progresses this knowledge using knockout and transgenic mice. Results in Part II clarify mechanisms that operate shortly after corneal infection using a mouse with defective neutrophil migration. Impaired corneal neutrophil migration delayed corneal viral clearance causing heightened inflammation in the cornea. The cytokine IL-6, a component of this response, was shown to be capable of inducing VEGF, resulting in an increased angiogenic response and enhanced HSK lesions. These results provide novel insights into the link between viral infection, pro-inflammatory molecules, neutrophil migration, angiogenesis and HSK development. The role of HSV reactive and non-reactive CD8+ T cells in HSK pathogenesis is discussed in Parts III and IV. It has been demonstrated that CD4+ T cells, crucial to the development of HSK, do not require HSV antigen recognition to mediate HSK. Instead they are activated and recruited to the cornea by bystander mechanisms apparently through the action of pro-inflammatory molecules. Our recent results indicate that bystander mechanisms also facilitate corneal recruitment of non-HSV specific CD8+ T cells. However, HSV reactive CD8+ cells were not involved directly in corneal lesions but instead modulated lesion severity and protected mice from lethal HSV induced encephalitis. This latter effect appeared to be due to the ability of HSV specific CD8+ T cells to control viral replication in the peripheral nervous system and thereby prevent spread to both the brain and the cornea.
This dissertation presents research aimed at elucidating both molecular and cellular events in HSK pathogenesis. These results will serve as guidelines for future development of more efficient prophylactic and therapeutic strategies.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2004-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2981</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4464&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Other Medical Specialties</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4221</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-01-23T21:47:48Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>DIFFERENTIATION OF EQUINE MESENCHYMAL STROMAL CELLS INTO CELLS OF NEURAL LINEAGE AND THEIR APPLICATION INTO A NOVEL MODEL FOR ACUTE PERIPHERAL NERVE INJURY IN THE HORSE</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Cruz, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Studies have shown that mesenchymal stromal cells (MSCs) are able to differentiate into extra-mesodermal lineages, including neurons. Positive outcomes were obtained after transplantation of neurally-induced MSCs in rats, rabbits and guinea pigs after nerve injury, but the effect of these cells is unknown in horses. Our objective was to test the ability of equine mesenchymal stromal cells to differentiate into cells of neuronal lineage, and to assess differences, if any, in morphology and protein expression. Additionally, we wanted to investigate if horse age and cell passage number contributed to the ability to achieve neural differentiation.
The first part of this research focuses on assessing the potential of equine bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stromal cells to undergo differentiation into cells of neural lineage cells after prior demonstration of their stemness. It describes the optimization of in vitro conditions to induce neural differentiation of equine MSCs and the use of neural markers in equine MSCs, which has not been previously reported.
Subsequent research focuses on further commitment of these neural cells into Schwann-like cells for possible transplantation into an acute peripheral nerve injury model in horses. After optimizing the laboratory conditions to induce Schwann cell differentiation of equine MSCs, their detachment from the tissue culture flasks resulted in poor viability. Therefore, undifferentiated MSCs were transplanted in the surrounding fascia after transecting the central portion of the anastomotic branch (ramus communicans) of the lateral and medial palmar nerves of the fore limbs in healthy horses. Approximately 45 days after the lesion was created, the whole nerve was removed for histological analyses.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3144</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4221&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>horse</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>peripheral nerve</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>mesenchymal stromal cells</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Schwann cell</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>nerve regeneration</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>nerve injury</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Large or Food Animal and Equine Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Other Veterinary Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4154</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-01-23T22:09:36Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Effect of a Core Conditioning Program on Lumbar Paraspinal Area, Asymmetry and Pain Score in Military Working Dogs with Lumbosacral Pain</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Henderson, Andrea Leigh</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Introduction: Lumbosacral pain and stenosis are common causes of retirement from duty for Military Working Dogs (MWDs). Working dogs that receive surgical management for this condition often have a poor prognosis for return to duty after recovery. Humans with chronic low back pain demonstrate paraspinal muscle asymmetry, pain and dysfunction that often improve in response to an exercise program. This study investigated whether dogs with mild lumbosacral pain have decreased lumbar paraspinal muscle area, symmetry, and density, as well as increased pain and dysfunction compared to control dogs. Additionally, response of pain and dysfunction to an exercise program was assessed.
Materials and Methods: Visual Analog Scale (VAS) scores for lumbosacral pain, functional questionnaire scores for search and detection tasks, and computed tomography images were evaluated for eight MWDs with lumbosacral pain along with eight control dogs. Mean cross-sectional muscle area (CSA)-to-vertebral ratio, asymmetry and density were determined for five lumbar paraspinal muscles bilaterally at the L5, L6 and L7 caudal endplates. Four dogs with lumbosacral pain rested and four dogs completed an eight-week core stabilizing exercise program. Repeated assessments of lumbosacral pain, dysfunction and muscle parameters for dogs with lumbosacral pain were made at the conclusion of the exercise program.
Results: The multifidus lumborum and longissimus lumborum muscles demonstrated significantly reduced CSA (p= 0.020, p = 0.021, respectively) in dogs with lumbosacral pain. Muscle density was decreased in dogs with lumbosacral pain for multifidus lumborum (p = 0.030) and quadratus lumborum (p = 0.011). Multifidus lumborum muscle CSA (p = 0.019), symmetry (p = 0.002) and density (p = 0.024) were significantly higher than at baseline for dogs with LS pain after completion of the exercise program. Functional questionnaire scores improved significantly for exercised dogs (p = 0.031) but did not improve for rested dogs (p = 0.828).
Discussion: Military Working Dogs with mild lumbosacral pain and dysfunction had significantly smaller CSA, symmetry and density for both multifidus lumborum and longissimus lumborum muscle groups. An 8-week core strengthening program was associated with significantly improved performance in evaluated tasks for dogs with lumbosacral pain.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3155</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4154&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>lumbosacral</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>stenosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>paraspinal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>muscle</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>atrophy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>exercise</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Small or Companion Animal Medicine</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4252</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-01-26T22:45:49Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Effect of Small Interfering RNAs on in Vitro Replication and Gene Expression of Feline Coronavirus</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Anis, Eman Ahmed Mohamed</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Feline corononavirus (FCoV) infection is ubiquitous in domestic cat populations worldwide and is usually associated with subclinical or mild enteritis. However, in some cats infection may result in the development of a fatal progressive disease called feline infectious peritonitis (FIP). FIP is considered to be the major cause of infectious-related death in pet cats. Currently, there is no protective vaccine or curative treatment to this highly fatal disease. In this study, we evaluated the ability of small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) to inhibit the in vitro viral replication and gene expression of FCoV as a potential treatment for FIP.
Five synthetic siRNAs were designed to target different regions of the FCoV genome. The siRNAs were tested individually and in various combinations in vitro for their antiviral effects against 2 strains of FCoV (feline infectious peritonitis virus WSU 79-1146 and feline enteric coronavirus WSU 79-1683). Tested combinations targeted the FCoV leader and 3′ untranslated region; FCoV leader region and nucleocapsid gene; and FCoV leader, 3′ untranslated region, and nucleocapsid gene. For each test condition, assessments included relative quantification of the inhibition of intracellular viral genomic RNA synthesis by means of real-time, reverse-transcription Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis; flow cytometric evaluation of the reduction of viral protein expression in infected cells; and assessment of virus replication inhibition via titration of extracellular virus with a 50% tissue culture infective dose (TCID50) assay.
The 5 siRNAs had variable inhibitory effects on FCoV when used singly. Combinations of siRNAs that targeted different regions of the viral genome resulted in more effective viral inhibition than did individual siRNAs that targeted a single gene. The tested siRNA combinations resulted in approximately 95% reduction in viral replication (based on virus titration results), compared with findings in negative control non-targeting siRNA-treated FCoV-infected cells. This study shows that FCoV replication can be specifically inhibited by siRNAs that target coding and noncoding regions of the viral genome, suggesting a potential therapeutic application of RNA interference in treatment of feline infectious peritonitis.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3107</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4252&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Virilogy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Molecular Biology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Feline coronavirus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Feline infectious peritonitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Real time PCR</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>small interfering RNA</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Veterinary Microbiology and Immunobiology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4347</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-01-27T16:56:51Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_compmeddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-vete</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The role of NAG-1 in Tumorigenesis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Min, Kyung-Won</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This dissertation explores the nature of a divergent member of the Transforming Growth Factor-β [beta] superfamily, the non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs activated gene (NAG-1), as it relates to its regulation and biological activity in cancer context. Our lab has extensively studied on the molecular mechanism by which phytochemicals and NSAIDs induce apoptosis correlation with NAG-1 expression in human colorectal cancer (CRC) cells. Significant data from in vitro studies suggest that NAG-1 has an anti-tumorigenic activity which elicits apoptosis in a cyclooxygenase (COX)-independent manner in CRC cells. Indeed, NAG-1 transgenic mice developed less aberrant polyp foci (APC) compared to those of control counterpart in chemically- , genetically induced colorectal cancer models. However, it has been reported that NAG-1 has a tumor-promoting activity in a different cancer type such as prostate cancer and in chapter 1, a literature review for the regulation and the role of NAG-1 in the context of cancer will be discussed. Human pancreatic cancer cells treated with the PPARγ [gamma] ligand MCC-555 showed the feature of apoptosis with associated with NAG-1 induction. MCC-555 induces KLF4 expression via PPARγ-independent pathway, which in turn induces NAG-1 transactivation by which KLF4 binds to NAG-1 promoter region, suggesting NAG-1 is also implicated in apoptosis in human pancreatic cancer cells (Chapter 2). During the study on the signaling pathway and target genes affected by NAG-1, we observed nuclear expression of NAG-1. Nuclear NAG-1 moderates TGFβ signaling by interfering binding of Smad complex to DNA, leading to the inhibition of cell migration and invasion induced by TGFβ signaling (Chapter 3). Taken together, the studies presented in this dissertation suggest that NAG-1 maybe a driver factor for apoptosis not only in CRC cells, but in pancreatic cancer cells, and this effect might arise from the activity of nuclear NAG-1 which attenuates Smad signaling required for cancer survival and progression.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3199</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4347&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>NAG-1</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Smad pathway</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cancer Biology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cell Biology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Molecular Biology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record>
</repository>
