<repository xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/"      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instanc">
<record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_chanhonoproj-2345</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-05-04T21:48:23Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_admi</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_prov</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_chanhono</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_chanhonoproj</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Gender Differences in Attitudes toward Math and Science among Elementary Students: An Exploration of the Role of Teachers</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Gugliotta, Katie F</dc:creator>
<dc:date>2010-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_chanhonoproj/1386</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2345&amp;amp;context=utk_chanhonoproj</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>University of Tennessee Honors Thesis Projects</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Education</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2033</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:43:53Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Adolescent Female Substance Use: An Examination of Male Peer Influences and Parental Control</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Whiteford, Sarah Gwynne</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Central to many theories of deviance and delinquency (differential association, social learning, and social bond) are peer and familial influences on deviant behavior.  A conceptual framework that incorporated both peer and familial influence to address the role of cross-sex peers on female deviance was built based on a review of the literature.  Using substance use as an indicator of deviance, the effects of having three forms of male associates (male friends, romantic partners, and sexual partners) on female substance use were examined. Focus was on the effects of different types of male peer relationships, how those effects differed from the effects of female peer relationships, and how parental control might be greater for girls with only female peers.
The conceptual model incorporated three measures of parental control—parentally granted autonomy, parental presence at home, and time spent in shared activities with parents—that were used to test the effects of male associates on female substance use.  Analyzing data from the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health (Add Health), one combined measure for male associates was regressed on female substance use while controlling for parental control measures to determine if the effects of male associates on female substance use were mediated by parental control.
Results indicated that while each type of male associate increased the likelihood of female substance use, effects were stronger for romantic and sexual partners than for male friends.  Female friends also increased the likelihood of substance use.  While the effects of male friends did not significantly differ from the effects of female friends, the effects of romantic and sexual partners did.  The effects of male associates were significant even with the inclusion of parental control measures.  Though both relationships with male associates and parents significantly affected female substance use, results did not provide support for the conceptual model.  With results providing greater support for theories of peer influence than parental influence, future research should continue to examine peer relationship influences on deviance, how these influences vary by type of association, and how gender effects peer influence processes.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/922</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2033&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>substance use</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>peer influence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>parental control</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>cross sex friends</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>adolescence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Control, Law, Crime, and Deviance</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1350</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:43:55Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Social Ecology of Parenting: Systematically Modeling The Antecedents of Supportive and Intrusive Parenting</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Schluterman, Julie A</dc:creator>
<dc:description>One of the significant contributions of this study is its inclusion of the role of social contextual factors in determining parenting. I built on the ecological model proposed by Belsky (1984). As such, the parenting model tested in this dissertation included individual level determinants of parenting: 1) parent characteristics (e.g., developmental history), and 2) child characteristics (e.g., behavior problems). Yet, rather than include a social context domain as described by Belsky, I distinguished between within family context (e.g., interparental hostility) and external to family context (e.g., work-family conflict, neighborhood disorganization) as social contextual sources of stress and support to the parent-child relationship.
A second significant contribution of this study is attention to parent gender. I included assessments of both mother and father parenting and specifically test for hypothesized differences in how the predictive model might operate differently depending on the parent’s gender. It is important to note further that the accomplishment of this examination of parent gender involved the use of a methodology that is itself an important contribution to the existing work. Specifically, my methodology involves simultaneous testing of mother and father data, something that has not typically been done in past studies. Critically, this methodology controls for any overlap or similarity between mother and father parenting and thereby allows for a better test of the uniqueness of mother and father parenting and of patterns of predicting mother and father parenting.
This study employed parent reported data from the NIMH-funded Ogden Youth and Family Project, a longitudinal, sequential-cohort study of families with adolescent children (N = 933). Using structural equation modeling, we found that the model adequately fit the data while direct and indirect effects on parenting were found. The individual level parenting determinants of child behavior problems and parental depression were significantly directly associated with parenting, particularly for fathers. The within family contextual variable of covert marital conflict was directly associated with father parenting, and directly and indirectly associated with mother intrusive parenting through maternal depression. As risk factors external to the family, workfamily conflict was not significantly related to parenting, and neighborhood disorganization was indirectly related to intrusive mothering (but not her supportive parenting or to father’s parenting), through elevated levels of marital conflict and depression.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/297</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/SchlutermanJulie.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Family, Life Course, and Society</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1885</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:44:06Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Systems, Social Order, and the Global Debt Crisis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Bradford, John Hamilton</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Part I examines the global rise of both public and private debt and its recent manifestations in the US housing bubble and the financial panic of 2007-8.  A review of the most popular theories of the debt crisis is provided, including an explication of securitized banking and economic theory.  The underlying condition of increasing ecological and energetic scarcity is accorded central significance in the broad trajectory of world growth and debt,    Part II explicates systems theories of social order and the social significance of markets.  The theories of Niklas Luhmann, Talcott Parsons, Mario Bunge, Anthony Giddens, and Jürgen Habermas are evaluated with respect to their theories of social order and crisis.  A central finding is that, although declining rates of exergy production inhibit the global economic recovery as measured by conventional economic tools, this fact is not likely to be widely recognized.  A central theme of Part II is how social systems handle uncertainty, risk, and to what extent complex social systems can be regulated normatively by the public sphere.  As global society becomes increasingly interconnected and dependent upon the depletion of material and energy resources, the communication channels that facilitate the self-understanding of modern society at the same time proliferate, becoming increasingly disconnected and self-referential.  Luhmann’s systems theory is used to explain why collective recognition and action is at once rendered more necessary and increasingly unlikely given the complexity of global society that Earth’s terrestrial stock of nonrenewable energy resources has engendered.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/778</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1885&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>luhmann</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>systems theory</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>global debt crisis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>financial crisis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>limits to growth</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>peak oil</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Work, Economy and Organizations</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1130</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:44:31Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Contested Legitimacy: Coercion and the State in Ethiopia</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Sarbo, Dima Noggo</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Most studies on Africa that analyzed the institution of the state emphasized the colonial origins of state formation, tracing the crisis of socioeconomic and political development to that specific historical trajectory. Colonialism has shaped the characteristics of modern African states, but it is also important to address institutional factors, methods of governance, and state-society relations in the post independence period. As Ethiopia was not directly constituted by European colonialism, a study of the Ethiopian state provides an opportunity to look at how the state has performed, and how it relates to its own society, without the colonial baggage. This case study explores the characteristics of the Ethiopian state employing neopatrimonialism as a theoretical framework. It addresses the system of personalization, hybridization, patronage, coercion and external factors in the exercise of state power.
According to both Weberian and Gramscian theories of the state, the legitimacy of states is contingent upon the tacit acceptance of its authority by the majority of the population under its jurisdiction. Coercion is used as a threat and a last resort when all other persuasive and ideological methods have failed or become inadequate. Yet, the case study shows the use of coercion as an enduring feature of some states. The Ethiopian state has been consistently challenged internally and isolated regionally. Consequently, it has depended on a combination of coercion and external patronage as a survival strategy. This strategy has further complicated internal cohesion, and external patronage has also served as a disincentive to accommodate internal demands for inclusion. The endurance of violence and internal challenges to the authority of states is a general characteristic of states with contested legitimacy.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/98</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1130&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2072</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:07Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Unto the Least of These: The Pentecostal Church and Social Ministry</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Tucker, Stacey U</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This project explores the relationship of Pentecostal churches in the U.S. to social ministry.  Taken from the results of multivariate logistic regression and likelihood ratio tests utilizing the National Congregations Study , a nationally representative sample of US congregations, I found that Pentecostal congregations are statistically less likely to participate in social ministry than non-Pentecostal Christian congregations. Through chi-square analyses, I also found Pentecostal churches to be less likely than non-Pentecostal Conservative congregations to participate in social ministry. Through a series of interviews and observations of five Pentecostal Assemblies of God churches in the Atlanta, Georgia metropolitan area, assessments were made on Pentecostal identity and Pentecostal perceived involvement in the community of Atlanta.  Recommendations for further research are provided.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1034</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2072&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Pentecostalism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Congregation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Ministry</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Service</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology of Religion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Other Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Religion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social and Behavioral Sciences</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1858</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:16Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Assumption of Non-coerciveness  and the Total Food Market</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Schaffer, Harwood</dc:creator>
<dc:description>For the last 46 years, the countries of the world have tried to reduce the number of chronically hungry people. Despite all the efforts, the numbers have barely budged from the over 850 million people who were chronically hungry in 1974 until the 2007-2009 food price crisis, when the numbers increased to over 1.02 billion. The blame for this situation has variously been put on bad governance, the lack of adequate market reforms, the market reforms that were imposed on developing nations, and globalization. Food, like other products in this globalized world, is allocated using the market system. One likely place to look for the cause of continuing hunger is at the assumptions that underlie the market system, in particular the assumption of non-coerciveness. This assumption asserts that the market transaction—in this case for food—is freely entered into by both the buyer and the seller and that either can refuse to enter into the transaction if it is not to their advantage. After looking at the traditional understanding of coerciveness in economics, this dissertation examines the logic system of economics concluding that the issue of non-coerciveness is a moral issue, and the argument of Frank Knight that the question of non-coerciveness is an issue of ethics. Using the work of Michael Keeley, this paper concludes that broadly accepted human rights is the best possible criterion for determining whether or not the aggregate food market is non-coercive. If the human right to food is abridged then it can be said that the aggregate food market is coercive and the assumption of non-coerciveness for the aggregate food market does not hold. With 1.02 billion people chronically hungry, 1/6 of humanity, it is clear that the right to food has been abridged and the aggregate food market is coercive. To overcome chronic hunger and enforce the right to food, governments, international agencies, and non-governmental organizations are going to have to supplement markets with non-market measures. The dissertation concludes with a number of recommendations for non-market measures that can be taken to ensure that all people enjoy the right to food.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/847</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1858&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>assumption of non-coerciveness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>food security</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>human rights</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>freedom</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>coerciveness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>development</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Agricultural and Resource Economics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rural Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Theory, Knowledge and Science</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1536</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:33Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Migrating Money: Remittances in a Global Setting</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Adams, Robert Randall</dc:creator>
<dc:description>In recent years, the term globalization and the global economy have caught the attention of scholars and popular media. Many of the aspects of globalization serve to create push and pull factors that encourage labor migration about the globe as individuals seek to establish some form of economic stability. The sending of money back to country of origin or remittances is often a result of this movement. This study uses data from the New Immigrant Survey to examine the characteristics of United States immigrants who have received “green cards” (granted legal permanent resident status) and who engage in remittance behavior. The study also seeks to bridge a gap between macro- and micro-approaches to understanding the willingness of immigrants to remit as well as examining the dollar amounts returned to country of origin and the propensity to use in-kind remittances or the sending of goods to friends and family who remain in the immigrant’s country of origin.
In an effort to examine the global and local aspects of remittance sending, predictors were chosen from both Demography studies and Globalization theory. These predictors of remittance behavior were analyzed in separate models and in combination. The results suggest that a holistic approach to understanding remittance behavior rather than a discipline specific approach provide a better understanding of immigrants and the characteristics that promote remittance sending. The results also suggest that cash remittances and in-kind remittances represent two distinctly different approaches and means to providing for friends and family left behind. Cash remittances are seen as a method of economic survival and possible advancement in country of origin but in-kind remittances represent more of a gift-giving activity by immigrants with greater levels of expendable income.
Both migration and remittance decisions are complex decisions that involve numerous individuals with in the household of those encouraged to migrate. An expanded knowledge of this process will help scholars and policy makers develop useful and efficient programs in the future.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2008-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/472</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008Dissertations/AdamsRobertRandall.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1175</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:37Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Groundwater: A Community’s Management of the Invaluable Resource Beneath its Feet</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Brannon, Nancy D.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Understanding the impact of human decisions on vital resources is a core task of environmental sociology, which studies the interaction between human society and the environment. The overarching theme of this research is the economicenvironmental relationship in U.S. public policy, using a case study of a specific environmental resource problem in a specific region. It fuses basic assumptions of two economic growth models (treadmill of production and the urban growth machine) to examine the extent to which these assumptions permeate the worldviews of policymakers and those who advise them. When the growth imperative is a priority in their worldviews, then the paradigm shapes policy decisions favorable to growth. When the growth imperative paradigm dominates the decision-making structure, then policy decisions favor economic growth over concerns for and at the expense of environmental resources. This is the case because economic growth requires unlimited commoditization and exploitation of finite resources. The results are impairment of both the quantity and quality of natural resources on which communities depend for growth and their existence.
This research examines the economic-environmental relationship in a case study of the Memphis, Tennessee area to ascertain how policy decisions that promote growth affect groundwater and may have sparked an inter-state water conflict. The State of Mississippi filed a federal lawsuit against Memphis and its utility Memphis Light, Gas and Water over rights to groundwater, the sole source of drinking water. The study ascertains that the predominance of the growth paradigm is linked to policymakers’ perspectives and reflected in their decisions that impair the quantity and quality of vital environmental resources. The case demonstrates how the growth imperative contributes to resource depletion, which can lead to conflict among users of a common resource.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/129</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/BrannonNancy.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1265</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:47Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Eight Karats of Justice: Analysis of the Grassroots Resistance Movement Against Goldmining in the Villages of Bergama, Turkey</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Koçer, Banu Aysu</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This study explores and analyzes the grassroots movement against goldmining in the villages of Bergama, Turkey. The struggle of Bergama villagers started out as a local ecological resistance movement in the early 1990s and gradually transformed into an environmental justice movement with national implications when activists adopted a rights-based discourse by incorporating into their claims the notions of justice, democratic participation, and citizenship rights.
Since goldmining investment in Bergama was a manifestation of significant shifts in the global corporate mining industry starting in the 1980s, and of changes in the world political economy, an account of these shifts is presented as the global political-economic background for the grassroots resistance movement in Bergama. This global perspective is complemented by an account of the domestic socio-economic and political context in which the Bergama villagers’ resistance movement unfolded.
The study employs two reference frames for the conceptual and theoretical analysis of the Bergama villagers’ movement. The Environmental Justice Movement (EJM) Literature is reviewed for conceptual clues pertaining to the transformation process of the movement under investigation. As the theoretical reference frame, the New Social Movements (NSM) approach to contemporary social movements is employed in an attempt to assess the applicability of this theoretical approach to the resistance movement of Bergama villagers, as well as the EJM in the United States.
NSM theories are inadequate in explaining these movements. Based on the weaknesses of the NSM and the similarities identified between the Bergama villagers’ movement and the EJM, I assert that a new approach to theorizing social movements, which takes as its point of departure these similarities, is necessary. I argue that such an approach will guide not only social movement scholars in understanding ecological grassroots movements in the global North and South but also movement activists in their struggle for social change. In contrast, an exclusive focus on the distinctions between the ecological grassroots movements in the global South, on the one hand, and in the North, on the other, based merely on their economic and cultural differences, will be counter-productive in challenging the systemic root causes of ecological problems plaguing the people of the world today.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/216</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/KocerBanu.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1041</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:45:48Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>&quot;Rapping About Authenticity&quot;: Exploring the Differences in Perceptions of &quot;Authenticity&quot; in Rap Music by Consumers.&quot;</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Wright, James L</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Historically, social scientists have not only marginalized rap music as a viable unit of scholarly analysis, but failed at attempts to understand the thoughts and actions of rap music consumers. This study analyzes the connection between rap music’s (and the artists’) authenticity and how those perceptions of authenticity affect music consumers’ decision making process, thus providing a possible explanation as to why music fans purchase rap music.  The goal of this research was to see if the reasons rap music fans provide explaining the rationale behind their purchases match the images and perceptions presumably held by the general public about rap music.
A snowball sample was used to survey a total of 30 rap music “experts.”  The findings from this study indicate the concept of authenticity is very important in validating not only rap music, but rap artist, rap music fans, and hip hop culture as a whole. The findings from this study provide empirical evidence supporting the importance of authenticity as a construct and the use of rap music as a unit of scholarly research analysis. By justifying the importance of authenticity to rap music and hip hop culture, this research proposes that authenticity may well be used as a means to maintain existing relationships with a fan-base and as a marketing tool used by record companies to attract new fans and generate album sales.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/760</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1041&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Music</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>rap</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>hip hop</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>identity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>culture</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Critical and Cultural Studies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ethnomusicology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Psychology and Interaction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology of Culture</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1222</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:46:06Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Felony Disenfranchisement Legislation: A Test of the Group Threat Hypothesis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Geoghagan, Angel Dawn</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The group threat hypothesis is part of the conflict theoretical perspective, which has been one of the most dominant and useful theories in the fields of criminology and criminal justice for decades. The usefulness of this perspective relates to the understanding it provides of how the law can be used by those in power as a measure of control. The use of law as a method of control has a long history in the US society, and there are many examples from which to pull. This project examines the use of one set of laws, felony disenfranchisement legislation, to determine if these laws can be seen as a method for controlling a subgroup of the population. Historically, felony disenfranchisement legislation has been a part of the American legal system from the founding of this country. While the laws have changed many times, the constant has been an effort to disenfranchise a segment of the population deemed as dangerous and prevent such groups from participating in the political process through their votes. Using data on African American population, arrests, and incarceration, this study tests if the strictness of disenfranchisement legislation is associated with the size of African American population, as well as African American arrest and incarceration rates. Both qualitative and quantitative methods were used to understand the nature of felony disenfranchisement legislation and to determine if disenfranchisement legislation could be used as a tool to control African Americans. The qualitative analysis indicates that African Americans are more impacted by disenfranchisement laws in two regards: the criteria that leads to disenfranchisement and the requirements for vote restoration. However, the research hypotheses are partially supported by quantitative analysis. That is, while results indicate that the proportion of African Americans in a state is correlated to the strictness of a state’s disenfranchisement law, there is no relationship between the arrest and incarceration rates and either the strictness of disenfranchisement legislation or the difficulty of the vote restoration procedures. These results point to limitations of using the group threat hypothesis to understand the relationship between disenfranchisement law and criminal justice operation.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/175</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/GeoghaganAngel.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1798</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:46:07Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Interstitial Copresence: Experiencing Self With and Within Everyday Forms of Electronically Mediated Communication</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Seiler, Steven J.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Cell phones and the Internet have become cornerstones in the daily lives of most Americans. Researchers have rigorously studied numerous dimensions of electronically mediated communication (EMC). Yet, very little research has explored the context and consequences of negotiating multiple forms of EMC within everyday life. The purpose of this study was to explore the impact of everyday forms of electronically mediated communication (EvEMC) – cell phone talk, text messages, instant messages, and email – on self-work, particularly within personal relationships. Results of OLS regression analyses of survey data collected from 617 college students and qualitative data analysis of three subsequent focus groups suggested that negotiating personal relationships with and within EvEMC produces a sense of interstitial copresence, which is an awareness of the convergence of perpetual copresence within a digital environment and presence or copresence within a physical environment.
The findings suggested that interstitial copresence is inherently Janus-faced. EvEMC provided people with a strong sense of freedom and control. However, negotiating personal relationships within interstitial copresence resulted in dissolution of relational boundaries. Consequently, deceptive tactics were commonly used to negotiate self-presentation within interstitial copresence, which had consequences for people’s self-appraisals as well. Since important others were expected to be accessible virtually anytime and anywhere, people with a strong sense of interstitial copresence often had an adverse emotional reaction when important others did not answer their calls or quickly reply to their messages or call or send messages regularly. As personal relationships negotiated within interstitial copresence move toward totality, the consequences for both the self and the relationships become more pronounced. Ultimately, the study concludes that self-work with and within interstitial copresence produces an interstitial self – a relational self that is, at all times, situated within a physical environment and a digital environment, yet never completely in either environment.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/849</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1798&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Self-Work</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Identity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Personal Relationships</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Boundary Work</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cell Phones</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Computer-Mediated Communication</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Psychology and Interaction</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-1630</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:46:18Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Giving Back Not Giving Up: Generativity Among Older Female Inmates</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Benedict, Regina White</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Extensive research has been conducted to understand the experience of incarceration, with the focus on hardships inflicted on inmates via incarceration. In addition, the current graying of America‟s prisons has gained some attention from both policymakers and the general public. However, despite the recent upsurge in concern and interest in matters pertaining to prison inmates, the focus by and large remains on young males. Meanwhile, studies addressing the experience of incarceration for older females are virtually non-existent. Generativity, defined as the desire to give back and execution of that desire, is regarded as a universal life stage first occurring sometime during middle age. Yet, generativity among older female inmates has not been specifically researched. This research project explores the experience of incarceration as well as the presence and practice of generativity among older female inmates.
Participants in this study were 29 female inmates housed at the Kentucky Correctional Institution for Women in Pewee Valley, Kentucky. Data were collected through low-structure interviews, which allowed the participants to discuss issues that were important to them.
The findings suggest that older women experience motherhood and incarceration in unique ways. Generativity was indicated to exist among older women inmates. Furthermore, the participants reported engaging in generative behaviors in prison and expressed desires to continue to be generative upon their release. A number of policy implications are suggested, as are a number of areas that may be of interest to researchers in future.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/562</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1630&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2192</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:46:27Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Role of &quot;Sense of Place:&quot; A Theoretical Framework to Aid Urban Forest Policy Decision-Making</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Davis, Kimberly Louise</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Urban forest management is being increasingly recognized as a viable policy vehicle for improving the overall quality of life in urban regions, promoting economic well-being as well as mitigating some of the environmental impacts of urbanization.  As a complex system of ecological merit, the urban forest is ultimately dependent upon community-directed efforts to protect and maintain its health, largely through tree ordinances. An understanding of how values and other social factors trigger public concern for and management of the local urban forest is important because of ramifications of community urban forestry policy on regional ecosystem functional capacity. This dissertation investigates the influence of individual experience with trees, knowledge about trees, and tree-related attitudes and beliefs on public support for management strategies to protect the urban forest. Attitude theory forms the foundation of the empirical approach used in this study. Drawing from place theory, attitudes representing Sense of Place were hypothesized to also play a role in explaining variation in homeowners’ support of urban forest protection strategies. Data were obtained from a public opinion survey of 800 homeowners living in a major urban area in Southern Appalachia and joined with measurements of tree canopy density. Geographic information systems software was used to create measures of tree canopy density from Light Detection and Ranging data for varying aerial extents around the survey respondents’ properties. Theoretical constructs were formulated and deployed in structural equation models to test the validity of the hypothesized relationships among the constructs, representing predictors of public support for urban forest protection policy. The modeling results showed that place-based contexts are significant in the prediction of community willingness to support higher levels of urban forest protection. Findings from this study suggest that although the presence of urban trees in one’s neighborhood leads a homeowner to place greater importance on various attributes of trees, this does not automatically lead to support for strong tree ordinances. One also must have a basis of attachment to tree places, which is predicted by tree knowledge and experience with caring for trees around one’s home. In conclusion, limitations and suggestions for future research are provided.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1070</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2192&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>urban forest</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>environmental policy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>sense of place</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>GIS</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>structural equation modeling</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>attitudes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2197</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-07T22:47:28Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Women and the Environment: Mediating and Moderating Effects of Gender and Demographic Characteristics of Environmental Concern</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Price, Carmel Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:description>In this study I examine the relationship between environmental attitudes and gender.  First, I explore variations across previous studies to determine patterns regarding gender differences in levels of environmental concern. Second, I look at the mediating effects of gender and several socio-demographic characteristics (age, race, class, education, political orientation, residence, martial status, number of children, religious identification, and scientific knowledge) on a variety of measures of environmental concern to assess the extent to which gender operates through other variables as it predicts levels of environmental concern. Third, I look at the moderating effects of gender on the same list of socio-demographic characteristics to determine the extent to which gender intersects with other variables to shape environmental attitudes.
I conduct a systematic review of literature using 22 peer reviewed journal articles, which include 128 measures of environmental concern, published between 1995 and 2010. I also test for mediating and moderating effects of gender and various socio-demographic characteristics on 14 measures of environmental concern using data from two sources: the General Social Survey Environment II: 2000 questionnaire and the American National Election Study 2008 Times Series Pre-election Survey. To test for mediating and moderating effects I employee several methodological techniques including principal component analysis, model building, linear regression techniques, and non-parametric regression methods.
The results of this study show that, in general, women do express a greater concern for the environment than men. However, gender in conjunction with other socio-demographic characteristics has the potential to produce different effects than when gender is considered alone. This study supports the idea that the intersectionality of gender and other socio-demographic characteristics is of great importance and should not be ignored.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1116</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2197&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Environmental sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>environmental concern</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>ecogender</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>environmental demography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Place and Environment</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1111</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:03:07Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Bolivarian Alternative for the Americas: Rethinking Economic Integration After the Failures of Neoliberalism</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Williams, Shannon D.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The deteriorating societal conditions that have accompanied the implementation of the neoliberal model in Latin America have been well documented. This analysis draws heavily on this work to identify the emergence of de-industrialization, displacement of food production, exclusion of basic human services, and excessive unemployment following the application of neoliberal reform. Such ill effects have ushered in a strong anti-neoliberal current that has opened up new spaces for discussion and debate about alternative development models for the region. Perhaps the most radical alternative to emerge is the Bolivarian Alternative for the Americas (ALBA). ALBA’s architects have been explicit in their denunciation of neoliberalism and insist that ALBA is an alternative that has been designed to rectify the ills associated with neoliberal reform. The following analysis examines ALBA as an alternative idea and practice of development. The following analysis examines the ways in which ALBA is formulated as an abstract alternative to neoliberalism and highlights the concrete policies and projects that distinguish it from the defining aspects of the neoliberal model.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/82</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1111&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1205</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:04:39Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>From Gay Street to Turkey Creek: Knoxville’s Urban and Suburban Growth Machines</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Morris, Katherine Leigh</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Using growth machine theory, this study examines the newly built &quot;lifestyle center&quot; of the suburban Turkey Creek development and the redevelopment of the Gay Street corridor in downtown Knoxville, TN. Growth machine theory is one of sociology's predominant theories used to understand development and growth projects in metropolitan areas, and although not specifically defined in current literature, I suggest there are many differences in suburban and urban growth machines. This study examines the local dependency and organization of pro-growth coalitions; the tactics, ideology, and culture used to promote development projects; and community reactions. Upon completion of this project, I found that urban and suburban growth machines differed in local dependency and level of community opposition, but utilized similar tactics, ideology, and culture. Furthermore, several themes emerged at the conclusion of this project- the attempts to structure social life around retail centers, suburbanization, and the increasing influence of growth language in everyday life- the further impact increasing pro-growth coalition influence.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/173</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/MorrisKatherine.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1772</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:05:11Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Modernity, Capitalism, and War: Toward a Sociology of War in the Nineteenth Century, 1815-1914</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Lybeck, Eric Royal</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The academic discipline of Sociology has rarely broached the subject of war and its recursive relationship with society. This paper addresses three major approaches in several disciplines that can be deemed ‘economically deterministic’: Marxist, Liberal, and Realist. These approaches can be useful for certain questions, but also leave out, or cloud other non-economic variables in understanding war – notably culture and military variables themselves. By using Karl Polanyi’s thesis regarding the “Myth of the Hundred Years’ Peace” (1815-1914) as a foil, the historical case of war in the nineteenth century is used to highlight the nature of war in European modernity and capitalism.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/728</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1772&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>war</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Europe</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>World War I</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nineteenth Century</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>capitalism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>modernity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>European History</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>International Relations</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Military History</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Politics and Social Change</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Theory, Knowledge and Science</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1139</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:05:20Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Media, Accounts, and Coherence: ‘De Facto’ Impression Management of a Transgressing Sport Star in &lt;em&gt;The Chicago Tribune&lt;/em&gt;</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Austin, Erin Maureen</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Using the Kobe Bryant sexual assault case as an example, this thesis attempts to understand how the media, specifically The Chicago Tribune, maintain the consistency of a certain representation given changing or new information. A full analysis of all 274 news articles found in The Chicago Tribune from June 30, 2003 (the date the alleged sexual assault took place) through August 31, 2004 (the day before the charges were dismissed), revealed five devices by which journalists managed Bryant’s image. These devices are: (1) case is not paramount, (2) case is hindering basketball, (3) external lures are to blame, (4) silver lining in the allegations, and (5) “court-to-the-court.” The Tribune writers used these devices in order to maintain the newspaper’s credibility as a consistent news source. The newspaper’s credibility was salvaged through reconstruction efforts to reconcile Bryant’s prior, positive persona with the current reality of the sexual assault allegations.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/108</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/AustinErin.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1970</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:05:36Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Passivity: Looking at Bystanding Through the Lens of Criminological Theory</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Manji, Rahim</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Criminologists have long since marginalized passivity as a variable of interest when studying the phenomenon of harm-doing.  In this thesis, I explore the role of passivity in such instances and build a case for its centrality to deviance.  I also undertake a number of other tasks.  First, I review the extent to which research throughout the academy has connected passivity to violence. Second, I explore whether criminological theories have incorporated the variable of passivity and how they could.  Lastly, I reflect on why more work on passivity has not been done given its manifest connection to harm, and I offer suggestions on how criminology can move forward in integrating bystander behavior in its theories of harm-doing.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/897</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1970&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>passivity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>bystanding</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>bystanders</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>criminological theories and passivity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>non-intervention</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Civic and Community Engagement</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Criminology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1061</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:06:15Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Construction of Social Networks of Support in a New Latino Gateway</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Conley, Meghan Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Beginning in the early 1990s and continuing through today, emerging Latino destinations such as Knoxville, Tennessee experienced tremendous growth in their population of Latina/o immigrants. Given that our traditional theories of immigrant adjustment address the formation of social networks exclusively in established immigrant gateways, and primarily based on observations of men, there is no reason to assume that Latina/o immigrants in emerging destinations build networks in similar ways as those in established destinations. This thesis first explores why some immigrants choose to migrate to Knoxville, Tennessee. Second, this thesis explores the extent to which the dominant theoretical frameworks of immigrant adjustment – specifically bounded solidarity and enforceable trust – speak to the behaviors of immigrants in one emerging Latino destination as they develop new networks of support. Third, by incorporating the voices of female immigrants alongside those of male immigrants, this thesis presents a gendered perspective on the creation of social networks. This thesis builds on previous research of immigrant support networks by examining how two largely understudied groups of immigrants – women and those in non-traditional gateways – adjust to life in the United States.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2009-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/32</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1061&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1502</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:06:58Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Industrial Concentration and Quality of Life</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Maples, James Nathaniel</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The purpose of this study is to examine the effects of industrial concentration at the county level on quality of life among residents of US counties. Data on various aspects of quality of life and industrial characteristics were collected for all United States counties. Four quality of life-related variables (infant mortality, percent of female-headed households, the burglary rate, and income inequality) were regressed on industrial concentration percentage and industrial concentration types. Industrial concentration was associated with an increase in infant mortality, a decrease in the burglary rate, and had no effect on the percent of female headed households or income inequality. Examining specific industry types, manufacturing proved significant in increasing the percent of female headed households, was less effective in reducing burglaries compared to other industry types, and was generally worse on quality of life than any other industry types.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2008-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/466</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008MastersTheses/MaplesJamesNathaniel.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1330</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:07:14Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Meth Epidemic in Rural Tennessee: Construction of a Social Problem</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Langley, Brian Harold</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Social constructionists argue that what problems are recognized as social problems in a society reflect the efforts of various individuals and organizations to frame particular issues as deserving of public attention and action. Illegal drugs (heroin, LSD, crack cocaine) repeatedly have been identified as social problems harming innocent victims (e.g., crack babies) and leading to various forms of criminal activity. The focus of this project is how media, specifically newspaper coverage, rose as claims makers identified methamphetamine (meth) production as a serious problem in rural areas of the southeast. Although the drug had been available under various names for decades, its definition as a problem requiring passage of new laws and the allocation of government resources can be linked to claims that operators of meth labs in rural areas were harming children, homes, the environment, and themselves. The southeast and particularly Tennessee were identified as having substantial rural areas where meth labs could be easily concealed. Using electronic data banks newspapers in the four largest cities in Tennessee (Memphis, Nashville, Knoxville, and Chattanooga) and one city in a more rural area (Clarksville), from 1990 to 2005 (for the earliest date accessible) that included the terms meth or methamphetamine were content analyzed. For each available year in the study time period the number of articles and the number of words in each story were recorded to establish trend data. At the beginning of the period few stories appeared. The number of stories dramatically increased in each newspaper between 2002 and 2003 or 2003 and 2004. One newspaper was selected to examine the typical location of stories, i.e., section placement. A key word analysis indicated that the primary claims makers were successful in that the media focused on the rural lab aspects of the meth story and gave limited play to the Mexican connection and drug usage in the gay community.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/297</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/Theses/LangleyBrian.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Rural Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1304</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:07:45Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Counterterrorism and the Deterrence Doctrine</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Cordy, Casey E.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The United States presently focuses much of its energy on the prevention of terrorism through particular counterterrorism policies and strategies. Today, deterrence is the primary theoretical basis for counterterrorism policies. If the United States invests so heavily in deterrence as a counterterrorism strategy, is it successful? If not, what are its theoretical flaws? Who is best served by efforts to prevent terrorism through a deterrent project?
This thesis will argue that a more appropriate understanding of terrorism is necessary. In order to achieve a more holistic conception of the terrorism problem, efforts should be made politically and theoretically to incorporate international relationships that include politics, economics and culture. Such an approach to understanding terrorism as a collective action that is related to various social structures is not facilitated within the 4 present theoretical application of deterrence to counterterrorism. Therefore, this thesis is a political and economic approach to understanding the relationship between theories of terrorism and strategies of counterterrorism. If deterrence is not the most appropriate way of addressing terrorism, then the first step to creating alternative strategies is to analyze the deterrence policies currently in place. Therefore, this thesis is a stepping stone to moving past present conceptions of how to address terrorism; in order to critique U.S. counterterrorism strategy and understand why deterrence is employed as a strategy so that we can create more suitable counterterrorism strategies.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/271</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/CordyCasey.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Politics and Social Change</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1293</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:07:50Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Falling Rate of Profit Thesis Reassessed: Toward a Sociology of Marx’s Value Theory of Labor</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Bradford, John Hamilton</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Marx considered his theory of the falling rate of profit to be one of the most important discoveries in the field of political economy. According to Marx’s theory, productivity increases put downward pressure on prices and hence profits. Recurrent crises of capital devaluation are both the consequence and solution to this pressure, aggravating the loss of profits initially, but enabling the pursuit of profits via accumulation to once again ensue. Marx’s argument, however, has been the subject of intense dispute for over a century. His critics charge that Marx’s thesis is not only improbable but impossible.
This study is an attempt at arbitration of this dispute, inspired by recent quantitative reinterpretations of Marx’s critique of political economy. In the interest of providing a detailed review of the theoretical and empirical literature surrounding this issue, I specifically address the debate about the “transformation” of values into prices. Resolving this issue not only removes some a priori objections to Marx’s value theory, it also provides a coherent interpretation of Marx’s falling profit rate thesis. It appears, then, that the alleged refutations of Marx have themselves been refuted.
In addition to investigating the logical validity of Marx’s argument, I attempt to ascertain whether and to what extent his argument is supported empirically. I therefore conduct a multivariate time-series regression analysis of various profit rates in the United States. I test several partially competing hypotheses concerning the most important determinants of the profit rate. Most importantly, I operationalize Marx’s concept of value by calculating an aggregate ratio of total price to total labor hours. I find that accelerating value accumulation correlates with a falling rate of profit, which is entirely consistent with Marx’s thesis.
Sociology, knowingly or not, has always been the study of modern society. Because of this, I suggest that there are certain core processes at work that are necessary for its reconstitution and which therefore retain a spatial and temporal contiguity. My aim in this study is to help reclaim for sociology the investigation of one of modern society’s most fundamental processes: the accumulation of value.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/261</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/BradfordJohn.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1290</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:07:57Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Does National Policy Influence Individual Car Driving Behavior: A Cross-National Study of the European Union</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Borek, Erika Lynn</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This study examines how the national policy climate affects individual driving behavior in the European Union. Using secondary data from the International Social Survey Program: Environment II 2000 in conjunction with national scores from the 2001 and 2002 Environmental Sustainability Indexes, I analyze the relationship between three macro-level predictors and the reduction of individual car driving. My results indicate that the national environmental policy climate positively relates with the likelihood of individuals driving less. Further individual’s likelihood to reduce car driving is significantly affected by the individual’s type of employment, education level, family income level, gender, age, and concerns toward the danger of air pollution for the environment and the respondent. Variables measuring respondent urbanicity, religiosity, and union/marriage status do not significantly affect individual driving behavior.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/258</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/BorekErika.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1617</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:07:58Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Georgian's Reaction to Water Shortage:  Water Conservation Behavior during the 2007 Drought</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Stoner, Alexander M</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This thesis examines whether or not differences in people’s water conservation attitudes, political party orientation, severity of drought, and attention to drought news affect their engagement in water conservation behavior during a time of continued water shortage.  Previously, it has been found that attitudes are predictive of intentions that relate to behaviors (e.g., Dietz et al. 2005).  Democrats have been shown to be more pro-environmental then Republicans (e.g., Dunlap et al. 2000).  It has also been found that severity of drought is positively related with environmental concern (e.g., Accury and Christianson 1990), and access to news information is directly related to willingness to take action (e.g., Johnson and Scicchitano 2000).
However, during a time of drought, what is the relationship between individual water conservation attitudes and behaviors?  Do conventional understandings of political party orientation and water conservation behaviors hold during a time of drought?   Do those living in counties that experience more severe drought engage in more water conservation behaviors?  Do those who pay more attention to drought news engage in more water conservation behaviors?  Using data from Georgia’s 2007 Peach State Poll, I explore the answers to these questions.
I examine how water conservation attitudes (Model 1), political party orientation (Model 2), drought severity (Model 3), attention to drought news (Model 4), sociodemographics, controls, and other factors from models 1-4 (Model 5) influenced water conservation behavior during the 2007 Georgia drought.
Results indicate that differences in people’s water conservation attitudes, political party orientation, drought severity, and attention to drought news did not significantly affect their water conservation behavior during the 2007 drought.  However, race, class, and gender variables in the full model did have a significant effect, which seems to suggest that one’s location in the social stratification system affects their opportunities to engage in water conservation behavior.  Therefore, environmental policy issues should not be considered apart from social issues.
The fundamental theoretical significance of the following research is that we affect and are in turn affected by the biophysical world in a dialectic fashion.  Recognizing the quality, quantity, and interrelatedness of nature-society relationships is essential for future research.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/663</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1617&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>environmental behavior</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>environmental concern</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>environmental attitudes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>water conservation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Demography, Population, and Ecology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1026</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:08:21Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Regulating the Global Politico-Economic Order: The Functioning of the Development Assistance Provision Regime</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Gann, Justin James</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This thesis is about the provisioning of development assistance, as a major component of foreign aid. Conventional approaches to the subject have tended to focus on the determinate interactions of discrete agents as the principle units of analysis. This necessarily obscures the functional role development assistance fulfills in relation to the global politico economic order, however.   This study, by contrast, properly situates individual programs of development assistance as belonging to a much larger historical pattern, or system of coordinated politico-economic behavior. The objective, therefore, is to apprehend the systematic and functional interrelations existing (i) among the various agents engaged in the transfer of assistance, on the one hand, and (ii) between these institutions and organizations as an aggregate and the global order itself, on the other. ‘Regime analysis’ is utilized as the preferred method of analysis.   The basis of the argument is that the regime for the provision of development assistance functions as a regulative-control mechanism, ancillary to the prevailing economic arrangements and relations within the global political economy. Altogether, I argue that regime apparatuses have been configured so as to (i) forestall cataclysmic instabilities in the global politico economic order, and (ii) to induce compliance among developing nations to the order’s organizing principles and-or logic. This is revealed in phases in the liberalization and-or illiberalization of access to external financing over different global-historical epochs and during periods and in contexts of either instability or stability.   I find that during periods and in contexts of instability, development assistance has been initiated or expanded in geo-strategic ways so as to regenerate markets and, thereby, obviate, or thwart the anticipated metastasization of adversarial politico-economic organizational frameworks. During periods and in contexts of relative stability, conversely, I find that the provision of development assistance becomes contracted, or made less expansive, as well as increasingly driven by conditionalities. Consequently, the functioning of the regime structurally conditions the developmental orientations and prospects of peripheral nations and regions and, thereby, also contributes to the overall evolution of the global politico-economic order.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2010-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/622</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1026&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Development Assistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Aid</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Development</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Globalization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Global Political Economy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Newly Industrializing Countries</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Work, Economy and Organizations</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1249</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:08:50Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Extraction, Ecology, Exploitation, and Oppression: The Political Economy of Coal in Appalachia</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Wishart, William R.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This thesis examines the social and ecological problems associated with mountaintop mining in central Appalachia. Theoretical insights from world system theorists and other political economists are used to trace the roots of these problems to the historical progression of different modes of extraction in the region. The restructuring of the region’s social, cultural, and ecological systems to meet the needs of core production over time has perpetuated its position as a resource extractive periphery. This occurred in three major modes: a frontier mode, an agricultural mode, and an industrial raw materials mode. The last mode has been characterized primarily by coal mining and has shifted from labor intensive forms to capital intensive forms. The role different classes of actors have played and continue to play is discussed. Finally, key processes are summarized and conclusions offered.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2007-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/217</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/WishartWilliamR.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-1415</identifier>
		<datestamp>2011-12-08T17:08:53Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Skin Color Bias in the Immigration Process: A Multi-Methods Approach</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hendricks, Sarah E</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This study looks at the intersection of the literature on immigration and on phenotype and life chances. As immigrant populations in the United States have shifted from European countries of origin to Latin American and Asian countries of origin in recent decades, the phenotype of these populations of immigrants is increasingly distinct from the privileged mainstream U.S. population with European origins. Do darker shades of skin color lead to correspondingly different experiences in the United States immigration system?
This study uses data from the New Immigrant Survey 2003 to explore the relationship between skin color and the duration of the legal permanent residency application process. The findings are supplemented by interviews with immigrants and agencies, providing a more nuanced understanding of the variety of experiences within the immigration process.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2008-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/382</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/HendricksSarah.pdf</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2193</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-04-25T01:16:18Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Mediating Justice: Toward A Critical-Reflexive Sociology</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Gondo, George Christopher</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Today, an increasing number of sociologists incorporate the theme of social justice within their work and strive to contribute to efforts to improve existing social conditions. In their view, sociological work that actively engages in issues related to social justice exemplifies ‘the promise’ of sociology and represents a means of refocusing and reinvigorating the discipline at a time of perceived crisis. Yet, a growing body of evidence questions whether previous efforts to use sociology as a mechanism of improving social conditions have been successful. In this thesis, I rely on the works of Alvin W. Gouldner to examine the relationship between sociology and the pursuit of social justice. Specifically, I contend that Gouldner’s works reflect an awareness of the problematic nature of such projects while attempting to reconstruct the practice of sociology in a manner that addresses its shortcomings. Thus, Gouldner’s body of work deepens our understanding of the problematic nature of using existing social scientific paradigms to pursue particular conceptions of social justice while attempting to formulate a vision for a new kind of social science more suitable for such a task.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1069</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2193&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Social Justice</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Alvin W. Gouldner</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Critical-Reflexive Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Critiques of Social Science</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inequality and Stratification</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Politics and Social Change</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Theory, Knowledge and Science</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2186</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-04-25T01:17:54Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Education &amp; Crime: A Study in Student Perceptions of Culpability</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Long, Larry Curtis</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Criminological research has long been concerned with how stereotypes of offender race and gender affect perceived culpability and policy formation. Using data collected from a college student population that were administered six vignettes written in the form of police blotters that depicted different crimes being committed by offenders with differing educational characteristics, this study seeks to identify whether or not an offender’s educational characteristics affect their perceived culpability. Although the data indicates that offender’s are seen as culpable regardless of their educational characteristics, it is evident that some degree or sociopathy is assessed to offender’s that are seen as educated and commit both White Collar and Street crimes.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1080</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2186&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Culpability</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Education</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Crime</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Psychology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociopathy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Stereotypes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Criminology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social and Behavioral Sciences</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Psychology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2213</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-04-25T23:58:29Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Financial Crisis as an Expression of Macrohistorical Trends: World Hegemony, Neoliberal Globalization, and  Financialization in 21st Century Capitalism</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Willson, Shane Montgomery</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Many studies try to understand the financial crisis that began in 2007 by utilizing short-term perspectives, but few step back far enough to see how macrohistorical transformations created the environment for a crisis of immense magnitude. In this work, I apply Arrighi’s theory of systemic cycles of accumulation to the current crisis and find that, while this theory elucidates some broad features of the global political economy that fostered the crisis, Arrighi’s explicit limitations lead to further areas of inquiry that help to understand this crisis in its specificity.
By analyzing large-scale historical lines unique to the late 20th century, I show that financialization and globalization – mediated through US world hegemony and neoliberalism – created feedback loops promoting, not just a quantitative rise in the use of finance, but qualitative changes to overarching production, distribution, and consumption practices throughout the global economy. Some of these changes include the integration of many new and varied actors into the financial sector, the financialization of the globalized production process, the increased use of finance by lower and middle classes to reproduce labor in the face of stagnant wages, and the increased use of derivatives for profit-making.
Additionally, I elaborate market-level changes in the US financial sector and show how the aforementioned macro-level transformations expressed themselves through the crisis. The use of “slice and dice” and “originate and distribute” models crippled the functions of derivatives and promoted their widespread misuse, even in the face of highly regarded theories of risk management. A historical view of derivatives shows that, while their use may be a fundamental cause of the crisis, derivatives express deeper trends in the evolution of capitalism: derivatives increase alienation, change the way we view ownership, and increase competition in our globalized political economy.
This long-term view allows me to elaborate how the nexus of financialization, globalization, neoliberalism, and world hegemony came together to create the most far-reaching financial crisis since the Great Depression.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2011-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1108</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2213&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Financial Crisis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>World Hegemony</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neoliberalism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Globalization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Financialization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Derivatives</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2517</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-08-22T17:59:30Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Effect of Race on Crime: A Multilevel Analysis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Cui, Wanjun</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Many studies have been carried out to examine the sources of racial disparities in crime.  However, there are some limitations in most of those studies. One limitation is that the majority focus on black-white comparisons.  Another limitation is that many primarily examine violent offending.  In addition, most studies have solely relied on either contextual level or individual level explanations.  My dissertation attempts to address these limitations in previous literature by using data from the first wave of the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health to examine racial disparities in different types of offenses among non-Latino whites, non-Latino blacks, non-Latino Asians, and Latinos.  I use a multilevel linear method to model self-reported violent, property, and drug offenses when controlling both contextual level and individual level covariates that are drawn from social disorganization, anomie/strain, social learning, and social bond theory, simultaneously.  Different from previous studies, I also use item response modeling to construct measures for my dependent variables such as violent offense.  Findings from my dissertation show that there are some disparities in different types of offending between white and non-white adolescents.  Furthermore, the gaps in different types of offending for Asian-white, black-white, and Latino-white comparisons are affected by different explanatory covariates.  Demographic background such as immigration status, school bonds, and grades (social bond theory) seem to explain Asians’ lower level of reported violence in relation to whites.  The gaps in violence between whites and blacks seem to stem from multiple sources.  All aforementioned four theories seem to provide some explanations for this group comparison, but none of these theories explain away the differences in violent offending between them.  For Latino-white gaps in violence, contextual effects such as concentration disadvantages account for the differences between these two groups.  As for property and drug offending, the social learning predictor peer delinquency seems to explain the gaps between whites and other races.  Additionally, different covariates such as peer delinquency, school bond, and grades also have differential effects on different types of offense across different neighborhoods.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1286</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2517&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Criminology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2338</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-08-28T23:04:18Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>New Means, Old Ends? World Bank Governmentality in Thailand and Lao People's Democratic Republic</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Zeller, Nicholas Ryan</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The purpose of this research is to make explicit the arts of government, defined as a field of power in the Foucauldian sense, employed by the World Bank in the cases of Pak Mun Dam in Thailand and Nam Theun II Dam in Lao PDR. Much of the literature on the latter case, both from the World Bank and its critics, focuses on the incorporation of conservation practices and the creation of state apparatuses which account for natural resources and local populations through a discourse of environmentalism. Using World Bank planning and evaluation documents, I argue that although these practices represent an escalation of the role of environmentalism in the justificatory logic for new hydropower projects, they do not represent a change in the World Bank’s major justificatory mechanism, the presence or absence of institutional structures necessary for present and future project implementation. That is, project justifications continue to rest, on the one hand, on an already established relationship with the borrower such that the World Bank’s technical and managerial expertise can be easily transmitted, or, on the other hand, the presumed likelihood that such a relationship can be established. In either case, the emphasis is on the creation of what I call a seasoned borrower and its inclusion into the production of knowledge legible to development discourse.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1224</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2338&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Governmentality</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>World Bank</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Thailand</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Laos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hydropower</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dams</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Politics and Social Change</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2545</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-08-29T13:37:08Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Seeing the Forest for the Trees: Finance and Managerial Control in the US Forest Products Industry, 1945-2008</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Gunnoe, Andrew Augustus</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Over the past three decades a significant change has taken place in the ownership structure of industrial timberlands in the United States. The once widely held belief that significant timberland ownership was a necessary ingredient for success in the forest products industry came to an end as millions of acres of productive land were sold from industrial forest products firms to institutional investment organizations, known as Timberland Investment Management Organizations (TIMOs) or Real Estate Investment Trusts (REITs). This dissertation examines this large-scale transfer of timberland ownership through a multi-level analysis of financialization and the rise of shareholder value ideology in corporate management. Part I of the dissertation provides a critical synthesis of these two literatures in order to construct a historical sociological framework for analyzing institutional change in modern corporations. Financialization is defined as a gravitational shift from productive to financial forms of capital accumulation. I then conceptualize the relationship between managers and shareholders as an institutional form of the broader social relation that exists between productive and financial capitalists. The shareholder value conception of managerial control is conceptualized as an ideological manifestation of the shift that took place in the relationship between these two sectors of the capitalist class that motivated and justified managerial decision-making in large non-financial corporations. Part II employs this framework to examine the historical development of the US forest products industry over the course of the second half of the 20th century. This includes an analysis of corporate land ownership strategies during the postwar era of managerial capitalism, the impact of the hostile takeover movement, and the rise of shareholder capitalism in recent decades. I argue that both the decision by managers to sell-off their timberland holdings and the growth of institutional investors seeking to expand their investment portfolios are directly related to the process of financialization. Furthermore, I conclude that the financialization of the US forest product industry led to favorable outcomes for financial interests, but has left the industry with higher levels of concentration, fewer employees, heightened risk, and declining profits.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1299</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2545&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Financialization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Shareholder Value</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Forest Products Industry</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Management</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Timberland</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Monopoly Capitalism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Political Economy</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2472</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-12-06T17:31:47Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Short-Term Missions: Reinforcing Beliefs and Legitimating Poverty</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Taylor, William Vaughan</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Every year more than a million short-term missionaries travel abroad. Many encounter intense poverty. Popular discourse suggests short-term missionaries return home radically changed. Social movement theory shows collective experiences can transform participants. In this thesis I explore the narratives of short-term missionaries to understand how they understand the poverty they encounter abroad. I have found short-term mission participants think about encounters with the poor in ways that produce contradictory beliefs and legitimate poverty. Interviewees consistently employed deficiency and fatalistic theories of poverty that provide little moral or practical justification for helping the poor. However, these beliefs conflicted with religious convictions. Interviewees reported increased awareness of physical and psychic suffering caused by poverty. However, they consistently romanticized poverty and enumerated its special spiritual, lifestyle, cultural, and psychological advantages. Most explicitly eschewed ethnocentrism and paternalism but employed deeply ethnocentric and paternalistic narratives. Short-term missions did not radically transform participants. Instead, the change is a slight amplification of existing beliefs that reinforce the status quo. Religious beliefs and the absence of alternative schemas or groups make it unlikely participants will develop challenging perspectives. This study highlights the difficulty we have developing critical perspectives on ideas that so powerfully support the legitimacy of our own favorable circumstances.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1288</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2472&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>religion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Christianity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>short-term mission</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>stratification beliefs</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>poverty</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2457</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-12-06T17:31:51Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Global Debt Minotaur: An Analysis of the Greek Financial Crisis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Panageotou, Steven Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Since November 2009, Greece has been mired in financial crisis with little indication that it will be solved in the near future. Research and media accounts have faulted Greece for sowing the seeds of its own financial crisis through fiscal mismanagement extending back to the 1980’s. Successive Greek governments have been criticized for racking up an unsustainable amount of foreign debt. Due to the prevalence of such accounts, European officials and Greek politicians have adopted a nationally oriented strategy to resolve the current crisis. This strategy means that the brunt of the reform effort falls on Greece to neoliberalize its economy in an attempt to fix its macroeconomic finances. In effect, Greece is viewed as ‘the sick man of Europe’ that must be ‘cured’ through structural adjustment measures and through liberalization, deregulation, and privatization of the economy. It is commonly thought that if Greece can fix its macroeconomic finances, then the crisis will be solved.
With expected deficit reductions failing to be achieved time and time again and the debt-to-GDP ratio continuing to climb, clearly this reform strategy is failing to provide a real solution to the crisis. This is because the Greek financial crisis is not strictly a national problem. Instead, the situation is a crisis of the eurozone, and any viable solution must take this into consideration.
When Greece adopted the euro in 2001, Greece effectively became a marginalized and indebted country in Western Europe. Greek exports became less competitive when Greece was tied to a hard euro currency, and it became economically rational for Greece to use cheap subsidies offered by the European Union to fund the importation of commodities produced in the core of the eurozone (Germany, France, Netherlands, Luxembourg). In effect, the creation of the eurozone created a massive power imbalance between the strong, Northern European countries and the weak, Southern European countries, Portugal, Spain, and Italy included. Until European officials take this dynamic into consideration and recommend a global reform strategy that takes the structured power imbalance into account, nationally oriented reforms will continue to be implemented in Greece, and the crisis will continue.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1291</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2457&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Greek Financial Crisis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Political Economy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Structural Adjustment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neoliberalism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Europe</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Other Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2632</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-12-06T17:33:53Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Parenting Behind Bars:  A Qualitative Study of Incarcerated Mothers</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Easterling, Beth Allen</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Policies of mass incarceration have resulted in a dramatic increase in the prison population in the United States over the past few decades. The number and proportion of women who are incarcerated have vastly increased as a result. Despite increased interest among criminologists, a variety of questions remain as to how women experience incarceration. Most women who are incarcerated are mothers, but criminological literature has yet to fully explain how mothers fulfill their parenting roles or navigate motherhood while incarcerated. No dominant theoretical framework exists to explain the experiences of incarcerated mothers in relation to their mothering roles. This research addresses such limitations by exploring the question: How do incarcerated mothers negotiate motherhood from behind bars?
Data from this study come from qualitative interviews with 49 mothers (35 individually and 14 in group settings) serving time at the Kentucky Correctional Institute for Women. Findings suggest that incarcerated mothers experience ambiguous loss of children and the mother identity. They deal with that loss through coping strategies to preserve motherhood and by redefining the mother role. Policy recommendations and suggestions for future research based on findings are discussed.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1408</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2632&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>incarceration</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>family</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>motherhood</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>ambiguous loss</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>prison</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Criminology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2645</identifier>
		<datestamp>2012-12-06T17:35:32Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Gender, Social Ties, And Reentry Experiences</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Scroggins, Jennifer Rhiannon</dc:creator>
<dc:description>A great deal of research has been conducted on factors associated with successful prisoner reentry. However, except for a few studies on women's reentry, most studies have failed to examine the role of parolees' social ties in contributing to reentry outcomes. Additionally, most studies on prisoner reentry only focused on male parolees, and few addressed the influence of gender on reentry experiences. Thus, my goal in this dissertation is to understand the influence of gender on male and female parolees' social ties, and how the resources their ties provide shape their reentry experiences. My dissertation research examines men and women’s strong- and weak-tie relationships and the resources available to them via their relationships to understand how these resources shape their reentry experiences. Study data, which were collected from in-depth interviews with fifty men and women under parole supervision, showed that they underwent many changes in their strong- and weak-tie relationships during and after incarceration. Shifts toward closer and more positive relationships with families and the addition of pro-social weak-tie relationships resulted in more tangible and intangible resources that were considered by the men and women as important to their reentry success. Data analysis showed that the relationship patterns experienced by the men and women in the present study were largely consistent with gendered relationship patterns described in the literature, but that patterns of resource availability from their social ties were less consistent with those described in the literature. Findings from the study suggest the influence of gender on men and women's social ties, as reflected in different patterns of strong-tie relationships experienced prior to, during, and after incarceration, and also reveal some similarities between men and women with regard to increases in the number of weak-tie relationships with various pro-social individuals after incarceration. By showing the significant role of social ties, especially strong-ties, in providing tangible and intangible resources to parolees upon their release from prison, this study provides support for social control theory and highlights the importance of helping ex-offenders develop and maintain positive social ties with pro-social individuals to enhance the availability of resources necessary for successful reentry.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1455</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2645&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Gender</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reentry</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Parole</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Networks</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Criminology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2627</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-02-20T20:46:36Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Changes in US Ethnic Niches, 2005-2010</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Maples, James N.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Ethnic niches are overrepresentations of an ethnic group in an occupation or industry. Ethnic niches occur as a mechanism for coping with discrimination in the larger labor market. Studies on ethnic niches have typically focused on single cities (such as Los Angeles or New York), but they have failed to provide a larger picture of ethnic niches in the United States. Hence, researchers know much about niches in a few places but very little about the state of ethnic niches across the United States. Additionally, researchers know a great deal more about the niche behavior of some groups (notably Cubans and Chinese) than others. Also, researchers have rarely examined changes in ethnic niches over time. In this study, I create a comprehensive snapshot of US ethnic niches from 2005 to 2010. Utilizing data from the American Community Survey, I analyze eight ethnic groups (Asian Indians, Chinese, Cubans, Filipinos, Koreans, Japanese, Mexicans, and Vietnamese) in the fifty largest metropolitan statistical areas in the United States across six years. From this, I create a descriptive picture of which ethnic groups control what ethnic niches, where they are located, and how they have changed over the last half of the 2000-2010 decade. I examine which groups, if any, are concentrated in specialized niches and why. I examine which US cities offer the most niche options for ethnic groups. I also examine in detail those niches that appear to be protected from members of other ethnic groups and discuss the reasons that some niches are protected. Finally, I examine the resiliency of niches, in general, and under conditions of extreme shock. Toward this end, I present an in-depth study of the Chinese-dominated garment industry in San Francisco before and after the Great Recession. I also study Mexican worker niches in New Orleans that arose in the aftermath of Hurricane Katrina.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1421</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2627&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>ethnic niche</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>enclave</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>queue</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>protected labor market</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inequality and Stratification</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2737</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-04-12T19:51:59Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Murder for Hire: Event Characteristics and Causal Implications</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Corsaro, Nicole Madonna</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The problem of criminal homicide has been extensively studied. A productive way to examine it has been through detailed analysis of homicides as criminal events. There are a number of characteristics that are common to all homicide events, such as background circumstances, participant characteristics, and interrelationships of offenders. However, murder-for-hire events contain distinctive interactive features that are not present in other types of criminal homicide, i.e. solicitor, hitman, and target scenarios and that have not received empirical attention. Using trial transcripts, news reports, pre-sentence investigations, and Tennessee Department of Correction records, 30 murder-for-hire events  have been identified involving 60 individuals convicted of solicitation and/or conspiracy to commit murder or attempted murder in Tennessee. In this study, details about these murder-for-hire events are explored in terms of the following variations: race, age, and sex of solicitor(s), hitmen, and targets across events; method, place of occurrence, time, and type of interpersonal relationship among participants. The results are compared with existing information on these characteristics for typical homicide events. The data suggest that murder-for-hire events involve different offender-victim profiles from those found in typical homicides. Implications of these differences for causal explanations of homicide events are explored.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1998-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1355</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2737&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2642</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-04-22T18:14:10Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>&quot;To Preserve This Much-Injured Race&quot;: Techniques of Neutralization and Indian Removal, 1829-1831</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Keeton, Robert Michael</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The Indian Removal Act of 1830 gave the President of the United States the authority to negotiate treaties with the Native American tribes in the east for their emigration to territory west of the Mississippi River. Although the emigration was technically voluntary, in practice, the Native tribes emigrated under coercion and force, the most infamous instance of which was the Cherokee Trail of Tears in 1838, which resulted in the deaths of at least 4,000 Native people. This dissertation applies Sykes and Matza’s (1957) neutralization theory to archival data including the papers of Andrew Jackson and publications documenting the removal debate, to explain how the policy was justified notwithstanding American norms and public opposition. Examples of neutralization techniques, especially denial of responsibility and denial of victim, were identified within the rhetoric of removal supporters, as were two new categories of neutralization: reducing the target and urgency of the moment. The research explores possibilities for the application of criminological theory for the study of atrocity crime.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1587</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2642&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Atrocity Crime</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Indian Removal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trail of Tears</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neutralization Theory</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mass Harm</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Discourse</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Criminology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2494</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-04-22T19:48:55Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Politics of Protection and Promotion: the Case of the Coal Industry in Environmental Politics</dc:title>
<dc:creator>East, Elizabeth Ashley</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Business actors have historically been an important point of discussion for environmental sociologists. However, theoretical assumptions of business as an environmental actor provide divergent understandings of business’s role in environmental problems, politics, and improvements. Also, empirical studies of business actors primarily examine how individual firms or industry-funded organizations participate in specific environmental controversies or in the attempted implementation of specific environmental policies. Although these approaches have been instrumental in understanding the roles power, privilege, and resources play in environmental politics, they present an understanding of business engagement in environmental issues as reactionary rather than sustained. Such a characterization neglects the long-term political strategies of business entities in environmental politics. A more comprehensive understanding of business political engagement, particularly of the organizations, claims, and tactics these actors use in environmental politics and how these change or remain the same over time, is needed to help clarify and evolve theoretical assumptions and empirical examinations of business actors.
Taking the case of a coal industry-funded organization, currently known as the American Coalition for Clean Coal Electricity, this study documents how a group of business actors in the coal industry organized and engaged in environmental politics over a 15-year period. Findings suggest these business actors collectively organized and pursued a political strategy of protection of their interests and positive promotion of their products and processes.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1370</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2494&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>environmental politics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>extractive industries</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>corporate politics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Place and Environment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Politics and Social Change</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2468</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-04-22T19:49:36Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Growing a Local Movement: New Social Movements, Food, and Activism</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hysjulien, Liam Vangsnes</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Over the last decade, concerns over healthy eating, the systemic causes of hunger, and alternative ideas over food production and consumption have become more prevalent issues in mainstream American society. This has resulted in increasing literature on whether alternative food movements and local food advocates are an emerging social movement. In using Knoxville, Tennessee as a case study, this thesis explores how historical changes in food-based welfare created conditions for increased local activism around issues of hunger and food insecurity. Second, this thesis uses interviews from key local food advocates to determine how their activism is shaped by personal identity, the building of coalitions, and the search for resources. Lastly, using New Social Movements literature, this thesis presents an understanding of how issues of identity, coalition building, and the search for resources influence local food activism. This thesis builds on previous research into how the New Social Movements literature informs the actions, role, and goals of many emerging new movements.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1385</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2468&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>food movement</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>community food security</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>hunger</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>welfare</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2543</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-04-22T19:49:51Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Understanding Biotechnology:  Conceptualizing and Measuring US Public Concern</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Lamphere, Jenna Ann</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Biotechnology has had a short but rather conflict-ridden history. The technology was commercialized in 1995 and since has become a volatile topic for international debate. Arguably, the United States is the biggest supporter of this technology. The United States conducted the first study using recombinant DNA, grows more biotech crops than any other country, and houses the vast majority of the largest biotech corporations. Proponents frequently claim that biotech crops are a way to improve crop production, lower food prices, decrease the need for petrochemical inputs, and alleviate international food security problems. Others see them as accelerating the loss of traditional agricultural techniques, raising the costs of agricultural production, increasing inequalities, and posing significant environmental and human health risks. The European Union has been more hesitant than the United States to adopt the use of biotechnology, which has resulted in open, international conflict. Given the novelty of and gross conflict over this technology, deeper analyses are needed before many of these concerns can be alleviated or substantiated.
Examining public concern can provide a rich description of the issues surrounding biotechnology. Since the emergence of biotechnology, the European Union, via the Eurobarometer, has frequently administered surveys to its members to measure public concern. Conversely, the United States has failed to systematically administer surveys to measure concern over biotechnology. Instead, US studies have tended to be ad hoc, a-theoretical, and noncumulative, which has thwarted the evolution of a well-developed literature on US public concern for biotechnology. Therefore, the aim of this study is to examine US public opinion data to identify the dimensions inherent in the indictors of social concern surrounding biotechnology. Questionnaires administered between 1993 and 2010 containing at least one measure of biotech concern were collected. To identify the dimensions of concern, a thematic content analysis was conducted on the opinion questions. Public concern was measured by the percentage of people that express concern in their responses to the questions. I also examine trends in concern, as they relate to the dimensions of concern proxied by the indicators.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2012-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1389</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2543&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>biotechnology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>genetic modification</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>public opinion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>public concern</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3157</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-07-29T16:50:45Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Multiculturalism and the State: Globalization, National Protection, and the Role of Social Policy in Québec and Canada</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Blad, Corey Allen</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This dissertation is an historical comparative examination of economic globalization (i.e., global market integration) effects on state political economic capacities in Québec and Canada. The central goal of the project is to understand how global market integration has altered the policy capacities of state institutions. Specifically, this dissertation examines Canadian multiculturalism and Québec interculturalism as social policy responses to ethno-cultural diversification resulting from increased global market integration. I argue that increased global market integration decreases state capacity to enact economic protections, but not the demand for protections from national populations. The result of these changes (ethno-cultural diversification and decreased economic policy capacity) is a shift in social policy capacity toward control and management of national cultural definitions, symbols, and structures of meaning. That is, as state capacity to meet national protectionist demands through economic policy decreases as a result of global market integration, the state must seek out alternative means of meeting national protectionist demands. These means are found in the management and control of national culture. The dissertation further concludes that this political re-orientation enables national populations to increases their relative power with respect to the state. This has placed the state in a precarious position between the powerful demands of global market proponents and the increasingly powerful demands of national populations for protections from the adverse affects of market integration.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2006-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1641</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3157&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3180</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-08-02T18:27:26Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Exploring Sexual Scripts: College Students’ Perceptions of Seduction and Rape</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Cravens, Nicole Corsaro</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Previous research has utilized script theory as an important tool for social scientists in understanding people’s attitudes and beliefs regarding problematic events, e.g., rape and violence. A study conducted by Ryan (1988) has shown the different scripts for rape and seduction scenarios perceived by introductory level college students. The present study is an extension of Ryan’s research on rape and seduction perceptions. Data will be collected from students currently enrolled at The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, instructing them to describe a &quot;typical&quot; rape and &quot;typical&quot; seduction scenario. These will be analyzed to: identify common stories of rape and seduction among college students; 2) compare freshmen-sophomore and junior-senior stories; and 3) compare males and females stories on rape and seduction. Data will include a detailed descriptive overview of elements presented in students’ stories; comparisons of stories with elements from current typologies; and excerpts from stories suggesting a new script, that is, scripts with new sequencing patterns and elements.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2006-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1658</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3180&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-2894</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-08-12T19:33:10Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Mobility and Isolation: Latino Immigrant Adjustment in Atlanta, Georgia</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hendricks, Sarah Ellen</dc:creator>
<dc:description>In the automobile society of the United States, virtually every adult needs a car to work, shop, and participate in social institutions. However, not everyone has a car. One of the populations with low access to vehicles is the Latin American immigrant population. This study asks to what extent Latino immigrants experience spatial constraints due to lack of mobility, what mobility strategies do they use in order to function in a context of automobility, and to what extent transportation limitations are associated with another socially isolating factor – English proficiency. I investigate these questions for employed Latino immigrants in the Atlanta, Georgia metropolitan area, which is a new Latino destination that has a particularly poor transportation system. Data sources include US Census summary files for 1980-2010, data from the Census Transportation Planning Package from 2000, and American Community Survey 2006-2010 pooled microdata.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1732</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2894&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>immigation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>transportation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>adjustment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>adaptation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>assimilation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>spatial mismatch</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Demography, Population, and Ecology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Place and Environment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Race and Ethnicity</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3235</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-08-19T22:34:49Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>A Study of the Characteristics Affecting Organizational Behavior of Nursing Homes and Related Home Care Facilities During Emergency Evacuations</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Vogt, Barbara Muller</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Both emergency planners and disaster researchers cite the lack of empirical data on the problems and needs of special populations during emergency evacuations. Although most evacuations of nursing homes and related care facilities are carried out successfully, the effectiveness of an evacuation (as measured by time to evacuate) appears limited by certain constraints. Among the factors affecting such evacuations are resources (such as the number of staff available at the time of the evacuation), type and number of clients, and community characteristics such as population density. This study describes selected organizational characteristics of nursing homes and related care facilities which have recently experienced either a partial or complete evacuation of their facilities. After discussing the theoretical aspects of organizations in evacuations and the methodology used for the study, the study discusses both the quantitative and qualitative factors affecting organizational behavior during evacuation.It is evident from the findings that the continuity of responsible care for clients is of critical concern to both management and staff during an evacuation. The findings suggest that individuals within specialized populations are unlike other disaster victims and may require different management strategies on the part of agencies assisting in the evacuation.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1988-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1815</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3235&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3454</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-09-24T17:34:16Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Toxic Communities:  Examining the Relationship between Race, Market Forces, and Environmental Hazards using Elementary Schools as Community Locus</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Gonzales, Stephanie Joy</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The purpose of this study is to examine the complex relationship between race, pollution, and market forces using elementary school zones as community locus within California.  This analysis examines the relationship between race and toxic facility sites using the Toxic Release Inventory (TRI), census data, and California school data.  This research improves on past research in several important ways.  First, the community is defined by giving attention to literature on environmental grassroots movements and the formation of informal social networks using local elementary schools as an organizational locus.  Second, the migration of Black, Hispanic, and White populations away from and towards toxic facility sites over a 20-year period is measured to help address the issue of market forces as a contributing factor in the disproportionate distribution of toxic facility sites in minority neighborhoods.  Third, each toxic facility is measured on its potential harm to the community by assessing the relative toxicity of chemicals released into the local environment.  Toxic Equivalency Potentials (TEP scores) provided by Scorecard are used to rate the relative toxicity of each facility.
Several conclusions can be drawn from this study.  First, even after controlling for market forces, measuring the mobility of the White populations away from toxic facility sites, there remains strong evidence of environmental racism.  Predominately Black and Hispanic communities are located almost 4 times closer to TRI facilities than are predominately White communities.  Second, the evidence suggests that White populations are moving away from TRI facilities, whereas Hispanic populations are settling near TRI facilities. There is no evidence to suggest that Black populations are moving towards TRI facilities.  Finally, TRI facilities located within 2-miles of predominately Black or Hispanic communities are no more toxic than TRI facilities located within 2-miles of predominately White communities.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2003-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2020</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3454&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-3414</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-01T19:03:43Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Culture of Intimidation: Power Relationships, Quiescence, and Rebellion in Oak Ridge, Tennessee</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Durbin, Barry R.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Studies suggest that quiescence, or the absence of challenge from deprived groups can be explained as a function of power relationships. Power has the potential to influence the decision-making process by monopolizing decision-making arenas. Furthermore, elites that occupy positions of power have the capability to resist challenges from deprived groups by preventing certain issues or grievances from ever being raised. This study’s focus is a former nuclear weapons production facility (the former K-25 Gaseous Diffusion Plant) in Oak Ridge, Tennessee, the quiescent nature of workers there, and the subsequent rise of rebellion. I employ a historical perspective using in-depth interviews and secondary data sources to investigate the perceptions of workers on power relationships. I explore the consequences of unequal power relationships on workers. K-25 was the first site built for the Manhattan Project in 1943. Findings indicate that the quiescent nature of K-25 workers cannot be explained by worker apathy or consensus with the status quo. In fact, the perception of quiescence can be explained by power relationships between dominant and subordinate groups. Generalized grievances were present, but were controlled and contained by the Department of Energy (DOE) and its corporate contractors. Even as rebellion emerged, traces of quiescence can still be found among workers in Oak Ridge.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2002-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2055</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3414&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-3540</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-08T20:52:42Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Survey of Student Opinion Toward Desegregation at the University of Tennessee</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Stone, Barbara</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The South is currently undergoing a period of transition for the traditional values, basic to a southern way of life, were upset by the 1954 Supreme Court decision concerning the desegregation of public schools. This ruling intensified the conflict between these traditional beliefs and attitudes of white supremacy and the fundamental principles of Christianity and democracy. Such conflict will not easily be resolved because it inevitably involves emotional behaviors which are not subject to logic or reason. The decision of the Supreme Court permitted the process of desegregation to be worked out by the local educational boards with all possible haste. Some three years following the decision, most of the South appears to be playing a waiting game. As a result of the actions of individual courts, the process of desegregating the elementary and secondary schools is progressing with mixed results.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1957-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2168</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3540&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3797</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-18T20:54:24Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Bridging Thought Communities: Implications of Membership in Degree-Completion Program Groups for the Self-Concepts of Adult Students</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Vos, Matthew S</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This study assesses the impact that an alternative delivery model in higher education may have for adult undergraduates who return to college.  In trying to adapt their institutions to the needs of adult students, and reduce barriers facing them, some colleges and universities have developed degree-completion programs.  In addition to offering convenient class times, some programs utilize what is known as a “group” or “cohort” model that provides a context within which students can find support, and which allows them to retain important outside-the-classroom statuses and identities.  The purpose of the study was to determine whether close identification with a group of relatively like others plays a role in elevating the self-concepts of adult students.
The research proposes that the group model utilized by some degree-completion programs may result in the creation of thought communities.  The study explores whether this delivery model has the potential to transform cohorts of adult students into thought communities from which learning cultures may emerge.  When groups become thought communities, learning environments can become places where students are less dependent on professors’ supervision, and are more empowered to recognize the depth of their own skill and experience, and the relevance of that experience to the ongoing task of learning.
Data for the study were obtained from nine program groups in the Covenant College Quest program.  A pretest-posttest quasi-experimental design was used to assess the impact of several features of small group process and structure on the self-concepts of adult students.  The pretest was administered when students first enrolled in the program, and the posttest was given when they entered their second semester (approximately seven months later).  Dependent variables were measured using the Tennessee Self-concept Scale (second version: TSCS:2).  Data for independent variables were obtained using a questionnaire designed by the researcher.  Complete pretest and posttest data were obtained from 109 Quest students (n = 109).  Results from multiple regression analysis suggested statistically significant relationships between “influence of instructor” and an increase in student “total” self-concept scores, and between the “group supplying imagery for a possible self” and an increase in total self-concept scores.  In addition, support was found for a positive relationship between a “student’s describing his/her group as cohesive” and an increase in “social” self-concept scores.
This study demonstrates that the program group does play a role in elevating the self-concepts of adult students in degree-completion programs.  It suggests that the program group provides a “context of possibility” from which thought communities may develop.  These thought communities may help bridge the gulf between the temporary world of higher education and the outside worlds which adult students inhabit.  This research raises questions about universalistic approaches to higher education and suggests that if education is to be made meaningful for adult students, the institutions that deliver education must develop programs that account for the mental memberships their students hold in worlds outside the academy.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2003-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2361</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3797&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3027</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-28T13:40:37Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Immigrant Rights in the Nuevo South: Enforcement and Resistance at the Borderlands of Illegality</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Conley, Meghan Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This dissertation examines the ways that immigrant illegality is structured and resisted in new Latino destinations in the US Southeast. I analyze the US Southeast as a new frontera, or borderland, for Latina/o immigrants, a border that is structured by racialized discourses of difference and belongingness between newcomer Latinas/os and long established Anglo and black populations. Experienced by Latina/o immigrants as a space of non-belongingness, this borderland has become an important site in the modern production of immigrant illegality. In the Southeast, illegality arises from the enforcement of non-belongingness, and it is structured through new forms of immigration enforcement, such as police-ICE collaboration and state-level “crimmigration” laws, which operate through what I refer to as the enforcement lottery and bureaucratic enforcement. These mechanisms render the threat of enforcement omnipresent, but never certain, producing illegality in everyday life and structuring the vulnerability of immigrants in the Southeast. Still, even as unauthorized immigrants are rendered vulnerable, they also resist the policies and practices that structure their illegality. Just as their vulnerabilities structure resistance, however, certain forms of resistance may actually legitimize illegality, ultimately reproducing the vulnerability of unauthorized immigrants.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2411</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3027&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Immigration</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Narrative</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ideology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>New Destinations</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Movements</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Latino</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Politics and Social Change</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3156</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-28T13:43:57Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>How Left a Turn? Legacies of the Neoliberal State in Latin America</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Rowland, Aaron Thomas</dc:creator>
<dc:description>In the 1980s and 1990s, the Latin American region experienced a profound shift in development ideologies that resulted in the creation of a new type of state: the Latin American neoliberal state. This state emerged in three stages: the stabilization stage—focused on balance of payments and austerity; the structural adjustment stage—which was more broadly and deeply focused on changing the structure and culture of society; and the institutional turn—which was an acknowledgment that the neoliberal state had not effectively dealt with poverty, inequality, or the quality of institutions that integrated market, society, and polity. Beginning in the early 2000s, an electoral shift to the left swept through the region and was characterized by antagonistic rhetoric towards neoliberal policies. This study compares the historical developments of Argentina, Ecuador, and Peru and shows that in cases where the neoliberal state was fully developed, the leftist shift either did not occur (Peru) during the 2000s, or where it did occur (Argentina) did not constitute a break with the neoliberal state but rather formed a fourth stage of neoliberalism. In this stage, the government sought to increase spending on some social programs but did so in ways that legitimated the wider neoliberal state rather than creating a new developmental model that would move beyond neoliberalism.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2475</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3156&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Argentina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Peru</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ecuador</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neoliberalism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>the State</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Economic Development</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Comparative Politics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Economic Policy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Growth and Development</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Latin American Studies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Politics and Social Change</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quantitative, Qualitative, Comparative, and Historical Methodologies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Policy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Work, Economy and Organizations</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3068</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-28T13:45:59Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Sociobiophysicality, Cold War, and Critical Theory: Human-Ecological Transformation and Contemporary Ecological Subjectivity</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Stoner, Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The United States is an important global player in resource depletion, energy use, waste production, and other indicators that contribute to economic threats to humanity’s ecological future. Critical theory provides conceptual tools that are uniquely well-suited to more fully comprehend the links between economic progress and ecological deterioration. In key regards, the present situation is the continuation as well as amplification of political-economic, social and cultural features that took hold during the Cold War, and which demand rigorous sociological focus, scrutiny and analysis. To date, however, sociology has barely begun to assess the consequences that resulted from the Cold War for the condition in which modern societies find themselves in the early twenty-first century, and for their ability to meet both persistent and new challenges. The purpose of this dissertation is to elucidate the present predicament, especially with regard to the link between modern society and natural environment, by introducing the concept of “sociobiophysicality” as a promising tool to address related issues in ways that highlight the importance of sociology today. To do so, however, the specific importance of the tradition of critical theory—especially as represented in the writings of Lukàcs, Adorno, and Postone—for sociology in general, and with regard to the link between human-ecological transformation and contemporary ecological subjectivity in particular—must be reconstructed and made explicit.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2488</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3068&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Environmental Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Marxism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Value</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dialectics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Critical Theory</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Political Economy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Earth Sciences</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Environmental Sciences</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Other Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Psychology and Interaction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Theory, Knowledge and Science</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3051</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-10-28T14:35:57Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Religion’s Influence on Environmental Concern: U.S. Evangelicals’ Construction of Climate Change Perceptions</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Routhe, Aaron S.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Scholars identify an emerging religious social base to U.S. environmentalism and public concern about anthropogenic global climate change. Surveys also show religious and political conservatives express skepticism about this environmental problem and oppose environmental regulations addressing it. White conservative Protestants reflect this contrast by denying human activity causes it and opposing climate policy for mitigating anthropogenic effects on Earth’s atmosphere, while concern and activism for climate protection simultaneously increases among other environmental evangelical Christians. Decades of quantitative investigations reveal religion’s role in environmental concern remains murky. Little clarity exists about how biblical literalism, “end times” eschatology, and religious environmental stewardship or creation care inform their opposition to environmentalism and emerging climate activism. How religion may constrain human agency in response to changing large-scale biophysical conditions or facilitate adaptation to global ecological change is unclear. This dissertation examines how religious beliefs inform public concern about global environmental problems among U.S. conservative Protestants using a qualitative research strategy and case study. It explores predominately white, Republican, educated, middle to upper-income evangelical Christians’ perceptions of climate change through individual, face-to-face unstructured interviews with 52 participants living in the Dayton, Ohio area. It describes how religion informs their climate change beliefs, perceptions it is a problem, and their responses from an applied sociology of knowledge perspective and within a constructionist approach to social problems. Participants differ in beliefs about anthropogenic climate change, but largely agree it is not a serious environmental problem. Six religious themes emerge: Creation beliefs, Sin beliefs, Anti-evolution, God’s involvement in the world, End Times, and Christian stewardship. Individuals’ religious mental schemas reflect literalist applications of Biblical texts to understand large-scale ecological conditions, a theology reducing human agency for addressing global environmental problems, and a perceived responsibility to engage in individual, pro-environmental actions in their everyday lives. This case study richly describes how religion informs public opinion, balances qualitative investigations of religious elites’ perceptions, and contextualizes quantitative analyses of lay evangelical Christians’ views. Implications arise from religion’s’ intersection with environmental policy, public environmental concern, and climate science communication to members of this highly religious segment of U.S. society.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2474</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3051&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Environmental concern and religion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>environmental policy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>evangelical Christian</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>environmentalism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>climate change</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>social construction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Place and Environment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Politics and Social Change</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rural Sociology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Theory, Knowledge and Science</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2814</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-11-05T17:59:54Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>“I am Working for the Good Guys:” Street-Level Enforcement of the Clean Water Act in East Tennessee</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Stover, Kayla Marie</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Environmental policies are designed to be governmental attempts to change social behaviors that have negative environmental consequences; they are intended to protect natural resources and the interests of U.S. citizens. However, the reality of policy enforcement rarely reflects these goals. Research shows that enforcement is often unequal, more stringent in some areas and weaker in others. The resulting environmental injustices are the manifestation of political interference and organizational impediments in the policy process. Most environmental policy analyses focus on the macro, federal-level of policy. In doing so, they neglect the final, crucial step in which policy is made real – enforcement. This thesis addresses the gaps in environmental policy research by studying the street-level bureaucrats who enforce the Clean Water Act (CWA), exploring the experiences of individual local regulators who write permits, run programs, and perform inspections. I engaged in ethnographic research to examine compliance enforcement at state and local levels. The data came from interviews and observations completed in the spring of 2011 with street-level environmental regulators in the Division of Water Quality in the Knoxville Field Office of the Tennessee Department of Environment and Conservation. Through this case study I draw connections among the experiences of street-level regulators, the politics of environmental policy, the problematic bureaucratic structure of public agencies, and the failures of environmental policies.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2464</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2814&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Environmental Policy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Clean Water Act</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bureaucracy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Water Protection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ethnography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Environmental Politics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Place and Environment</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3927</identifier>
		<datestamp>2013-11-26T20:47:48Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Toxins! Tocsin: The North Hollywood Dump in Memphis, Tennessee: A Community's Struggle Against Environmental Racism</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Johnson, Glenn Steve</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This research describes the &quot;voices&quot; of Hollywood residents who are impacted by a toxic landfill in their backyard. These residents were not included in the decision-making process to get the Hollywood Dump cleaned up. The residents were not allowed to be equal political participants in the Hollywood Dump issue. The residents lacked a strong collective resistance to influence local, state and federal officials to respond to this community problem. The &quot;voices&quot; of the Hollywood residents provided a natural history of a social problem which represents the political, cultural, and religious concerns of grassroots individuals who agreed that the local dump was posing an environmental, and public health threat to their community. This research concluded that the Hollywood Dump issue is a classic example of environmental racism which is a form of environmental injustice.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1996-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2528</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3927&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-2869</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-01-29T15:56:08Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Who Supports Labor? The Intersection of Race and Skill in Union Campaigns</dc:title>
<dc:creator>McKenney, Zachary Joseph</dc:creator>
<dc:description>In the past half century, there has been an unprecedented decline in labor union membership, organizing ability, political effectiveness and strike activity in the United States. As a result, the ability of labor unions to influence the debate on labor standards and social reforms has experienced a significant decline. Using a mixed method approach, this research explores differences in attitudes and orientations towards labor unions across racial groups in the United States as well as organizational strategies and capacities of a labor union in a right-to-work state. Although African Americans and Latinos have been discriminated against at the hands of organized labor, the quantitative component of this research indicates that minority groups hold more positive attitudes towards unions than whites. In light of this fact, organized labor has been slow to realize that its revitalization may be contingent upon the ability of unions to organize and recruit minority populations and very little emphasis has been placed on the effects of racial differences in attitudes and orientations toward union membership and union support. Although the quantitative component of this research indicates that minority groups hold more positive attitudes towards unions, the qualitative component of this research argues that the challenges of organizing in a cross-class, cross-race union extend beyond racial and ethnic difference to issues of skill. This research, therefore, attempts to illustrate how a labor union in a right-to-work state navigates the intersection of race and skill in union campaigns.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2013-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2625</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2869&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>unions</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>organizing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>attitudes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>race</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>skill</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>solidarity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Arts and Humanities</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-3801</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-01-31T20:50:13Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Straightedge Subculture on the Internet: A Case Study</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Williams, James Patrick</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This dissertation is a case study analysis of the straightedge youth subculture on an Internet bulletin board system (forum), located on the worldwide web between September 2001 and May 2003. Ethnographic methods, including participant observation, e-focus groups, in-depth interviews, and qualitative content analysis are used to collect relevant data. Concepts from subcultural theory, identity and social identity/categorization theory are used throughout my analysis of the Straight Edge Discussion Forum to highlight cultural and social-psychological aspects of subculturally-based behavior and identity. Substantive chapters are divided as follows. First, the types of subcultural information available to subculture members and visitors of the straightedge website under investigation are described. Second, data are presented to demonstrate how three subcultural processes – style displays, affiliation, and boundary maintenance – occur through textual interaction in the forum. Third, I demonstrate that straightedge subculture is not comprised of a homogenous group, but rather of different member types. These member types are based on whether one uses the Internet to supplement participation in face-to-face straightedge culture versus reliance on the Internet as the sole means of subcultural participation. Fourth, subcultural norms are shown to be negotiated and contested through textual interaction between forum participants. The analysis informs sociological knowledge in three areas. It provides more detailed knowledge of straightedge by deconstructing the taken-for-granted meanings attached to subcultural norms. It suggests that the Internet serves as both medium and resource for subculturalists. Lastly, it shows how identity theory and social identity/categorization theories can be used in tandem to better illuminate subcultural identity processes.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2003-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2358</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3801&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4189</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-06-06T16:51:33Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Gender Ideology and Drinking Norms: Content Analysis of Alcohol Advertisements in Selected Magazines, 1973 to 1988</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Walker, Sherry Jo</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This content analysis compared gender-alcohol associations presented in alcohol advertisements in Ms. and Sports Illustrated from 1973 to 1988. Analysis focused on (1) changes in gender representations during a period of transitional female roles, (2) relative frequencies of cognitive and emotion-inducing themes appearing in sex specific alcohol advertising, and (3) drinking norms presented by alcohol advertisers during a period characterized by criticism of alcohol marketing.
Portrayals of women did not accurately reflect the actual employment status of women. Images of feminism were superficial portrayals of women imitating men (e.g., whiskey consumption) or presented feminists as decorative objects. From 1973 to 1988, alcohol ads in Ms. and Sports Illustrated increasingly presented gender stereotypes.  Women were defined by their relationships with men, whereas men were defined by their accomplishments.
In both magazines, for all sample years (i.e., 1973, 1982, 1988), emotion-inducing themes predominated. Personal satisfaction was the most frequent type of emotion-inducing appeal. Frequencies of other emotion-inducing themes suggested that different images were used to target a female versus a male market (e.g. elegance in Ms. and tradition in Sports Illustrated).
Comparison of normative messages revealed that alcohol ads in Ms. more often presented alcohol as a means of emotion-management, whereas alcohol ads in Sports Illustrated more often associated drinking with hazardous activities. In both magazines, images of heavy drinking were more frequent than images of moderation.
It was concluded that alcohol producers, and their advertisers, experimented with non-conventional gender portrayals only when it was presumed novel and/or profitable to do so. Moreover, representations of drinking (i.e., types of appeals and normative messages) apparently changed only when there were direct threats to the self-regulation of alcohol advertising.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1992-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2665</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4189&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4300</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-08-14T20:44:49Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Dialectics of Power and Dissent: A Study of the U.S. Army's Chemical Stockpile Disposal Program</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Davies, Carol Griffith</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This research is a study of power in contemporary American society which calls into question the assumptions of openness and permeability so cherished by the pluralists. Within a power framework, we explore the functional realities of government that illuminate why some powerful interests manage to prevail with some consistency, while the broad public is assigned to a lesser task. The context for the study is the U.S. Army's $ 11 billion dollar Chemical Stockpile Disposal Program (CSDP). The Army's decision to use on-site incineration for the destruction of the stockpile ignited a social movement in opposition. Employing participant observation and in-depth interviews, we analyze the citizen-led opposition movement that began at the Lexingtron-Bluegrass Army Depot (LBAD) in Kentucky, and the ambiguous role of the NEPA (National Environmental Policy Act) regulatory process. Using the 'three dimensions of power' framework formulated by Steven Lukes (1974) and extended by Gaventa (1980), and Bachrach and Baratz (1974), we uncovered patterns of power (i.e., &quot;hidden faces of power&quot;) that allowed the Army to exploit some issues and suppress others while all the time urging that citizens abide by &quot;the process.&quot; This was accomplished chiefly through the 'mobilization of bias', and propped up by a heavily-financed public relations campaign which emanates from the Pentagon. We conclude with some recommendations for what can be done to revitalize our moribund democracy.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1995-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2786</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4300&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4209</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-09-30T15:58:30Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Uncovering Latino Sex Trafficking in a New Destination Area: A Case Study</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Copley, Lauren Kimberlee</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The phenomenon of sex trafficking has gained significant public attention in the past few decades. The Trafficking Victims Protection Act of 2000 was passed by the United States’ Congress to provide increased federal penalties and victim services to address what was perceived as a growing social and crime problem. Research has shown that law informs the way that sex trafficking is dealt with in the criminal justice and social service systems and the ways that the crime, victims, and offenders are constructed in these processes. We know very little about how sex trafficking works on the ground in specific cases, specifically in regards to Latino sex trafficking. This research addresses these issues by examining how sex traffickers, victims, legal actors, and other stakeholders conceptualize sex trafficking and construct it as a social problem; how Latino sex trafficking is investigated and prosecuted; and how Latino sex trafficking is connected to the vulnerabilities of Latina women.
The federal prosecution of a Latino sex trafficking case in East Tennessee provided the opportunity for a multi-method case study of a specific Latino sex trafficking network operating in new (immigrant) destination areas. Data for this project was collected through direct observations, interviews with 12 legal and social service actors, and secondary data analysis of legal records. Findings from this research suggest the concepts of force, fraud, coercion, and agency are central to constructing sex trafficking, with the law recognizing only specific definitions of these concepts. The variability in the ways that victims, offenders, legal and social service actors conceptualize the victimization involved in sex trafficking highlight the constructed nature of the concepts of force, fraud, coercion, and agency. Further, law and strict legal definitions regarding sex trafficking constrain the recognition of the variability of victim experiences, specifically those of undocumented immigrant victims. Finally, legal actors’ construction of the crime of sex trafficking and victimhood influence case processing, the representation of victims and crime in court, case outcomes, and services available to victims. As a result of these findings, policy recommendations and directions for future research are suggested.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2813</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4209&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sex Trafficking</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social Constructionism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Socio-legal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Criminology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4212</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-09-30T18:39:23Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Agent of Harm and Good Corporate Citizen? The Case of Tyson Foods</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Schally, Jennifer Lindmar</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Industrial agriculture inflicts major harms on nonhuman animals, the environment and human health.  How do agribusinesses culturally legitimize their harmful practices?  Utilizing critical discourse analysis, I clarify the ways in which one large agribusiness, Tyson Foods, disguises their actions while at the same time presents the image of a benign, good corporate citizen.  The discourses employed by Tyson gain legitimacy by drawing on and aligning with larger cultural discourses that are often taken for granted.  This research, situated at the intersection of green and cultural criminologies, makes a contribution to these as well as to the burgeoning social harm approach within criminology.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2856</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4212&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>critical criminology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>green criminology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>animal harm</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>critical discourse analysis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Criminology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4239</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-09-30T18:39:58Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Self, Society, and Environment in the 21st Century: The Development and Assessment of an Ecological Identity Scale</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Walton, Tobin N.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Through a mixed-methods approach, this dissertation develops and assesses a multi-item scale measure of ecological identity (EI). Although recent decades have seen increased attention devoted to research on identity in relation to nature and the bio-physical environment, a valid and reliable scale capable of encompassing the complexities of this construct has yet to be developed. This dissertation uses an integral approach to build upon and extend recent attempts to develop measures of similar constructs. Key facets of multiple theories and perspectives on identity are integrated into a unified framework capable of multi-level identity analysis. A rigorous statistical approach that combines a pre-test power analysis with information-theoretic techniques of multi-model comparison and inference reveal a highly reliable and valid scale. The Ecological Identity Scale (EIS scale) is shown to better explain pro-ecological behavior than measures of many of the other more established constructs in this area (e.g. worldviews, attitudes, norms). Once developed, the new EIS scale is integrated with several other social and psychological measures into an exploratory path model of pro-ecological behavior. Three top performing models with varying levels of complexity are identified and EI appears in each of them, further supporting the validity of the construct.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2871</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4239&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Ecological</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Identity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Behavior</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Environment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Social and Behavioral Sciences</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4148</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-10-01T17:26:52Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Using Audio/Visual Media to Increase the Sociological Imagination of an Adolescent Audience</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Phoenix, Jon Cariba</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Adolescence is a time of drastically increased sociological inequality. This thesis explores the possibility of using an educational sociology television show as a means to increase teen empowerment by developing their sociological imagination. After reviewing the causes of increased inequality during adolescence, I probe the link between sociology and empowerment by critiquing Mills’ conception of the sociological imagination. After finding his formulation incomplete, I use Bandura’s social cognitive theory to fill the gaps in the original framework and derive a new expanded sociological imagination focused on increasing efficacy. Efficacy is the social science construct most closely related to empowerment, and without an explicit focus on increasing it, highlighting the links between history and biography (Mills’ original concept) is very likely to cause resignation amongst substantial portions of students. The expanded sociological imagination’s focus on efficacy means that sociology instructors have to either provide mastery experiences or model for students how sociological knowledge can lead to better outcomes compared to a purely individualistic approach. I demonstrate how this can be done in a television program that follows entertainment-education best practices. I also use the expanded model to derive both a list of cognitive components that comprise sociological thinking and a skeletal storyline that can integrate sociology into a television program regardless of the amount of narrative. A case study that is attempting to integrate sociology and television is examined, followed by an exploration as to the type of research necessary to gauge the effectiveness of sociological edutainment programming. The thesis concludes with a discussion of how the E-SI might benefit undergraduate instruction of introductory sociology and its implications for ongoing efforts to bring sociology to high school.</dc:description>
<dc:date>2014-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2875</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4148&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>sociological imagination</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>edutainment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>sociology education</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>efficacy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>sociological thinking</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>educational television</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Educational Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4340</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-10-06T20:23:02Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Energy Attitudes, Beliefs and Behavior: A Specification of Situational and Personal Determinants of Residential Conservation Behavior</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hand, Carl Michael</dc:creator>
<dc:description>This dissertation examines the nature and extent of residential energy conservation behavior as well as consumers' view of the energy problem. The primary policy question raised by this research has been to clarify the link between energy attitudes, beliefs and conservation actions performed in the home context as a basis for furthering energy policies directed at encouraging residential energy conservation. Despite a plethora of such studies, research findings have failed to provide an unequivocal understanding of the role of consumer energy attitudes and beliefs in guiding behavior.
Theoretical basis for this research is drawn from attitude theory, particularly recent discussions of the attitude-behavior problem in social psychology. Two recent attitude-behavior models are examined in detail: (1) Fishbein and Ajzen's theory of &quot;reasoned action&quot; based upon an informational processing model of behavior, and (2) Triandis's multicomponent model which assumes the latter perspectives well as elements of both symbolic interactionist and behaviorist traditions. Although the models are similar in how they conceptualize social behavior, they differ considerably with respect to the actor's degree of volitional control over behavior they assume. Predicting conservation behaviors, which manifest marked differences in term of such control, time and resources required of the individual, provided an appropriate test case to examine the validity of either model's approach. To clarify the analysis, three general classes of conservation behavior were constructed: (1) curtailment activities--which involve a limitation of energy services, (2) efficiency behaviors--which make better use of energy services, and (3) efficiency improvements--which involve home retrofit and appliance change.
Utilizing data from a mail survey of Knoxville area residents (N=286), the results indicate that the majority of individuals have made at least moderate efforts to conserve energy. Such efforts usually entailed some curtailment of energy use (primarily turning the thermostat down), more efficient use of appliances and additional insulation and weatherstripping. Overall the relationship to consumer energy attitudes and beliefs is moderate although consistent. The best cognitive predictors of behavior tend to be attitudes toward specific actions as well as beliefs about the outcomes of those behaviors; i.e., their expected utility. While this finding suggests that definitions of the energy problem are not strongly linked to behavior, such general beliefs are instrumental in shaping more proximate attitudinal and belief determinants.
A comparison of the two models suggests that their predictive power is equivalent when the behavior requires only consumer motivation to perform (e.g., turning down the thermostat). As the behavior becomes more constrained by resource and opportunity factors, the utility of either model diminishes. The Triandis model is clearly superior under such circumstances as it includes measures of &quot;facilitation&quot; factors--such as perceived difficulty of the behavior and behavior relevant knowledge, constraining behavioral choices. By incorporating resource and opportunity factors affecting behavior, the Triandis model provides a broader based theoretical model for understanding behaviors of sociological interest.
Several policy implications are discussed. Programs endeavoring to promote conservation should first encourage a broader based view of the energy problem. A more integrated view of energy issues could be instrumental in providing a receptivity to specific appeals to conserve. Second, programs should target specific behaviors for change as well as normative beliefs and attitudes toward those behaviors. Third, providing practical knowledge for saving energy in the individual's residential context could encourage behavior, at least for some types of conservation activity.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1986-06-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2914</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4340&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4291</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-10-27T17:15:52Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>County Jails in Tennessee: A Survey of Forty-five County Jails</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Wilson, Rollin Virginius</dc:creator>
<dc:description>De Tocqueville has said, &quot;The American county jail is the worst prison in the world.&quot; The system of county jails has grown up with little interest or attention on the part of the citizens of the state of Tennessee. Some have contended that any sort of prison is too good for the criminal, but the public does not realize that thousands who are innocent, are detained annually in these jails to await trial. Moreover, no man is guilty under the law until he is convicted in the courts.
The county jail, which creates one of our greatest social problems, can only be reformed through educational processes. Citizens of the State of Tennessee, their officials and the local authorities in the ninety-five counties of the state must be awakened to an adequate conception and understanding of the jail problem before any reforms can be attempted.
It is not the purpose of the writer to suggest a general reformation but his analysis is an attempt to illustrate graphically the construction of the county jail, how the jail is administered, and the treatment of its prisoners. The precepts of humanity charge society with the care of its defectives and from a humane standpoint, we should not confine persons in places which will injure them physically or morally. The conditions revealed are probably no worse than those existing in other states yet are nothing of which may be justly proud. However, the work has been done and the information compiles in a friendly and helpful spirit and it is hoped that this study may serve in some small way the cause of thousands of unfortunates who may be in the future confined in the county jails of Tennessee.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1926-01-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2911</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4291&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4322</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-11-04T19:04:24Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>An Examination of the Relationship Between Kindred Connected­ness and the Riesman Inner-Other Directedness</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Wadford, Judith Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The purpose of this study is to investigate the family as a socializing agency from the standpoint of a possible relationship between kindred connectedness and inner-other direction.
The concept of kindred connectedness, developed by Whiteside and used in this study, is defined as the degree to which kin are bound to­gether by mutual assistance, affective support, and commonly held values and norms. Whiteside argues that persons from a close kindred have been socialized to be more sensitive to the expectations of others than persons from a non-close kindred.
There have been numerous attempts to develop empirical measures of the dimensions involved in Riesman's inner-other typology of personality. Research in this area has shown inner-other directedness to be related to susceptibility to influence from others, socioeconomic status, age, and sex. However, most of these studies have assumed that inner- and· other-direction form poles of a single dimension. Peterson takes ex­ception to this approach and conceptualizes inner-other direction as cells in a property-space model. Inner-other direction is defined by affiliation-achievement, introversion-extroversion, external conformity­ individuality, and the like.
It is hypothesized that subjects from high connected families are more likely to be other-directed and subjects from low connected families are more likely to be inner-directed. It should follow that high connected subjects would show more of the characteristics defined as other-directed on the Peterson I-0 scale while the reverse should be true for low connected respondents .
The measure of kindred connectedness is developed from a matrix analysis of visits between each member of the respondent ' s relatives . Quartile distributions are developed for the kindred connectedness scores.
The measure of inner-other direction is a modification of the measure used by Peterson. Four factor and seven factor summary scales are developed from the individual factors of the I-0 scale as well as summated scales for the individual factors. Quartile distributions are developed for the scales.
A convenience sample of 692 students on the Knoxville Campus of The University of Tennessee was taken during the Spring and Summer of 1967. Questionnaires were administered to the students in lower level sociology classes and one of the women's dorms on the campus .
Analysis of the data was conducted through use of the card sorting machine and the IBM 7040 computer. The X^2 test of association was used for statistical analysis.
The results of the study do not support the hypothesized relationship nor the direction of the relationship between kindred connectedness and inner-other direction. The data show a tendency toward other-direction for low connected respondents and inner-direction for high connected respondents. Although the first three factors of the Peterson I-0 scale are related to kindred connectedness at the .05 level, the relationship between kindred connectedness and all of the first four factors of the Peterson I-0 scale are in the opposite direction from that hypothesized .
Discussion as to what might have affected the outcome of the study included the question of the adequacy of visitation as a sufficient index of kindred connectedness, sensitivity as an outgrowth of high kindred connectedness, the homogeneity of the sample, and the restrictions on the number of measures due to limits of time and space. In an attempt to ex­plain the unexpected findings, a theoretical rationale was developed in­volving the relationship among kindred connectedness, dependency, and inner-other direction. A replication of the study is suggested, incorporating these factors.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1969-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2924</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4322&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4369</identifier>
		<datestamp>2014-12-08T22:26:59Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Changes in Social and Economic Status of People in Sullivan County for a Thirty Year Period</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Chase, Lewis I.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Purpose of Study: The purpose of this study is to indicate some of the more important trends in Sullivan County, largely within the last thirty years. Whenever it has been difficult to get information indicating trends then it has been necessary to present conditions without adequate foundational information to indicate trends.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1936-08-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2993</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4369&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4419</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-01-08T18:18:28Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>School Attendance, Absenteeism and Withdrawal: A Sociological Analysis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Bogert, John Martin</dc:creator>
<dc:description>In recent years, considerable interest in the phenomenon of absenteeism has been expressed by sociologists.  Most of the work in this area has been confined to the industrial situation.  In our present model-testing experiment, we wish to compare high school attendance with an industrial model.
The high school chosen to represent our model was the Mountain Grove Senior High School, Mountain Grove, Missouri.  This particular school was chosen because of the availability of excellent records.  The school records were of extreme significance as they represent the primary source of data used to construct our high school model.  The only other source of data was lengthy, unstructured interviews with Ronald Compton, principal of the institution.  Is is quite unfortunate that time and budget did not permit interview and testing of the subjects in social and psychological phases not covered by school records.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1962-05-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3041</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4419&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4443</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-01-13T21:20:54Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Religious Education in Prisons</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Gwin, John L.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The problem of crime is one of growing importance, and every means available should be used to reform and train the prisoner so that when he leaves the penitentiary he will go out and become a useful member of society.  The average age of American prisoners is nineteen years.  This means that after a few years most of our prisoners will re-enter society, and certainly it must be possible to do much to help these young people to readjust themselves to our social order.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1938-06-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3064</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4443&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4478</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-01-16T21:30:09Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Changing Male Role? An Empirical Analysis</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Stallings, Floyd M.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>The purpose of this project was threefold: first, to review and critique a body of literature on the male sex role, and specifically the male liberation literature; second, to present a discussion of social psychological concepts pertinent to the topic of the male sex role which are often absent in the literature; and third, to conduct an exploratory study to determine if the behaviors and attitudes of the men interviewed were consistent with the themes expounded in the literature.
An open-ended interview schedule based on themes in the male sex role literature was developed.  Thirty middle class, married males between the ages of 20 and 30 years were chosen through the process of snowball sampling.
The interview data supported some of the themes but failed to support others.  In most cases the findings showed that the assertions in the male sex role literature have been overstated and oversimplified.  For example, while most men agreed that men generally have trouble expressing emotions, a large percentage indicated that they personally could freely expression their emotions.  Although most of the subjects stated that they had in the past felt the pressure to prove their masculinity, most indicated that it was not a constant consideration.  Other themes received similar qualified support.  The various findings in this study suggest that men hold conflicting views about what is masculine and what is appropriate behavior.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1976-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3097</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4478&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4607</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-01-20T18:10:01Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Doing Crime: An Analysis of Repetitive Property Offenders' Decision-Making</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Tunnell, Kenneth D.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Over the past two decades social theory and research have focused increasingly on issues of criminal decision-making and deterrence. This inter-disciplinary movement draws from criminology, economics, and psychology, which share common assumptions that point toward a model of rational decision-making. Each body of thought considers criminal decision-making as being no different than non-criminal decision-making. Deciding whether to commit a crime is considered a &quot;decision problem,&quot; a unique one no less, but a decision that is resolved similarly to other decision problems.
The central objective of my research is to enhance our understanding of decision-making, specifically individual career criminal decision-making about whether or not to commit a crime, various alternatives considered in the decision problem, and influences on the decision processes.
This dissertation reviews literature on decision-making processes as explicated by perceptual deterrence, economic, and cognitive decision-making theories. They serve as theoretical guidance for this research. I then review previous research on perceptual deterrence and criminal decision-making processes and suggest that both merits or rational decision-making theory and proposed modification of it are debated with little empirical guidance.
A purposive sample of 60 adult male repetitive offenders incarcerated in the Tennessee Department of Corrections was selected and interviewed at two different points in time. The interviews focused on each subject's criminal calculus, i.e., their decision-making processes. The findings provide a description of criminal decision-making from which typologies of decision-making were constructed. Offenders were separated into Type I and Type II lambda categories, based on offense frequency, resulting in the following typological constructs: (1) the Type I lambda offender; (2) the non-drug-addicted Type II lambda offender; (3) the drug-addicted Type II lambda offender; (4) the hustling Type II lambda offender.
The major conclusion of the study is that criminals do not engage in rational decision-making. The especially do not weigh the possible legal consequences of their actions. Negative consequences are far less influential than positive consequences. This conclusion has implications for deterrence and decision-making theories in that they may not explain adequately the decisions made by repetitive property criminals. The research also addresses the question of offense specialization. My findings are at odds with those who argue for a &quot;generalist&quot; position suggesting that specialization does occur when criminal activities are viewed over time. Theoretical and methodological suggestions for future research of this nature are offered.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1988-12-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3095</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4607&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_graddiss-4740</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-02-27T21:19:53Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_graddiss</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>Social Psychological and Hormonal Correlates of Alcohol Consumption: A Psychobiological Study of Social Behavior</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Tuchfeld, Barry S.</dc:creator>
<dc:description>Statement of the Problem: The present study is concerned with social psychological and hormonal correlates of alcohol consumption among males in a social setting. In particular, the focus is on self-concept factors and two steroid hormones, testosterone and cortisol. Self-concept is viewed as a multi-dimensional construct which includes &quot;self-esteem&quot; and &quot;self-evaluation.&quot; the construct of &quot;social anxiety&quot; is introduced as a conceptual link between self-concepts and the selected steroids.
While no literature was found which relates directly to the specific research topic, a conceptual scheme is presented which attempts to integrate indirectly related and often tangential research findings into a quasi-explanatory sketch. This sketch is used to sensitize the analysis to the possible interrelationships that are suggested by prior research. The proposed variables are then viewed simultaneously in an effort to predict alcohol consumption. Pearson's r correlations are analyzed as an initial step to the predictive portion of the study.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1974-08-01T07:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3260</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4740&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Doctoral Dissertations</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record><record>
	<header>
		<identifier>oai:trace.tennessee.edu:utk_gradthes-4752</identifier>
		<datestamp>2015-04-10T21:47:03Z</datestamp>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-artsscin</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk_gradthes</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-soco</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-coll</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:utk-grad</setSpec>
				<setSpec>publication:socioetds</setSpec>
			</header>
	<metadata>
		<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
			<dc:title>The Effect of Pittman Center on the Community Life</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Hall, Russell</dc:creator>
<dc:description>It can be said very definitely that the school has done a good work of the conventional type in the educational field.  It has, without a doubt, changed the moral and religious life of the people for the better.  It is furnishing some needed recreation for the young people.  It is also doing good work in the medical care and prevention of disease.  All of these enterprises are handicapped, however, by the great economic problem which has not been solved and has hardly been attacked.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1939-08-01T08:00:00Z</dc:date>
<dc:type>text</dc:type>
<dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3312</dc:identifier>
<dc:identifier>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4752&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Masters Theses</dc:source>
<dc:publisher>Trace: Tennessee Research and Creative Exchange</dc:publisher>

<dc:subject>Sociology</dc:subject>

		</oai_dc:dc>
	</metadata>
</record>
</repository>
